<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Betrixaban" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Betrixaban</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Betrixaban</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Betaxolol" document-type="chapter">Betaxolol</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Bevacizumab" document-type="chapter">Bevacizumab (Antineoplastic)</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Betrixaban.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Betrixaban.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Betrixaban is an oral anticoagulant and direct inhibitor of factor Xa which is used to decrease the risk of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolus in hospitalized patients at high risk for venous thromboses. Betrixaban has been linked to a low rate of serum aminotransferase elevations during therapy, but has not been linked to instances of clinically apparent liver injury.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Betrixaban.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Betrixaban (be trix' a ban) is an orally available, small molecule direct inhibitor of coagulation factor Xa (-xaban), the rate controlling last step in the generation of thrombin, the final intermediate in blood coagulation. Inhibiting thrombin prevents the conversion of fibrinogen to fibrin and subsequent cross linking of fibrin monomers, platelet activation and amplification of coagulation. Clinical trials have also shown that betrixaban therapy can decrease the risk of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism in patients undergoing hip or knee replacement surgery or hospitalized with an acute medical illness that places them at high risk for thromboembolism. Betrixaban was approved for use in the United States in 2017 for prophylaxis of thromboembolism in high risk patients. Betrixaban is available in 40 and 80 mg capsules under the commercial name Bevyxxa. The recommended dose is an initial single dose of 160 mg on day 1 followed by 80 mg once daily for 35 to 42 days. Lower doses are recommended for patients with renal dysfunction. Unlike warfarin, betrixaban and the other oral direct thrombin and factor Xa inhibitors do not require monitoring of bleeding time or INR. Side effects are not common, but can include bleeding, headache, dizziness, fatigue, gastrointestinal upset, nausea, arthralgias and rash. Uncommon, but potentially severe adverse events include severe bleeding episodes and hypersensitivity reactions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Betrixaban.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>In prelicensing studies, serum aminotransferase elevations of greater than 3 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) occurred in 1% to 2% of betrixaban-treated patients and in a similar proportion of control subjects treated with enoxaparin. Similarly, aminotransferase levels rose to above 5 times ULN in 0.6% of betrixaban and 0.4% of enoxaparin treated control subjects. Aminotransferase elevations with jaundice arose in &#x0003c;0.2% of patients in both groups and all cases appeared to be due to heart disease and congestive liver injury and unrelated to the anticoagulants used. Since approval and more widespread use, there have been no reports of clinically apparent liver injury due to betrixaban. On the other hand, other direct factor Xa inhibitors, such as apixaban and rivaroxaban, have been linked to rare instances of idiosyncratic liver injury, generally arising within days or a few weeks of starting and presenting with a mild-to-moderate hepatocellular injury without prominent immunoallergic and autoimmune features. This syndrome has not been reported with betrixaban.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: E* (unproven but suspected rare cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Betrixaban.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The causes of the mild serum aminotransferase elevations during betrixaban therapy are unknown. Betrixaban has minimal hepatic metabolism and has no drug-drug interactions with substrates or modulators the cytochrome P450 system, but is a substrate of P-glycoprotein, potent inhibitors of which (such as amiodarone, azithromycin, clarithromycin, verapamil, ketoconazole) can cause elevated levels of betrixaban, increasing the risk of bleeding.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Betrixaban.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>Betrixaban has been associated with mild, asymptomatic and self-limited elevations in serum aminotransferases but not with hepatitis with jaundice. There have been no reports of fulminant hepatic failure attributed to betrixaban or cases of chronic hepatitis or vanishing bile duct syndrome. In some instances, patients with acute liver injury due to one direct factor Xa inhibitor (rivaroxaban) have tolerated another (apixaban) without recurrence of liver abnormalities.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Anticoagulants">Antithrombotic Agents</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Anticoagulants">Anticoagulants</related-object></p>
          <p>Other Drugs in the Subclass, Anticoagulants, Factor Xa Antagonists: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Apixaban">Apixaban</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Edoxaban">Edoxaban</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Fondaparinux">Fondaparinux</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Rivaroxaban">Rivaroxaban</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Betrixaban.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Betrixaban.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Betrixaban &#x02013; Generic, Bevyxxa&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antithrombotic Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=Betrixaban">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Betrixaban.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTUR">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Betrixaban.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Betrixaban</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://135203225">330942-05-7</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C23-H22-Cl-N5-O3</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Betrixaban.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Betrixaban_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Betrixaban Chemical Structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Betrixaban.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 11 April 2019</p>
        <ref-list id="Betrixaban.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Platelet aggregation inhibitors. Drugs used in cardiovascular disease. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 639-42.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of hepatotoxicity published in 1999 well before the availability of betrixaban and the direct Factor Xa inhibitors).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">De Marzio DH, Navarro VJ. Antiplatelet agents. Hepatotoxicity of cardiovascular and antidiabetic drugs: antihypertensives. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013, p. 527-8.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of cardiovascular drugs does not discuss the anticoagulants).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hogg K, Weitz JI. Blood coagulation and anticoagulant, fibrinolytic, and antiplatelet drugs. In, Brunton LL, Hilal-Dandan R, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 13th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2018, pp. 585-604.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cder/daf/">https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cder/daf/</ext-link>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(FDA Drug Approvals website that has product labels [package inserts], letters of approval and full FDA scientific review of the new drug application for safety and efficacy; mentions that rates of serum aminotransferase elevations during betrixaban therapy were similar to rates in patients treated with comparator anticoagulants [1.7% vs 1.5%] and the rare instances of clinically apparent liver injury with jaundice were all attributable to other causes such as heart failure and bacterial sepsis).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
            </mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Turpie AG, Bauer KA, Davidson BL, Fisher WD, Gent M, Huo MH, Sinha U, et al.; EXPERT Study Group. A randomized evaluation of betrixaban, an oral factor Xa inhibitor, for prevention of thromboembolic events after total knee replacement (EXPERT). Thromb Haemost 2009; 101: 68-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 215 patients undergoing knee replacement surgery treated with betrixaban [15 or 40 mg twice daily] or enoxaparin [30 mg sc every 12 hours] for 10-14 days, venous thromboembolism was more frequent with betrixaban [15% and 20%] than enoxaparin [10%]; no mention of ALT elevations or hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19132191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reuben A, Koch DG, Lee WM; Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Drug-induced acute liver failure: results of a U.S. multicenter, prospective study. Hepatology 2010; 52: 2065-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1198 patients with acute liver failure enrolled in a US prospective study between 1998 and 2007, 133 were attributed to drug induced liver injury, but none were due to anticoagulants).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Caldeira D, Barra M, Santos AT, de Abreu D, Pinto FJ, Ferreira JJ, Costa J. Risk of drug-induced liver injury with the new oral anticoagulants: systematic review and meta-analysis. Heart 2014; 100: 550-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of 29 controlled trials of oral anticoagulants in 152,116 patients focusing on risk of drug induced liver injury [including 7 trials with 22,992 patients on apixaban] found no increase in rate of serum ALT or AST elevations above 3 times ULN [1.0% vs 1.2%], or combined enzyme and bilirubin elevations above 2 times ULN [both 0.2%] with apixaban therapy compared to control patients on standard therapy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24476812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liakoni E, R&#x000e4;tz Bravo AE, Kr&#x000e4;henb&#x000fc;hl S. Hepatotoxicity of new oral anticoagulants (NOACs). Drug Saf 2015; 38: 711-20. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of evidence of hepatotoxicity of new oral anticoagulants including rivaroxaban, apixaban, edoxaban and dabigatran found 22 cases of liver injury due to rivaroxaban, 2 dabigatran, 2 apixaban, but none to edoxaban).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26138527</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anastasia EJ, Rosenstein RS, Bergsman JA, Parra D. Use of apixaban after development of suspected rivaroxaban-induced hepatic steatosis; a case report. Blood Coagul Fibrinolysis 2015; 26: 699-702. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(67 year old man developed ALT elevations 6 months after starting rivaroxaban [peak ALT 391 U/L, Alk P 120 U/L, bilirubin 1.3 mg/dL], which fell into the normal range within 2 months of switching to apixaban; ultrasound suggested fatty liver which also resolved with stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26154612</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52.e7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, two cases were attributed to anticoagulants(prasugrel and dalteparin), but none to direct factor Xa antagonists).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cohen AT, Harrington RA, Goldhaber SZ, Hull RD, Wiens BL, Gold A, Hernandez AF, Gibson CM; APEX Investigators. Extended thromboprophylaxis with betrixaban in acutely ill medical patients. N Engl J Med 2016; 375: 534-44. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 7513 patients hospitalized with acute medical illness and at risk of venous thromboembolism treated with betrixaban [80 mg daily for 35-42 days] or enoxaparin [40 mg sc once daily for 10-14 days], evidence of venous thromboembolism was found in 69% on betrixaban and 8.5% on enoxaparin; no mention of ALT elevations or hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27232649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Garland SG, DeRemer CE, Smith SM, Gums JG. Betrixaban: a new oral factor Xa inhibitor for extended venous thromboembolism prophylaxis in high-risk hospitalized patients. Ann Pharmacother 2018; 52: 554-61. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the pharmacology, clinical efficacy and safety of betrixaban; no mention of ALT elevations or hepatoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29338293</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Comparison table: some oral anticoagulants for VTE. Med Lett Drugs Ther 2018; 60 (1542): e51-e54. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Table of oral anticoagulants used for VTE compares, indications, doses, adverse events and special issues; mentions adverse events of aminotransferase elevations for apixaban, edoxaban, rivaroxaban but not betrixaban or dabagatran).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29537394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Betrixaban (Bevyxxa) for VTE prophylaxis in acute medical illness. Med Lett Drugs Ther 2018; 60 (1537): 4-5. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of the currently approved drugs for prevention of venous thromboembolism and the clinical efficacy, safety and costs of betrixaban; no mention of ALT elevations or hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29294463</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Betrixaban.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drugs for treatment and prevention of venous thromboembolism. Med Lett Drugs Ther 2018; 60: 41-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of drugs approved for venous thromboembolism; mentions that betrixaban is approved for prophylaxis only and not treatment; no mention of hepatic side effects).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29537392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Betrixaban.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Betrixaban/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Betrixaban: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Betrixaban">Trials on Betrixaban: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
