<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Clorazepate" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Clorazepate</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Clorazepate</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Clopidogrel" document-type="chapter">Clopidogrel</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Clotrimazole" document-type="chapter">Clotrimazole</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Clorazepate.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Clorazepate.Introduction">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p content-type="pubmed-excerpt">Clorazepate is a benzodiazepine used as an anticonvulsant as adjunctive therapy in management of epilepsy and as an anxiolytic for therapy of anxiety and alcohol withdrawal. Therapy with clorazepate is not associated with serum aminotransferase elevations, and cases of clinically apparent liver injury from clorazepate have been reported but are very rare.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Clorazepate.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Clorazepate (klor az' e pate) is a benzodiazepine with particular activity against spread of seizure activity in several animal models. The antiseizure activity of the benzodiazepines is mediated by their ability to enhance gamma-aminobutryic acid (GABA) mediated inhibition of synaptic transmission through binding to the GABA A receptor. Clorazepate is used both as an anticonvulsant and anxiolytic agent. Clorazepate was approved in the United States in 1972 and currently more than 3 million prescriptions are filled yearly. Current indications are as adjunctive therapy in management of partial seizures and for treatment of anxiety disorders and acute alcohol withdrawal. Clorazepate is available in generic forms and under the brand name Tranxene in tablets and capsules in concentrations of 3.75, 7.5, 11.25, 15 and 22.5 mg. Delayed release formulations are also available. The recommended initial dose for adults with seizures is 7.5 mg three times daily, with gradual dose increases generally to an average dose of 30 to 60 mg daily and not in excess of 90 mg daily. Common side effects of clorazepate include drowsiness, lethargy, ataxia, dysarthria and dizziness. Tolerance develops to these side effects, but tolerance can also develop to the therapeutic effects.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Clorazepate.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Clorazepate, as with other benzodiazepines, is rarely associated with serum ALT elevations, and clinically apparent liver injury from clorazepate is extremely rare. A few only partially convincing case reports of acute hepatocellular injury from clorazepate have been reported. Rare instances of drug induced liver injury have been reported with other benzodiazepines, such as chlordiazepoxide, diazepam, flurazepam, triazolam and alprazolam. In benzodiazepine related cases of acute liver injury, the latency has ranged from a few weeks to 6 months; the typical pattern of liver enzyme elevations has been cholestatic or mixed, but instances of hepatocellular patterns have also been reported. The injury is usually mild to moderate in severity and self-limited. Fever and rash have not been described nor has autoantibody formation.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: D (possible but rare cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Clorazepate.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The liver injury from benzodiazepines is probably due to a rarely produced intermediate metabolite.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Clorazepate.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>The few case reports of hepatic injury due to clorazepate were followed by complete recovery. No cases of acute liver failure or vanishing bile duct injury due to clorazepate have been described. There is no information about cross reactivity with other benzodiazepines (clonazepam, lorazepam or diazepam), but some degree of cross sensitivity should be assumed.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Anticonvulsants">Anticonvulsants</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="BenzodiazepineDrugs">Benzodiazepines</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Clorazepate.CASE_REPORT">
        <title>CASE REPORT</title>
        <sec id="Clorazepate.Case_1._Acute_hepatitis-like">
          <title>Case 1. Acute hepatitis-like injury due to clorazepate.</title>
          <p>[Modified from: Parker JLW. Potassium clorazepate (Tranxene)-induced jaundice. Postgrad Med J 1979; 55: 908-910. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/44913">PubMed Citation</ext-link>]</p>
          <p>A 27 year old man developed jaundice and fever, 2 months after starting clorazepate (15 mg increasing 30 mg once daily) for depression. He had poor appetite and had lost 9.5 kilograms since starting the drug. Clorazepate was continued for another two months, at which time he was found to have jaundice and hepatomegaly. Blood tests showed total bilirubin of 8.6 mg/dL, ALT 880 U/L, AST 620 U/L, GGT 104 U/L (normal &#x0003c;45) and alkaline phosphatase 29 KA units (normal &#x0003c;13). He had no rash, fever or eosinophilia and autoantibodies were negative. Clorazepate was stopped. He underwent three liver biopsies over the next five months showing an acute cholestatic hepatitis with gradual resolution, but residual minimal portal lymphocytic infiltrates and thin portal-to-portal fibrosis.</p>
          <sec id="Clorazepate.Key_Points">
            <title>Key Points</title>
            <table-wrap id="Clorazepate.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clorazepate</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Pattern:</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatocellular (R=16)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Severity:</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+ (jaundice and hospitalization)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Latency:</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 months</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Recovery:</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete recovery over 5 months</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Other:</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None mentioned</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Clorazepate.Comment">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>Acute hepatitis with cholestatic feature arose between 2 and 4 months after starting clorazepate. The pattern of liver enzyme elevations suggested hepatocellular injury. Liver biopsies showed mild fibrosis that was still present five months later. Tests to exclude hepatitis A and B were not done and tests for hepatitis C were not available when this case was reported.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Clorazepate.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Clorazepate.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Clorazepate &#x02013; Tranxene&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Anticonvulsants</p>
          <p>
            <bold>COMPLETE LABELING</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Clorazepate.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTU">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Clorazepate.T2" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clorazepate<break/> Dipotassium</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://135004253">57109-90-7</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C16-H10-Cl-N4-O3.K.H-K-O</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Clorazepate.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Clorazepate_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Clorazepate chemical structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Clorazepate.REFERENCES">
        <title>REFERENCES</title>
        <p>References updated: 25 January 2017</p>
        <ref-list id="Clorazepate.REFERENCES.reflist0">
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Benzodiazepines. Psychotropic and anticonvulsant agents. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 491-3.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of benzodiazepines and liver injury published in 1999; mentions rare instances of cholestatic hepatitis have been reported due to alprazolam, chlordiazepoxide, clonazepam, diazepam, flurazepam, and triazolam, and hepatocellular injury with clorazepate, but no reports of hepatic injury with lorazepam, oxazepam or temazepam).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Larrey D, Ripault M-P. Benzodiazepines. Hepatotoxicity of psychotropic drugs and drugs of abuse. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013, p. 455.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of drug induced liver injury mentions that there have been rare instances of acute liver injury [usually cholestatic] reported with alprazolam, bentazepam, chlordiazepoxide, clonazepam, clorazepate, clotiazepam, diazepam, flurazepam, and triazolam; a hepatitis-like pattern was reported with alprazolam and diazepam).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pirmohamed M, Leeder SJ. Anticonvulsant agents. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013: pp 423-42.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of anticonvulsant induced liver injury; benzodiazepines are not discussed).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McNamara JO. Pharmacology of the epilepsies. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman&#x02019;s the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 583-607.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mihic SJ, Harris RA. Hypnotics and sedatives. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 457-80.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Parker JLW. Potassium clorazepate(Tranxene)-induced jaundice. Postgrad Med J 1979; 55: 908-10. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(27 year old man developed jaundice, pruritus and fever, 2 months after starting clorazepate [bilirubin 7.6 mg/dL, ALT 880 U/L, Alk P 2.3 times ULN] and had 3 liver biopsies done over 5 months showing intrahepatic cholestasis with thin portal-portal fibrosis septae that persisted as cholestasis and inflammation resolved).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">44913</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bonkowsky HL, Sinclair PR, Emery S, Sinclair JF. Seizure management in acute hepatic porphyria: risks of valproate and clonazepam. Neurology 1980; 30: 588-92. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(38 year old man with acute intermittent porphyria and seizures did not respond to clonazepam, and testing in chicken embryos showed that it increased hepatic prophyrins and ALA synthase activity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6770287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">D&#x000f8;ssing M, Andreasen PB. Drug-induced liver disease in Denmark. An analysis of 572 cases of hepatotoxicity reported to the Danish Board of Adverse Reactions to Drugs. Scand J Gastroenterol 1982; 17: 205-11. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Among 572 cases of hepatotoxicity reported to a Danish registry between 1968 and 1978, 97 were due to psychotropic agents, but only two attributed to benzodiazepines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6982502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ker&#x000e4;nen T, Sivenius J. Side effects of carbamazepine, valproate and clonazepam during long-term treatment of epilepsy. Acta Neurol Scand Suppl 1983; 97: 69-80. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Clonazepam has many dose related sedative side effects, but compared to carbamazepine and valproate, few serious or long term side effects; no mention of hepatic side effects of clonazepam).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6424398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Davion T, Capron-Chivrac D, Andrejak M, Capron JP. [Hepatitis due to antiepileptic agents] Gastroenterol Clin Biol 1985; 9: 117-26. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of anticonvulsants; among benzodiazepines, cases of cholestatic hepatitis have been linked to chlordiazepoxide and diazepam, but liver injury from this class of drugs is rare).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3920108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Olsson R, Zettergren L. Anticonvulsant-induced liver damage. Am J Gastroenterol 1988; 83: 576-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (30 year old man developed fever, rash and jaundice 6 weeks after starting phenytoin; he was switched to carbamazepine and clonazepam, but redeveloped jaundice 3 months later; resolved with stopping, but recurred with restarting clonazepam alone [bilirubin 1.8 mg/dL, ALT 1380 U/L, Alk P 176 U/L] without rash, fever or eosinophilia; resolving in 6 weeks of stopping clonazepam).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3364416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Suzuki A, Aso K, Ariyoshi C, Ishimaru M. Acute intermittent porphyria and epilepsy: safety of clonazepam. Epilepsia 1992; 33: 108-11. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (13 year old girl with acute intermittent porphyria worsened on valproate and on phenytoin therapy, but clonazepam led to control of seizures and no worsening of porphyria).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1733741</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wallace SJ. A comparative review of the adverse effects of anticonvulsants in children with epilepsy. Drug Saf 1996; 15: 378-93. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review; ALT elevations occur in 4% of children on phenytoin, 6% on valproate, 1% on carbamazepine; &#x0201c;No child taking&#x02026; benzodiazepines had raised liver enzyme levels,&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8968693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lewis JH, Zimmerman HJ. Drug- and chemical-induced cholestasis. Clin Liver Dis 1999; 3: 433-64, vii. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of drug induced cholestatic syndromes, listing many causes including chlordiazepoxide and flurazepam; &#x0201c;Benzodiazepines may cause cholestatic injury, although this is rare&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11291233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Selim K, Kaplowitz N. Hepatotoxicity of psychotropic drugs. Hepatology 1999; 29: 1347-51. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of phenothiazines, butyrophenones, tricyclics, MAO inhibitors, acetylcholesterase inhibitors, and psychotropic drugs of abuse; &#x0201c;benzodiazepines&#x02026;have a very low hepatotoxic potential, with only case reports in the literature, usually with a cholestatic pattern).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10216114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russo MW, Galanko JA, Shrestha R, Fried MW, Watkins P. Liver transplantation for acute liver failure from drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Liver Transpl 2004; 10: 1018-23. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among ~50,000 liver transplants done in the US between 1990 and 2002, 137 [0.2%] were done for idiosyncratic drug induced acute liver failure, of which 10 were attributed to phenytoin, 10 to valproate and 1 to carbamazepine, but none to benzodiazepines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15390328</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson E, Jerlstad P, Bergqvist A, Olsson R. Fulminant drug-induced hepatic failure leading to death or liver transplantation in Sweden. Scand J Gastroenterol 2005; 40: 1095-101. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(36 years of reporting to Swedish registry identified 103 cases of acute liver failure due to drugs, of which 1 was attributed to phenytoin, 1 to valproate and 1 to carbamazepine, but none to benzodiazepines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16165719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gil-Martin A, Saez-Royuela F, Arias L, Angulo ML, Nogal B. [Hepatic fibrosis after antidepressant treatment] Rev Esp Enferm Dig 2005; 97: 461-2. Spanish. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (32 year old woman developed pruritis and jaundice 1-2 months after starting sertraline, aprazolam and clorazepate, resolving with stopping sertraline, but had persistent minor ALT elevations and biopsy showing mild bridging fibrosis 4 months later).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16048430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Andrade RJ, Lucena MI, Kaplowitz N, Garc&#x000ed;a-Mu&#x00146;oz B, Borraz Y, Pachkoria K, Garc&#x000ed;a-Cort&#x000e9;s M, et al. Outcome of acute idiosyncratic drug-induced liver injury: Long-term follow-up in a hepatotoxicity registry. Hepatology. 2006; 44: 1581-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(28 of 493 [5.7%] cases of drug induced liver disease had evidence of chronicity, including 3 cases due to bentazepam and one with clorazepate, the latter with recovery at 25 months).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17133470</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sabat&#x000e9; M, Ib&#x000e1;&#x000f1;ez L, P&#x000e9;rez E, Vidal X, Buti M, Xiol X, Mas A, et al. Risk of acute liver injury associated with the use of drugs: a multicentre population survey. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2007; 25: 1401-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 126 cases of drug induced liver injury seen in Spain between 1993-2000, 20 were attributed to benzodiazepines including 5 for clorazepate, 5 alprazolam, 6 lorazepam and 4 diazepam, but compared to controls, relative risk of injury was increased only for clorazepate [8.3: estimated frequency 3.4 per 100,000 person-year exposures]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17539979</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Fontana RJ, Bonkovsky HL, Watkins PB, Davern T, Serrano J, Yang H, Rochon J; Drug Induced Liver Injury Network (DILIN). Causes, clinical features, and outcomes from a prospective study of drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Gastroenterology 2008; 135: 1924-34. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 300 cases of drug induced liver disease in the US collected from 2004 to 2008, none were attributed to a benzodiazepine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson E. Hepatotoxicity associated with antiepileptic drugs. Acta Neurol Scand 2008; 118: 281-90. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of all anticonvulsants focusing upon phenytoin, valproate, carbamazepine; &#x0201c;Furthermore, hepatoxicity has not been convincingly shown to be associated with the use of benzodiazepines&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18341684</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ferrajolo C, Capuano A, Verhamme KM, Schuemie M, Rossi F, Stricker BH, Sturkenboom MC. Drug-induced hepatic injury in children: a case/non-case study of suspected adverse drug reactions in VigiBase. Br J Clin Pharmacol 2010; 70: 721-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Worldwide pharmacovigilance database contained 9036 hepatic adverse drug reactions in children; benzodiazepines were not among the top 40 agents implicated).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21039766</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reuben A, Koch DG, Lee WM; Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Drug-induced acute liver failure: results of a U.S. multicenter, prospective study. Hepatology 2010; 52: 2065-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1198 patients with acute liver failure enrolled in a US prospective study between 1998 and 2007, 133 were attributed to drug induced liver injury, but none were linked to benzodiazepine use).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wick JY. The history of benzodiazepines. Consult Pharm 2013; 28: 538-48. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (History of the development, approval, widescale use and eventual restriction and decrease in use of the benzodiazepines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24007886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES, Bergmann OM, Bj&#x000f6;rnsson HK, Kvaran RB, Olafsson S. Incidence, presentation and outcomes in patients with drug-induced liver injury in the general population of Iceland. Gastroenterology 2013; 144: 1419-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In a population based study of drug induced liver injury from Iceland, 96 cases were identified over a 2 year period, but none were linked to benzodiazepines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America. An analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of literature of drug induced liver injury in Latin American countries published from 1996 to 2012 identified 176 cases, but none were attributed to a benzodiazepine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Clorazepate.R28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, 40 [4.5%] were attributed to anticonvulsants, but none to benzodiazepine anticonvulsants).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Clorazepate.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(clorazepate/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Clorazepate: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=clorazepate">Trials on Clorazepate: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
