<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Fluphenazine" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Fluphenazine</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Fluphenazine</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2018</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Fluoxetine" document-type="chapter">Fluoxetine</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Flurazepam" document-type="chapter">Flurazepam</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Fluphenazine.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Fluphenazine.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Fluphenazine is a phenothiazine and antipsychotic agent which is no longer in common use. Fluphenazine can cause mild and transient serum enzyme elevations and has been linked to rare instances of clinically apparent cholestatic liver injury.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Fluphenazine.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Fluphenazine (floo fen' a zeen) is a tricyclic aliphatic phenothiazine which acts by postsynaptic inhibition of dopamine receptors. Fluphenazine has other peripheral and central nervous system effects, producing both alpha adrenergic stimulation and blocking histamine- and serotonin-mediated effects. Fluphenazine was approved in the United States in 1972 for use in the therapy of acute and chronic psychosis. It was formerly a commonly prescribed antipsychotic medication, but in recent years has been replaced in large part by the atypical antipsychotics, which have fewer extrapyramidal side effects. Fluphenazine is currently used as parentral therapy of psychosis and is available generically in solution for depot injection. Fluphenazine was previously available under the brand name Prolixin. The typical maintenance dose in adults in 12.5 to 25 mg im or sc every 3 to 6 weeks. Common side effects include drowsiness, dizziness, headache, blurred vision, dry mouth, constipation, tremor, restlessness, muscle spasms and weight gain. Rare but potentially severe adverse effects include suicidal thoughts or behaviors, neuroleptic malignant syndrome and tardive dyskinesia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Fluphenazine.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Liver test abnormalities have been reported to occur in up to 40% of patients on long term therapy with phenothiazines, but elevations are uncommonly above 3 times the upper limit of normal. The aminotransferase abnormalities are usually mild, asymptomatic and transient, reversing even with continuation of medication. Several instances of clinically apparent acute liver injury have been reported due to fluphenazine, which have resembled the liver injury caused by chlorpromazine and other phenothiazines. The onset of phenothiazide-related jaundice is usually within 1 to 4 weeks, and the pattern of serum enzyme elevations is typically cholestatic or mixed. Immunoallergic features (fever, rash and eosinophilia) are present in some cases, but they are usually mild and self-limited; autoantibodies are rare. Most importantly, phenothiazide induced jaundice can be prolonged and associated with vanishing bile duct syndrome. All phenothiazine antipsychotic agents are probably capable of causing cholestatic liver injury, but the frequency of hepatotoxicity appears to be far greater with chlorpromazine than with others such as fluphenazine.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: C (probable cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Fluphenazine.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The mechanism by which fluphenazine and other phenothiazines cause serum aminotransferase elevations is not known. Many aspects of the clinical presentation of phenothiazine hepatotoxicity (short latency period, fever, eosinophilia) suggest a hypersensitivity reaction, and rechallenge typically causes a rapid recurrence of injury. Fluphenazine is extensively metabolized by the liver via sulfoxidation and oxidation, and some instances of serum aminotransferase elevations as well as more clinically apparent liver injury may be caused by production of a toxic intermediate of its metabolism.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Fluphenazine.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>The serum aminotransferase elevations that occur on fluphenazine therapy are usually self-limited and do not require dose modification or discontinuation of therapy. The acute cholestatic hepatitis caused by fluphenazine is typically self-limited and benign. While cases of prolonged jaundice and cholestasis have not been described with fluphenazine, many instances of vanishing bile duct syndrome have been attributed to other phenothiazides. Many patients with chronic cholestasis eventually improve but they often have persistent enzyme elevations and biliary cirrhosis. Fatalities from fluphenazine jaundice have not been reported. Rechallenge should be avoided. Patients with fluphenazine induced liver injury may have cross sensitivity to other phenothiazines, but generally tolerate the atypical antipsychotics.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="AntipsychoticAgents">Antipsychotic Agents</related-object></p>
          <p>Other Drugs in the Subclass, Phenothiazines: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Chlorpromazine">Chlorpromazine</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Perphenazine">Perphenazine</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Prochlorperazine">Prochlorperazine</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Thioridazine">Thioridazine</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Trifluoperazine">Trifluoperazine</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Fluphenazine.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Fluphenazine.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold> REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Fluphenazine &#x02013; Generic, Prolixin&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antipsychotic Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=Fluphenazine">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Fluphenazine.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCT">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Fluphenazine.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluphenazine</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://134971528">69-23-8</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C22-H26-F3-N3-O-S</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Fluphenazine.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Fluphenazine_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Fluphenazine Chemical Structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Fluphenazine.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 02 February 2018</p>
        <ref-list id="Fluphenazine.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Neuroleptic drugs. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 483-91.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of hepatotoxicity of neuroleptic drugs including chlorpromazine published in 1999; several hundred cases of jaundice related to chlorpromazine have been reported, usually cholestatic, arising after 1-5 weeks, often with fever and eosinophilia, sometimes causing vanishing bile duct syndrome; other phenothiazines have only rarely been linked to liver injury, except for prochlorperazine).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Larry D, Ripault MP. Hepatotoxicity of psychotropic drugs and drugs of abuse. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013, pp. 443-62.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of phenothiazine induced liver injury; liver enzyme elevations arise in up to 42% of patients treated with phenothiazines, and hundreds of cases of chlorpromazine jaundice have been published, frequency ~0.5-1%; onset in 2-5 weeks, usually with an acute cholestatic hepatitis with jaundice and pruritus; a prodrome of fever and abdominal pain is common; prolonged course in 7% but often benign; other phenothiazines including fluphenazine have been linked to liver injury similar to that of chlorpromazine, but with a lower frequency).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meyer JM. Pharmacotherapy of psychosis and mania. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman&#x02019;s the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 417-56.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Walters GM, Terrence C, Steckel R. Jaundice following administration of fluphenazine dihydrochloride. Am J Psychiatry 1963; 120: 81-2. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(29 year old woman developed rash 2 days after starting fluphenazine, followed by facial edema and then jaundice with a tender liver [bilirubin 4.7 mg/dL, Alk P ~3 times ULN], resolving within 2 weeks of stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13998698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McQueen EG. Toxic effects of phenothiazine tranquillizers. N Z Med J 1963; 62: 460-2. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the phenothiazines and their side effects; &#x0201c;Jaundice has occurred in about 1% of patients taking chlorpromazine, and also, although less frequently, in patients taking one of the more recently developed analogues&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14073060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Walker CO, Combes B. Biliary cirrhosis induced by chlorpromazine. Gastroenterology 1966; 51: 631-40. (<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">Two patients, a 32 year old woman and a 31 year old man developed persistent jaundice [&#x0003e;4 years], cholestasis and liver fibrosis 3 and 4 weeks after starting chlorpromazine; acute cholestatic hepatitis evolving into chronic form with biopsies showing cirrhosis and complications of portal hypertension).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5926937</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ishak KG, Irey NS. Hepatic injury associated with the phenothiazines. Clinicopathologic and follow-up study of 36 patients. Arch Pathol 1972; 93: 283-304. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of 36 liver biopsies of phenothiazine induced hepatotoxicity from the files of the Armed Forces Institute of Pathology; 33 were due to chlorpromazine, 3 prochlorperazine; mean onset 15 days, eosinophilia in 73%, mean bilirubin 12.4 mg/dL, Alk P ~8 fold elevated, ALT 146 U/L; 6 [17%] had prolonged course for 10-16 months).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5017281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nolen WA, B&#x000f6;rger J. Disturbances of liver function of long acting neuroleptic drugs. Pharmakopsychiatr Neuropsychopharmakol 1978; 11: 199-204. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Analysis of 39 patients receiving fluphenazine; abnormalities of thymol turbidity were common, small number had ALT elevations, but no details given).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">674355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Snyder S. Fluphenazine jaundice. Report of a case. Am J Gastroenterol 1980; 73: 336-40. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(19 year old woman developed jaundice within days of starting fluphenazine [bilirubin 3.9 mg/dL, AST 2660 U/L, Alk P 181 U/L], improving over the next 2 weeks, but with rise in AST with restarting [59 to 94 U/L], and ultimately falling to normal after stopping; patient had recent history of injection drug use and report predated availability of tests for hepatitis C).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7416129</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">D&#x000f8;ssing M, Andreasen PB. Drug-induced liver disease in Denmark. An analysis of 572 cases of hepatotoxicity reported to the Danish Board of Adverse Reactions to Drugs. Scand J Gastroenterol 1982; 17: 205-11. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 572 cases of drug induced liver disease seen between 1968-78 in Denmark, 51 were attributed to chlorpromazine [9%, ranking 2nd behind halothane], latency averaging 14 days [range 11-46]; 5 deaths; no mention of fluphenazine or other phenothiazines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6982502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kennedy P. Liver cross-sensitivity to antipsychotic drugs. Br J Psychiatry 1983; 143: 312. 6138114.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(26 year old man with schizophrenia developed jaundice while on chlorpromazine [bilirubin 14.7 mg/dL, ALT 240 U/L, Alk P 294 U/L], had enzyme elevations within 2 weeks of starting haloperidol but then tolerated depixol [a thioxanthene antipsychotic not available in the US] long term). </italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6138114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jones JK, Van de Carr SW, Zimmerman H, Leroy A. Hepatotoxicity associated with phenothiazines. Psychopharmacol Bull 1983; 19: 24-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Analysis of several health databases for rates of hepatotoxicity and prescription drug use suggested that all categories of phenothiazides are associated with liver injury, being more common in persons under the age of 50 and not limited to chlorpromazine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6131467</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Holt RJ. Fluphenazine decanoate-induced cholestatic jaundice and thrombocytopenia. Pharmacotherapy 1984; 4: 227-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(30 year old man developed abdominal pain and fever ~9 months after starting intermittent fluphenazine [bilirubin 2.5 mg/dL, AST 173 U/L, Alk P 100 U/L, low platelet count], resolving rapidly with stopping fluphenazine; patient later tolerated haloperidol without liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6483640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kaplowitz N, Aw TY, Simon FR, Stolz A. Drug-induced hepatotoxicity. Ann Intern Med 1986; 104: 826-39. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of drug induced hepatotoxicity including phenothiazine induced jaundice).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3518564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Munyon WH, Salo R, Briones DF. Cytotoxic effects of neuroleptic drugs. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 1987; 91: 182-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In vitro assay for cytotoxicity of 8 neuroleptic drugs found that chlorpromazine was more toxic than haloperidol and loxapine, but similar to other phenothiazines including fluphenazine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2883697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Regal RE, Bili JE, Glazer HM. Phenothiazine-induced cholestatic jaundice. Clinical Pharmacy 1987; 6: 787-94. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of phenothiazine induced liver injury; cross sensitivity is rare &#x0201c;but does exist&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2905941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lok AS, Ng IO. Prochlorperazine-induced chronic cholestasis. J Hepatol 1988; 6: 369-73. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(68 year old man developed jaundice 4 weeks after starting prochlorperazine [peak bilirubin 26 mg/dL, ALT 50-90 U/L, Alk P 120-500 U/L], jaundice and pruritus persisting for more than a year, but then gradual clinical improvement but with persistent enzyme elevations, and biopsy 22 months after onset showed fibrosis and paucity of bile ducts).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3392386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pillans PI. Drug associated hepatic reactions in New Zealand: 21 years experience. NZ Med J 1996; 109: 315-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Over 21 year period in New Zealand, there were 943 adverse event reports of liver injury involving 205 drugs; chlorpromazine was in the top 20 drugs implicated accounting for 2.7% of cases; prochlorperazine was the cause of 4 cases, but other phenothiazines were not mentioned).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8816722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sabat&#x000e9; M, Ib&#x000e1;&#x000f1;ez L, P&#x000e9;rez E, Vidal X, Buti M, Xiol X, Mas A, et al. Risk of acute liver injury associated with the use of drugs: a multicentre population survey. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2007; 25: 1401-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 126 cases of drug induced liver injury seen in Spain between 1993-2000, 3 were due to chlorpromazine with relative risk of 613: frequency of 261 per 100,000 person year exposures; no mention of fluphenazine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17539979</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Aruna AS, Murungi JH. Fluphenazine-induced neuroleptic malignant syndrome in a schizophrenic patient. Ann Pharmacother 2005; 39: 1131-5. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(21 year old man developed fever, tremors, obtundation and tachycardia 7 days after an injection of fluphenazine while continuing thioridazine, haloperidol, lithium and carbamazepine [bilirubin normal, ALT 116 U/L, AST 410 U/L, CPK 36,696], resolving with intensive medical support; enzyme elevations likely from muscle).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15840734</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Fontana RJ, Bonkovsky HL, Watkins PB, Davern T, Serrano J, Yang H, Rochon J; Drug Induced Liver Injury Network (DILIN). Causes, clinical features, and outcomes from a prospective study of drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Gastroenterology 2008; 135: 1924-34. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 300 cases of drug induced liver disease in the US collected between 2004 and 2008, none were attributed to phenothiazines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reuben A, Koch DG, Lee WM; Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Drug-induced acute liver failure: results of a U.S. multicenter, prospective study. Hepatology 2010; 52: 2065-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1198 patients with acute liver failure enrolled in a US prospective study between 1998 and 2007, 133 were attributed to drug induced liver injury including 4 due to psychotropic agents; one each for quetiapine, nefazodone, fluoxetine and venlafaxine, but none for phenothiazines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Molleston JP, Fontana RJ, Lopez MJ, Kleiner DE, Gu J, Chalasani N; Drug-induced Liver Injury Network. Characteristics of idiosyncratic drug-induced liver injury in children: results from the DILIN prospective study. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr 2011; 53: 182-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 30 children with suspected drug induced liver injury, half [n=15] were due to antimicrobials [minocycline 4, INH 3, azithromycin 3] and the rest largely due to CNS agents and anticonvulsants; one case was attributed to perphenazine). </italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21788760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marwick KF, Taylor M, Walker SW. Antipsychotics and abnormal liver function tests: systematic review. Clin Neuropharmacol 2012; 35: 244-53. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of the literature found rates of any serum enzyme elevation during antipsychotic therapy to range from 5-78% and "clinically significant' elevations in 0-15%; lists 3 reports of clinically apparent liver injury due to fluphenazine, none of which were fatal [Holt 1984; Snyder 1980; Kennedy 1983]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22986798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drugs for psychiatric disorders. Treat Guidel Med Lett 2013; 11 (130): 53-64. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Concise review and recommendations on use of antidepressants and antipsychotic medications including fluphenazine; no discussion of hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23715100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES, Bergmann OM, Bj&#x000f6;rnsson HK, Kvaran RB, Olafsson S. Incidence, presentation and outcomes in patients with drug-induced liver injury in the general population of Iceland. Gastroenterology 2013; 144: 1419-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In a population based study of drug induced liver injury from Iceland, 96 cases were identified over a 2 year period including one non-fatal but icteric case due to chlorpromazine, but none to fluphenazine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America: an analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 176 reports of drug induced liver injury from Latin America published between 1996 and 2012, one non-fatal, but icteric case [from 2003] was attributed to chlorpromazine but none to fluphenazine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52.e7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, 5 [0.4%] were attributed to antipsychotic agents, including 3 to quetiapine and 2 olanzapine, but none phenothiazines such as fluphenazine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Fluphenazine.R29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drugs for psychotic disorders. Med Lett Drugs Ther 2016; 58 (1510): 160-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of medications available in the US for therapy of psychotic disorders; mentions fluphenazine, but does not discuss hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27960194</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Fluphenazine.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Fluphenazine/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Fluphenazine: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Fluphenazine">Trials on Fluphenazine: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
