<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="glossary" content-type="glossary" from-where="back" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="glossary">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">glossary</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Glossary</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="abbreviation" document-type="appendix">Abbreviations Used In LiverTox</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="resource" document-type="appendix">DILI Information Resources</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <def-list>
        <def-item id="glossary.acinus">
          <term>Acinus</term>
          <def>
            <p>The main structural unit of the liver seen under the microscope; each acinus includes liver cells, sinusoids, central and portal areas with blood vessels, lymphatics and bile ducts.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.acute-fatty-liver">
          <term>Acute fatty liver</term>
          <def>
            <p>Rapid accumulation of fat in the liver usually caused by alcohol or medications that interfere with fat metabolism. Rarely, this can occur in the last trimester of pregnancy.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.acute-liver-disease">
          <term>Acute liver disease</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver disease that is limited in duration, but usually with a sudden and symptomatic onset.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.acute-liver-failure">
          <term>Acute liver failure</term>
          <def>
            <p>Serious liver failure arising suddenly in a person without previous liver disease.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.acute-hepatic-necrosis">
          <term>Acute hepatic necrosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Sudden severe liver (hepatic) cell death (necrosis) that is typical of toxic injury to the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.adenoma">
          <term>Adenoma</term>
          <def>
            <p>A benign tumor of the liver that can grow large and rupture, causing internal bleeding.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.adenosine-triphosphate-atp-">
          <term>Adenosine triphosphate (ATP)</term>
          <def>
            <p>The molecule within cells used for energy reactions.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.alanine-aminotransferase-alt-">
          <term>Alanine aminotransferase (ALT)</term>
          <def>
            <p>An enzyme found in the blood that is elevated with liver injury, particularly hepatocellular (formerly SGPT). This is the most sensitive indicator of injury to the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.alkaline-phosphatase-alk-p-">
          <term>Alkaline phosphatase (Alk P)</term>
          <def>
            <p>An enzyme found in the blood that is elevated with liver injury, particularly cholestatic. This enzyme can also originate from other structures, like bone and bowel; if originating from the liver, other enzymes, such as the GGT, ALT, or liver fraction of the alkaline phosphatase will be abnormal.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.allogeneic">
          <term>Allogeneic</term>
          <def>
            <p>A transplant in which the recipient receives an organ or cells from another (usually related) person.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.aminotransferase">
          <term>Aminotransferase</term>
          <def>
            <p>One of two enzymes (alanine or aspartate aminotransferase: ALT and AST) found in the blood that, when elevated, are sensitive indicators of liver injury.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.anicteric">
          <term>Anicteric</term>
          <def>
            <p>Absence of jaundice (icterus).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.anorexia">
          <term>Anorexia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Loss of appetite.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.antinuclear-antibody">
          <term>Antinuclear antibody</term>
          <def>
            <p>An antibody found in blood directed against the nucleus of cells, typically present in patients with autoimmune hepatitis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.antismooth-muscle-antibody">
          <term>Anti-smooth muscle antibody</term>
          <def>
            <p>An antibody found in blood directed against smooth muscles, typically present in patients with autoimmune hepatitis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.apoptosis">
          <term>Apoptosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Programmed cell death which is typical of the liver cell injury from hepatitis, as opposed to necrosis which is typical of toxic injury or shock.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.ascites">
          <term>Ascites</term>
          <def>
            <p>Accumulation of fluid in the abdominal cavity, which is usually caused by acute or chronic liver failure.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.aspartate-aminotransferase-ast-">
          <term>Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)</term>
          <def>
            <p>An enzyme found in the blood that is elevated with liver injury, particularly hepatocellular (formerly SGOT). Although elevated in liver disease, the enzyme can originate from other organs and muscle.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.asterixis">
          <term>Asterixis</term>
          <def>
            <p>A jerking motion of the outstretched hands that is a sign of early stages of liver coma.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.autoantibodies">
          <term>Autoantibodies</term>
          <def>
            <p>Antibodies in the blood that are directed against normal body proteins or cells, such as antinuclear antibody or anti-smooth muscle antibody.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.autoimmune-features">
          <term>Autoimmune features</term>
          <def>
            <p>Findings suggestive of an overactive immune system, such as high antibody levels and "autoantibodies".</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.autoimmune-hepatitis">
          <term>Autoimmune hepatitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>A chronic liver disease in which an overactive immune system appears to damage the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.autologous">
          <term>Autologous</term>
          <def>
            <p>A transplant in which the recipient receives his/her own organ or cells.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.ballooning-degeneration">
          <term>Ballooning degeneration</term>
          <def>
            <p>A form of liver cell (hepatocyte) degeneration associated with cell swelling.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.benign-postoperative-cholestasis">
          <term>Benign postoperative cholestasis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Jaundice after major surgery that is temporary and resolves without treatment.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.bile-ducts">
          <term>Bile ducts</term>
          <def>
            <p>The small conduits (ducts) in the liver that allow the flow of bile from liver cells out through gradually larger bile ducts into the intestine.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.bilirubin">
          <term>Bilirubin</term>
          <def>
            <p>The chemical breakdown product of red blood cells that is normally removed by the liver and excreted in bile. Bilirubin can accumulate in the serum and lead to detectable jaundice when there is liver injury and dysfunction, obstruction to the flow of bile, or spontaneous red cell destruction (hemolysis).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.bland-cholestasis">
          <term>Bland cholestasis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Cholestatic liver injury with minimal or no inflammation in the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.bone-marrow-transplantation">
          <term>Bone marrow transplantation</term>
          <def>
            <p>Replacement of a person's bone marrow with that of another person, used to treat leukemia and other severe forms of cancer or genetic disease.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.buddchiari-syndrome">
          <term>Budd-Chiari syndrome</term>
          <def>
            <p>A severe liver disease caused by clotting and blockage of the large veins that drain the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.celiac-disease">
          <term>Celiac disease</term>
          <def>
            <p>An inherited disease of the small intestine caused by allergy to wheat (gliadin).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cerebral-edema">
          <term>Cerebral edema</term>
          <def>
            <p>Swelling of the brain due to accumulation of fluid, that can occur in liver failure.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cholangiography">
          <term>Cholangiography</term>
          <def>
            <p>An X-ray that shows the large bile ducts that drain bile from the liver into the intestine.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cholecystectomy">
          <term>Cholecystectomy</term>
          <def>
            <p>A surgical operation to remove the gallbladder.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cholecystitis">
          <term>Cholecystitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Inflammation of the gallbladder, typically causing fever, nausea, and abdominal pain.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.choledocholithiasis">
          <term>Choledocholithiasis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Gallstones which have passed into the bile ducts.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cholelithiasis">
          <term>Cholelithiasis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Gallstones in the gallbladder.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cholestatic-injury">
          <term>Cholestatic injury</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver injury in which interference with bile flow and jaundice are prominent.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cholesterol">
          <term>Cholesterol</term>
          <def>
            <p>The major form of fat in the body, most of which is produced in the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.chronic-liver-disease">
          <term>Chronic liver disease</term>
          <def>
            <p>Persistent, long term liver disease often with vague or mild symptoms and slow onset. Conventionally, disease has been present for more than 6 months.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.chronic-liver-failure">
          <term>Chronic liver failure</term>
          <def>
            <p>Serious liver failure arising gradually in a person with a chronic liver disease.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.cirrhosis">
          <term>Cirrhosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Scarring and permanent injury to the liver, usually the result of chronic, long term damage.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.clinical-phenotype">
          <term>Clinical phenotype</term>
          <def>
            <p>A pattern of clinical presentation and course of liver injury that is typical for a specific disease or injury from a specific medication.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.clinical-signs">
          <term>Clinical signs</term>
          <def>
            <p>Findings on physical examination such as rash, fever, enlarged or tender liver and jaundice.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.clinical-symptoms">
          <term>Clinical symptoms</term>
          <def>
            <p>Patient complaints such as fatigue, nausea, poor appetite, dark urine or yellow discoloration of the skin (jaundice).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.coagulopathy">
          <term>Coagulopathy</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormal bleeding tendency which can be caused by lack of clotting factors that are made by the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.collagen">
          <term>Collagen</term>
          <def>
            <p>The major protein found in scars and that is increased in cirrhosis of the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.dark-urine">
          <term>Dark urine</term>
          <def>
            <p>Dark or tea-colored urine is a symptom of liver disease caused by elevations in serum bilirubin and secretion of bilirubin in the urine.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.dietary-supplements">
          <term>Dietary Supplements</term>
          <def>
            <p>Dietary supplements contain one or more dietary ingredients such as vitamins, minerals, herbals or other botanicals, amino acids or organ extracts that are intended to supplement the diet.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.ductopenia">
          <term>Ductopenia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Finding on liver histology of a decrease or lack of small bile ducts in the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.ductules">
          <term>Ductules</term>
          <def>
            <p>The smallest bile ducts that can be seen on liver histology.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.edema">
          <term>Edema</term>
          <def>
            <p>Tissue swelling of the feet, ankles or other parts of the body caused by abnormal accumulation of fluid which can be the result of heart, kidney or liver failure.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.eosinophilia">
          <term>Eosinophilia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Increased eosinophils in the blood (the white blood cells that are active in allergic reactions).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.elastography">
          <term>Elastography</term>
          <def>
            <p>A noninvasive X-ray method of measuring stiffness of the liver, which is increased with advancing fibrosis and cirrhosis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.encephalopathy">
          <term>Encephalopathy</term>
          <def>
            <p>Mental confusion and altered level of consciousness that can occur in liver failure.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.endothelial-cell">
          <term>Endothelial cell</term>
          <def>
            <p>The cells in the liver that line the blood channels (sinusoids).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.esophagus">
          <term>Esophagus</term>
          <def>
            <p>The muscular swallowing tube that runs from the mouth to the stomach.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.fatty-acid">
          <term>Fatty acid</term>
          <def>
            <p>The breakdown product of triglycerides and fat that are taken up by the liver and used as a source of energy or to make triglycerides.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.fibrosis">
          <term>Fibrosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>The presence of scarring in the liver, usually shown by liver biopsy histology.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.focal-nodular-hyperplasia">
          <term>Focal nodular hyperplasia</term>
          <def>
            <p>A benign tumor of the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.gamma-glutamyl-transpeptidase-ggt-">
          <term>Gamma glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT)</term>
          <def>
            <p>An enzyme found in the blood that is elevated with liver injury, particularly cholestatic. This is also commonly elevated in recent alcohol consumption.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.glutathione">
          <term>Glutathione</term>
          <def>
            <p>A substance made in the liver that binds to and helps remove drugs and toxins.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.glycogen">
          <term>Glycogen</term>
          <def>
            <p>The principal storage form of glucose (sugar) in the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.granulomatous-hepatitis">
          <term>Granulomatous hepatitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver injury in which granulomas (small collections of inflammatory cells) are found in the liver biopsy.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.graves-disease">
          <term>Graves' disease</term>
          <def>
            <p>A disease of the thyroid (hyperthyroidism)</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatic-encephalopathy">
          <term>Hepatic encephalopathy</term>
          <def>
            <p>Confusion, mental dullness, drowsiness and even coma caused by liver failure.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatitis-a">
          <term>Hepatitis A</term>
          <def>
            <p>Infectious liver disease, spread primarily through the fecal-oral route, caused by the hepatitis A virus; now preventable by vaccine. Most people recover and the infection does not become chronic.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatitis-b">
          <term>Hepatitis B</term>
          <def>
            <p>Infectious liver disease caused by the hepatitis B virus, spread primarily through sexual contact or through perinatal (vertical) transmission; now preventable by vaccine. Approximately 5% of acute hepatitis B cases become chronic.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatitis-c">
          <term>Hepatitis C</term>
          <def>
            <p>Infectious liver disease caused by the hepatitis C virus for which there is no vaccine and which commonly becomes chronic; now the most common cause of cirrhosis in the United States.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatitis-d">
          <term>Hepatitis D</term>
          <def>
            <p>Rare but severe liver disease caused by the hepatitis D virus, which only affects persons who are also infected with hepatitis B.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatitis-e">
          <term>Hepatitis E</term>
          <def>
            <p>Infectious form of viral hepatitis that is rare in the United States but common in the developing world; may also be spread by contact with pigs or wild boar.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatocellular-injury">
          <term>Hepatocellular injury</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver injury in which liver cell damage and inflammation are prominent.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatocyte">
          <term>Hepatocyte</term>
          <def>
            <p>The major cells in the liver responsible for its function.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatotoxicity">
          <term>Hepatotoxicity</term>
          <def>
            <p>Toxin injury to the liver due to a medication, chemical, herbal or dietary supplement; another term for drug induced liver injury.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hemangioma">
          <term>Hemangioma</term>
          <def>
            <p>A benign tumor of the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hematopoietic-cell-transplantation">
          <term>Hematopoietic cell transplantation</term>
          <def>
            <p>Transplantation of blood elements such as bone marrow or stem cells.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatic-venous-pressure-gradient">
          <term>Hepatic venous pressure gradient</term>
          <def>
            <p>A diagnostic measurement of the pressure inside the veins of the liver that is increased in cirrhosis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hepatomegaly">
          <term>Hepatomegaly</term>
          <def>
            <p>Enlargement of the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hyperammonemia">
          <term>Hyperammonemia</term>
          <def>
            <p>High levels of ammonia in the blood which can occur in liver failure.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hyperlipidemia">
          <term>Hyperlipidemia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormally high levels of lipids (cholesterol, triglycerides) in the blood.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hyperthermia">
          <term>Hyperthermia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormally high body temperature, usually due to heat shock, which can cause liver injury.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hypotension">
          <term>Hypotension</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormally low blood pressure, which can cause liver injury (ischemic hepatitis).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.hypoxia">
          <term>Hypoxia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Low oxygen tension in the blood which can cause liver injury (ischemic hepatitis).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.icteric">
          <term>Icteric</term>
          <def>
            <p>Presence of jaundice, which is typically first evident in the whites of the eyes (sclera) followed by skin.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.icterus">
          <term>Icterus</term>
          <def>
            <p>Another name for jaundice, used to describe a yellowish tinge to the skin and eyes.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.idiopathic">
          <term>Idiopathic</term>
          <def>
            <p>A medical term meaning "of unknown cause".</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.immunoallergic-hepatitis">
          <term>Immunoallergic hepatitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver injury with prominent features of allergy or hypersensitivity. Typically, this includes fever, rash, and/or hives.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.immunoglobulin">
          <term>Immunoglobulin</term>
          <def>
            <p>A class of blood proteins that include antibodies.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.interlobular-bile-ducts">
          <term>Interlobular bile ducts</term>
          <def>
            <p>The larger bile ducts in the liver that allow the flow of bile from intralobular bile ducts to the larger bile ducts that, ultimately, direct bile to the gallbladder and intestine.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.intralobular-bile-ducts">
          <term>Intralobular bile ducts</term>
          <def>
            <p>The small conduits (ducts) in the liver than allow the flow of bile from liver cells to the larger, interlobular bile ducts.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.ischemic-hepatitis">
          <term>Ischemic hepatitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Severe hypotension (shock), lack of oxygen (anoxia), or sudden heart failure that leads to decreased blood flow to the liver; usually resolves quickly if the sudden insult is corrected.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.itching">
          <term>Itching</term>
          <def>
            <p>Irritating skin sensation that provokes scratching, a symptom of liver disease, particularly cholestatic (also known as "pruritus").</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.jaundice-of-sepsis">
          <term>Jaundice of sepsis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Jaundice occurring in the setting of severe bacterial infections (sepsis) that resolves if the infection in treated; liver biopsy shows prominent cholestasis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.jaundice">
          <term>Jaundice</term>
          <def>
            <p>Yellowish tinge to the skin or whites of the eyes caused by elevation in bilirubin in the blood; also called "icterus".</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.lactic-acidosis">
          <term>Lactic acidosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>High levels of lactic acid in the blood, usually caused by failure of mitochondrial function in the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.large-bile-ducts">
          <term>Large bile ducts</term>
          <def>
            <p>The bile ducts in the liver (right and left hepatic duct) and outside of the liver (common bile duct) allow the flow of bile to the gallbladder and intestine.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.latency">
          <term>Latency</term>
          <def>
            <p>The duration between ingestion, or exposure, to a drug, toxin, or infectious agent and the onset of disease.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.liver-histology">
          <term>Liver histology</term>
          <def>
            <p>Findings on microscopic assessment of a liver biopsy.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.liver-inflammation">
          <term>Liver inflammation</term>
          <def>
            <p>Findings of white blood cells (inflammatory cells) in the liver on microscopic assessment of a liver biopsy.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.liver-test-abnormalities">
          <term>Liver test abnormalities</term>
          <def>
            <p>Blood tests results that indicate liver injury such ALT, AST, alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin, albumin and prothrombin time (or INR).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.liver-transplantation">
          <term>Liver transplantation</term>
          <def>
            <p>Replacement of a person's liver with that of another person, used to treat end stage liver disease, acute liver failure, liver cancer and rare genetic disorders.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.lymphocyte">
          <term>Lymphocyte</term>
          <def>
            <p>A type of white blood cell that is responsible for immune responses.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.macrophage">
          <term>Macrophage</term>
          <def>
            <p>A large cell found in the liver that engulfs foreign material and takes part in inflammation.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.macrovesicular-fat">
          <term>Macrovesicular fat</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormal large droplets of fat found in liver cells; typically, the nucleus is pushed to one side of the cell by fat droplets.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.mallory-bodies">
          <term>Mallory bodies</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormal twisted rope-like bodies seen by microscope in fatty liver disease.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.matrix">
          <term>Matrix</term>
          <def>
            <p>The proteins that surround and support cells.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.microvesicular-fat">
          <term>Microvesicular fat</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormal numbers of small droplets of fat in liver cells; typically, the nucleus remains in the center of the cell.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.mitochondria">
          <term>Mitochondria</term>
          <def>
            <p>A component found in all living cells that is responsible for producing energy and is essential for health.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.mixed-injury">
          <term>Mixed injury</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver injury with features of both hepatocellular and cholestatic injury.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.monoclonal-antibody">
          <term>Monoclonal antibody</term>
          <def>
            <p>Antibodies produced in mice that are highly specific for a single protein or substance, which can be used to treat serious diseases such as cancer (rituximab) or arthritis (infliximab).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.mononucleosis">
          <term>Mononucleosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Acute illness caused by the Epstein Barr virus that can cause liver disease that resembles acute viral hepatitis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.mononucleosis_1">
          <term>Mononucleosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Acute illness caused by the Epstein Barr virus that can cause liver disease that resembles acute viral hepatitis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.m--v-scale">
          <term>M &#x00026; V Scale</term>
          <def>
            <p>A causality assessment method similar to RUCAM developed by Drs. Maria and Victorino.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.myeloablation">
          <term>Myeloablation</term>
          <def>
            <p>Deliberate destruction of the bone marrow by chemotherapy, done in preparation of bone marrow transplantation.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.myopathy">
          <term>Myopathy</term>
          <def>
            <p>Disease of the muscles.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.naranjo-scale">
          <term>Naranjo Scale</term>
          <def>
            <p>A causality assessment method for assessing all forms of drug induced adverse events.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.neuropathy">
          <term>Neuropathy</term>
          <def>
            <p>Disease of the brain, nerves or nervous system.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.neutropenia">
          <term>Neutropenia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Decrease in neutrophils, a white blood cell important in defense against infections.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.neutrophil">
          <term>Neutrophil</term>
          <def>
            <p>A white blood cell which is an important defense in bacterial infections.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.nodular-regenerative-hyperplasia">
          <term>Nodular regenerative hyperplasia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Unusual transformation of the normal liver structure into nodules. Typically, there is little or no scar tissue, differentiating this from cirrhosis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.nonparenchymal">
          <term>Nonparenchymal</term>
          <def>
            <p>A liver histology term referring to those parts of the liver other than the major hepatocytes (liver cells) including the endothelial cells, macrophages, veins, arteries and bile ducts.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.nystagmus">
          <term>Nystagmus</term>
          <def>
            <p>Involuntary jerking motion of the eyes that occurs with brain injury and liver coma.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.optic-neuritis">
          <term>Optic neuritis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Inflammation of the nerves of the eye, which can cause blindness.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.pancreatitis">
          <term>Pancreatitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Inflammation and injury of the pancreas.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.parenchymal">
          <term>Parenchymal</term>
          <def>
            <p>A liver histology term referring to the part of the liver with hepatocytes (liver cells) as opposed to the areas with supporting cells, veins, arteries and bile ducts.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.percutaneous-liver-biopsy">
          <term>Percutaneous liver biopsy</term>
          <def>
            <p>A liver biopsy that is done by passing a needle through the skin into the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.plasma-cell">
          <term>Plasma cell</term>
          <def>
            <p>A cell that makes antibodies, which is often found in liver inflammation caused by autoimmune reactions.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.portal-hypertension">
          <term>Portal hypertension</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormally increased pressure in the portal vein that delivers blood from the intestine to the liver, which is caused by cirrhosis and can result in bleeding and fluid retention (ascites).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.portal-inflammation">
          <term>Portal inflammation</term>
          <def>
            <p>Findings of inflammatory cells on liver biopsy in areas around the veins, arteries and bile ducts entering the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.primary-biliary-cirrhosis">
          <term>Primary biliary cirrhosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>A chronic liver disease marked by gradual autoimmune loss of bile ducts leading ultimately to cirrhosis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.primary-sclerosing-cholangitis">
          <term>Primary sclerosing cholangitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>A chronic autoimmune disease marked by damage and loss of the large bile ducts that can lead to liver damage and cirrhosis.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.prodromal">
          <term>Prodromal</term>
          <def>
            <p>In acute liver disease, the period of symptoms, frequently vague, immediately before appearance of jaundice.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.prognosis">
          <term>Prognosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Prediction or likelihood of an outcome (good or bad) of an illness.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.prothrombin-time">
          <term>Prothrombin time</term>
          <def>
            <p>A measure of clotting ability that becomes abnormal (prolonged) with liver failure.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.pruritus">
          <term>Pruritus</term>
          <def>
            <p>Itchiness of the skin, a symptom of liver disease, particularly cholestatic.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.radiomimetic">
          <term>Radio-mimetic</term>
          <def>
            <p>Resembling radiation effects.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.rechallenge">
          <term>Rechallenge</term>
          <def>
            <p>Reexposure, deliberate or accidental, of a patient to a medication that was believed to have caused an adverse side effect, such as drug induced liver injury.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.reticulin">
          <term>Reticulin</term>
          <def>
            <p>A stain used on liver biopsies to visualize elastic fibers.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.reyes-syndrome">
          <term>Reye's syndrome</term>
          <def>
            <p>An acute and severe liver disease of children that follows an acute viral illness and aspirin use.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.rucam">
          <term>RUCAM</term>
          <def>
            <p>The Roussel Uclaf Causality Assessment Method for evaluating the likelihood that a medication has caused drug induced liver injury.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.r-value">
          <term>R value</term>
          <def>
            <p>The ratio of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) to alkaline phosphatase (Alk P) values, both expressed as multiples of the upper limit of normal. An R value of &#x0003e;5.0 is used to define hepatocellular injury, R &#x0003c;2.0 as cholestatic injury, and R between 2.0 to 5.0 as mixed hepatocellular-cholestatic injury.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.sinusoids">
          <term>Sinusoids</term>
          <def>
            <p>The small passages between liver cells in which blood flows from the portal areas to the central veins.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.sinusoidalobstruction-syndrome-sos-">
          <term>Sinusoidal-obstruction syndrome (SOS)</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver histology findings indicating a blockage of blood flow out of the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.splenomegaly">
          <term>Splenomegaly</term>
          <def>
            <p>Enlargement of the spleen.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.status-epilepticus">
          <term>Status epilepticus</term>
          <def>
            <p>Persistent, uninterrupted seizures.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.steatohepatitis">
          <term>Steatohepatitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Excess fat with inflammation and damage in the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.steatosis">
          <term>Steatosis</term>
          <def>
            <p>An abnormal amount of fat in the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.stellate-cells">
          <term>Stellate cells</term>
          <def>
            <p>Fat storing cells in the liver that make collagen (fibrosis).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.stevensjohnson-syndrome">
          <term>Stevens-Johnson syndrome</term>
          <def>
            <p>Sudden onset of fever and severe body rash often due to an allergic reaction to a medication.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.synthesis">
          <term>Synthesis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Production or making of a substance.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.tachycardia">
          <term>Tachycardia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Rapid heart rate.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.tachypnea">
          <term>Tachypnea</term>
          <def>
            <p>Rapid breathing rate.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.thrombocytopenia">
          <term>Thrombocytopenia</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormal decrease in the numbers of blood platelets, which are small elements needed for clotting.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.transjugular-liver-biopsy">
          <term>Transjugular liver biopsy</term>
          <def>
            <p>A liver biopsy that is done by passing a needle in a flexible tube from a vein in the neck into the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.triglycerides">
          <term>Triglycerides</term>
          <def>
            <p>One of the major forms of fat that is produced in the liver and found in the blood.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.varices">
          <term>Varices</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abnormal, large veins that are found in the esophagus and intestine when there is portal hypertension.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.vanishing-bile-duct-syndrome-vbds-">
          <term>Vanishing bile duct syndrome (VBDS)</term>
          <def>
            <p>A chronic form of liver disease in which there is a gradual loss of small bile ducts in the liver (ductopenia).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.venoocclusive-disease-vod-">
          <term>Veno-occlusive disease (VOD)</term>
          <def>
            <p>Another term for "sinusoidal-obstruction syndrome" or liver histology findings indicating a blockage of blood flow out of the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.vinyl-chloride">
          <term>Vinyl chloride</term>
          <def>
            <p>Chemical used in manufacturing that can harm the liver.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.viral-hepatitis">
          <term>Viral hepatitis</term>
          <def>
            <p>Liver disease caused by one of 5 hepatitis viruses (A, B, C, D or E).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item id="glossary.wilson-disease">
          <term>Wilson disease</term>
          <def>
            <p>An inherited disease marked by accumulation of copper in the liver, brain and other tissues that can cause cirrhosis and be fatal if not detected early and treated.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
