<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Siponimod" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Siponimod</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Siponimod</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Simvastatin" document-type="chapter">Simvastatin</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Sirolimus" document-type="chapter">Sirolimus</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Siponimod.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Siponimod.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Siponimod is an orally available immunomodulatory drug used to treat relapsing forms of multiple sclerosis. Siponimod is associated with transient serum enzyme elevations during therapy but has not been linked to instances of clinically apparent liver injury with jaundice, although experience with its use has been limited.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Siponimod.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Siponimod (si pon&#x02019; i mod) is an immunomodulatory agent used in the treatment of multiple sclerosis that is believed to act by modulating sphingosine-1-phosphate (S1P) receptors. Siponimod is a derivative of myriocin, a metabolite of the fungus Isaria sinclairii and is a structural analogue of sphingosine. Related in structure to fingolimod, the first S1P receptor inhibitor approved for use in multiple sclerosis, siponimod appears to have greater selectivity of S1P receptors 1 and 5, and thus might have equivalent potency but fewer off-target side effects. Once phosphorylated intracellularly, siponimod acts as a S1P receptor antagonist which renders T and B cells insensitive to signals necessary for egress from lymphoid tissue. In animal models of multiple sclerosis, siponimod resulted in reduced recirculation of autoaggressive lymphocytes to the central nervous system. Subsequently, in several large, randomized controlled trials, siponimod was shown to reduce relapse rates and improve neuro-radiologic outcomes in adult patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis. Siponimod was approved for use in the United States in 2019 and is available in tablets of 0.25 and 2 mg under the brand name Mayzent. The recommended maintenance dose in adults is 2 mg orally once daily. Common side effects are lymphopenia, headache, diarrhea, cough, rhinorrhea and back and abdominal pain. Rare, but potentially severe adverse events include severe viral, bacterial or fungal infections, atrial arrhythmias and bradycardia, macular edema, decrease in pulmonary function, progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), and embryonal-fetal toxicity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Siponimod.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>In large controlled trials of siponimod in patients with multiple sclerosis, serum ALT elevations were common, typically arising during the first 3 months and persisting throughout the treatment period. The elevations were generally mild and asymptomatic, and they returned to baseline values within 3 months of stopping. Aminotransferase elevations above 3 times upper limit of normal (ULN) were reported in 6% to 8% of siponimod recipients compared to less than 2% of placebo recipients. In these prelicensure clinical trials, there were no cases of acute hepatitis or clinically apparent liver injury but elevations in liver tests led to discontinuation in 1% if subjects. Thus, mild-to-moderate and transient serum enzyme elevations during therapy are not uncommon, but clinically apparent liver injury with jaundice due to siponimod has not been reported, although the clinical experience with its use has been limited.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: E* (suspected but unproven cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Siponimod.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The mechanism by which siponimod might cause liver injury is not known. It is extensively metabolized by liver via the cytochrome P450 system, predominantly CYP 2C9 and 3A4 and drug-drug interactions with agents that induce or inhibit these enzymes are likely to occur.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Siponimod.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>While chronic therapy with siponimod can be associated with mild-to-moderate serum aminotransferase elevations, it has not been linked to any cases of clinically apparent liver injury. Because of the frequency of enzyme elevations detected during therapy, the product label for siponimod recommends obtaining baseline liver tests before initiation of treatment. However, no specific recommendations for monitoring liver tests during treatment have been made. There is no known cross sensitivity of the hepatic injury from siponimod with other agents used to treat multiple sclerosis. Because of the similarity in chemical structure and mechanism of action, there may be cross sensitivity to side effects with fingolimod.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="livertox" document-id="MultipleSclerosisAge" document-type="chapter">Multiple Sclerosis Agents</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Siponimod.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <p>
          <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Siponimod &#x02013; Mayzent&#x000ae;</p>
        <p>
          <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Multiple Sclerosis Agents</p>
        <p>
          <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/drugInfo.cfm?setid=44492772-5aed-4627-bd85-e8e89f308bb3">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
        </p>
        <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Siponimod.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTURE">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Siponimod.Tc" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NO</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_4" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siponimod</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://172113595">1230487-00-9</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C29-H35-F3-N2-O3</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Siponimod.Tc_1_1_1_4" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="ext-image-back-link" source-id="pubchem" document-id="172113595" document-id-type="sid" document-type="summary" object-id="172113595" object-id-type="sid" object-type="image"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Siponimod.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 13 January 2020</p>
        <ref-list id="Siponimod.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.zimmerman.1999">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Zimmerman HJ. Oncotherapeutic and immunosuppressive agents. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 697-8.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of hepatotoxicity published in 1999 before the availability of siponimod).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.kaplowitz.2013">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Multi-authored textbook of hepatotoxicity published in 2013 does not discuss the drugs for multiple sclerosis).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.krensky.2018">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Krensky AM, Azzi JR, Hafler DA. Immunotherapy for multiple sclerosis. Immunosuppressants and Tolerogens. In, Brunton LL, Halal-Dandan R, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 13th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2018, pp. 649-52.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">FDA: Center for Drug Evaluation and Research. 209884Orig1s000. Clinical Review(s). pp: 166-73.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="web">
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/nda/2019/209884Orig1s000MedR.pdf">
                <underline>https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/nda/2019/209884Orig1s000MedR.pdf</underline>
              </ext-link>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(FDA website with product labels and medical review of the efficacy and safety of siponimod; mentions that serum aminotransferase elevations are common during siponimod therapy occurring in almost half of patients but are typically mild and resolve rapidly with stopping and that serious hepatotoxicity was not encountered; ALT elevations above 3 times the ULN occurred in 6-8% of subjects).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
            </mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.kappos.2010.387">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kappos</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Radue</surname>
                  <given-names>EW</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>O'Connor</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Polman</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hohlfeld</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Calabresi</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Selmaj</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <etal/>
                <collab>FREEDOMS Study Group</collab>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>A placebo-controlled trial of oral fingolimod in relapsing multiple sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>N Engl J Med</source>
              <year>2010</year>
              <volume>362</volume>
              <fpage>387</fpage>
              <lpage>401</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Among 1272 patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis treated with fingolimod [0.5 or 1.25 mg daily] or placebo for 24 months, 8.5-12.5% of fingolimod, but only 1.7% of placebo recipients developed ALT elevations above 3 times ULN, and ALT levels fell to normal with or without discontinuation, and serum bilirubin levels did not change).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089952</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.cohen.2010.402">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cohen</surname>
                  <given-names>JA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Barkhof</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Comi</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hartung</surname>
                  <given-names>HP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Khatri</surname>
                  <given-names>BO</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Montalban</surname>
                  <given-names>X</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pelletier</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <etal/>
                <collab>TRANSFORMS Study Group</collab>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Oral fingolimod or intramuscular interferon for relapsing multiple sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>N Engl J Med</source>
              <year>2010</year>
              <volume>362</volume>
              <fpage>402</fpage>
              <lpage>15</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Among 1280 patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis treated with fingolimod [0.5 or 1.25 mg daily] or interferon beta [30 mg weekly] for 12 months, relapse rates were lower, but ALT elevations above 3 times ULN were more common with fingolimod [7% and 8%] than interferon beta [2%], although there were no clinically apparent episodes of liver injury).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089954</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF8">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <article-title>Oral fingolimod(gilenya) for multiple sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>Med Lett Drugs Ther</source>
              <year>2010</year>
              <volume>52</volume>
              <issue>1353-1354</issue>
              <fpage>98</fpage>
              <lpage>9</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of mechanism of action, efficacy, safety and costs of fingolimod shortly after is approval for use for multiple sclerosis in the US, mentions that common side effects are headache, cough, diarrhea, back pain and aminotransferase elevations; no mention of clinically apparent liver injury).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21344782</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF9">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <article-title>New drugs for relapsing multiple sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>Med Lett Drugs Ther</source>
              <year>2012</year>
              <volume>54</volume>
              <issue>1403</issue>
              <fpage>89</fpage>
              <lpage>91</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of efficacy, safety and costs of new disease modifying drugs for multiple sclerosis lists side effects in a table including "transaminase elevations" for interferon beta, fingolimod and teriflunomide and "hepatotoxicity" for natalizumab, but not for glatiramer or mitoxantrone).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23183318</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.oh.2013.591">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Oh</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>O'Connor</surname>
                  <given-names>PW</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of Oral Therapies for Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>CNS Drugs</source>
              <year>2013</year>
              <volume>27</volume>
              <fpage>591</fpage>
              <lpage>609</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Review of efficacy and safety or oral agents for multiple sclerosis, including fingolimod, teriflunomide, dimethyl fumarate, laquinimod and cladribine, none of which have raised major issues of hepatotoxicity).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23801528</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.kappos.2015.1582">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kappos</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <comment>O.Connor P, Radue E-W, Polman C, Hohlfeld R, Selmaj K, Ritter S, et al</comment>
              <article-title>Long-term effects of fingolimod in multiple sclerosis: the randomized FREEDOMS extension trial.</article-title>
              <source>Neurology</source>
              <year>2015</year>
              <volume>84</volume>
              <fpage>1582</fpage>
              <lpage>91</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Among 920 patients with multiple sclerosis enrolled in an extension study of fingolimod [0.5 vs 1.25 mg daily], beneficial effects were sustained and no new safety concerns arose, serum enzyme elevations occurring in 13% and 19% of subjects during the first and 7% and 8% during the second year of fingolimod therapy).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25795646</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.selmaj.2013.756">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Selmaj</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>DK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hartung</surname>
                  <given-names>HP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hemmer</surname>
                  <given-names>B</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kappos</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Freedman</surname>
                  <given-names>MS</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>St&#x000fc;ve</surname>
                  <given-names>O</given-names>
                </name>
                <etal/>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Siponimod for patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (BOLD): an adaptive, dose-ranging, randomised, phase 2 study.</article-title>
              <source>Lancet Neurol</source>
              <year>2013</year>
              <volume>12</volume>
              <fpage>756</fpage>
              <lpage>67</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Among 297 patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis treated with siponimod [0.25, 0.50,1.25, 2 or 10 mg] or placebo once daily for 6 months, there was a dose related increase in clinical responses and higher rates of adverse events including ALT elevations [0% to 6-8%], but levels were rarely above 3 times ULN and there were no hepatic serious adverse events).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23764350</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.english.2015.691">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>English</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Aloi</surname>
                  <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>New FDA-approved disease-modifying therapies for multiple sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>Clin Ther</source>
              <year>2015</year>
              <volume>37</volume>
              <fpage>691</fpage>
              <lpage>715</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of efficacy and safety of the newer disease modifying therapies of multiple sclerosis lists ALT elevations as adverse events associated with fingolimod, teriflunomide and dimethyl fumarate, but not peginterferon beta or alemtuzumab).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25846320</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.kappos.2016.1089">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kappos</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>DK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>St&#x000fc;ve</surname>
                  <given-names>O</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hartung</surname>
                  <given-names>HP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Freedman</surname>
                  <given-names>MS</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hemmer</surname>
                  <given-names>B</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rieckmann</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <etal/>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Safety and Efficacy of siponimod (BAF312) in patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis: dose-blinded, randomized extension of the phase 2 BOLD study.</article-title>
              <source>JAMA Neurol</source>
              <year>2016</year>
              <volume>73</volume>
              <fpage>1089</fpage>
              <lpage>98</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Among 252 patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis continued in an extension of a phase 2 study of siponimod [Selmaj 2013], there was a dose related increase in ALT elevations [2% to 17%] but there were no hepatic serious adverse events).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27380540</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.hammond.2016.1052">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hammond</surname>
                  <given-names>ER</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Perspectives on safety and efficacy-the BOLD phase 2 extension study of siponimod in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>JAMA Neurol</source>
              <year>2016</year>
              <volume>73</volume>
              <fpage>1052</fpage>
              <lpage>4</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Editorial in response to the analyses of efficacy and safety of siponimod in an extension study [Kappos 2016]).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27380179</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.shakerinejad.2017.41">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shakeri-Nejad</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Aslanis</surname>
                  <given-names>V</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Veldandi</surname>
                  <given-names>UK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gardin</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zaehringer</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dodman</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Su</surname>
                  <given-names>Z</given-names>
                </name>
                <etal/>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Pharmacokinetics, safety, and tolerability of siponimod (BAF312) in subjects with different levels of hepatic impairment: a single-dose, open-label, parallel-group study.</article-title>
              <source>Int J Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>
              <year>2017</year>
              <volume>55</volume>
              <fpage>41</fpage>
              <lpage>53</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Single dose studies of siponimod done in 40 subjects found little difference in pharmacokinetics among patients with or without hepatic impairment).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27443658</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.kappos.2018.1263">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kappos</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bar-Or</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cree</surname>
                  <given-names>BAC</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Fox</surname>
                  <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Giovannoni</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gold</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Vermersch</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <etal/>
                <collab>EXPAND Clinical Investigators</collab>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Siponimod versus placebo in secondary progressive multiple sclerosis (EXPAND): a double-blind, randomised, phase 3 study.</article-title>
              <source>Lancet</source>
              <year>2018</year>
              <volume>391</volume>
              <issue>10127</issue>
              <fpage>1263</fpage>
              <lpage>73</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Among 1645 patients with secondary progressive multiple sclerosis enrolled in a controlled trial for up to 3 years, disability progression was less frequent with siponimod than placebo [26% vs 32%] but liver related &#x0201c;investigations&#x0201d; were more common [12% vs 4%], although none resulted in clinically apparent liver injury with jaundice ).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29576505</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.jin.2018.455">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jin</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Borell</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gardin</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ufer</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Huth</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Camenisch</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>In vitro studies and in silico predictions of fluconazole and CYP2C9 genetic polymorphism impact on siponimod metabolism and pharmacokinetics.</article-title>
              <source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source>
              <year>2018</year>
              <volume>74</volume>
              <fpage>455</fpage>
              <lpage>64</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(In vitro metabolic studies using human liver microsomes demonstrated possible functional consequences of CYP2C9*2/*2 and CYP2C9*3/*3 polymorphisms on the metabolism of siponimod which predict significant reductions in clearance and possible drug accumulation to toxic levels).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29273968</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF19">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <article-title>Siponimod (Mayzent)--a new drug for multiple sclerosis.</article-title>
              <source>Med Lett Drugs Ther</source>
              <year>2019</year>
              <volume>61</volume>
              <issue>1571</issue>
              <fpage>70</fpage>
              <lpage>2</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of the mechanism of action, clinical efficacy, safety and costs of siponimod in comparison to other agents used to treat multiple sclerosis; mentions that serum aminotransferase elevations can occur with siponimod therapy and that patients should be tested for liver function tests and have CYP 2C9 genotype testing before starting treatment).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31169805</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Siponimod.REF.alsalama.2019.1009">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Al-Salama</surname>
                  <given-names>ZT</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Siponimod: First global approval.</article-title>
              <source>Drugs</source>
              <year>2019</year>
              <volume>79</volume>
              <fpage>1009</fpage>
              <lpage>15</lpage>
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">(Review of the mechanism of action, history of development, clinical efficacy and safety of siponimod; mentions the common side effects include headache, hypertension, aminotransferase elevations, peripheral edema, nausea, dizziness, diarrhea, bradycardia and musculoskeletal pain but that the aminotransferase levels were rarely severely elevated).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31144287</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="link-group" id="Siponimod.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Siponimod/AE)%20AND%20Human%5bMH%5d%20AND%20(drug%20induced%20liver%20injury%20OR%20jaundice/CI%20OR%20bile%20duct%20diseases/CI%20OR%20liver/DE%20OR%20liver%20diseases/CI)%20AND%20(%221900%5C%5C1%5C%5C1%22%5bEDat%5d:%222999%5C%5C12%5C%5C31%22%5bEDat%5d)">Recent References on Siponimod: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Siponimod">Trials on Siponimod: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
