<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Atorvastatin" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Atorvastatin</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Atorvastatin</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Atomoxetine" document-type="chapter">Atomoxetine</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Atovaquone" document-type="chapter">Atovaquone</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Atorvastatin.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Atorvastatin is a commonly used cholesterol lowering agent (statin) that is associated with mild, asymptomatic and self-limited serum aminotransferase elevations during therapy and rarely with clinically apparent acute liver injury.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Atorvastatin (a tor" va stat' in) is a potent, orally available inhibitor of hepatic 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A (HMG-CoA) reductase, the major rate-limiting enzyme in cholesterol synthesis. Like other members of its class (the &#x0201c;statins&#x0201d;), atorvastatin lowers total serum cholesterol and low density lipoprotein (LDL) concentrations, thereby reducing the risk of atherosclerosis and its complications &#x02013; myocardial infarction and stroke. Atorvastatin was approved for use in the United States in 1996 and has become one of the most commonly prescribed drugs in America, with more than 50 million prescriptions filled yearly. The current primary indication for atorvastatin is the treatment of hypercholesterolemia in persons at high risk for coronary, cerebrovascular and peripheral artery disease. Atorvastatin is available in tablets of 10, 20, 40 and 80 mg generically and under the trade name Lipitor, and is also available in combination with other cardiovascular agents such as amlodipine (Caduet). The recommended dose is 10 to 80 mg once daily based upon tolerability and lipid levels. Common side effects include muscle cramps, joint aches, headache, dyspepsia and weakness, symptoms that occur with all of the currently available statins.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Atorvastatin therapy is associated with mild, asymptomatic and usually transient serum aminotransferase elevations in 1% to 3% of patients but levels above 3 times ULN is less than 1%. In summary analyses of large scale studies with prospective monitoring, ALT elevations above 3 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) occurred in 0.7% of atorvastatin treated versus 0.3% of placebo recipients. These elevations were more common with higher doses of atorvastatin, being 2.3% with 80 mg daily. Most elevations were self-limited and did not require dose modification.</p>
          <p>Atorvastatin is also associated with frank, clinically apparent hepatic injury but this is rare, occurring in ~1:3000 to 1:5000 treated patients. The clinical presentation of atorvastatin hepatotoxicity varies greatly from simple cholestatic hepatitis, to mixed forms, to frankly hepatocellular injury. The latency to onset of injury is also highly variable ranging from 1 month to several years. However, most cases arise within 6 months of starting atorvastatin or several months after a dose escalation. The most common presentation is a cholestatic hepatitis that tends to be mild to moderate in severity and self-limiting in course (Cases 1 and 2). Atorvastatin hepatotoxicity can also present with a distinctly hepatocellular pattern of injury with marked elevations in serum aminotransferase levels and minimal or no increase in alkaline phosphatase. Rash, fever and eosinophilia are uncommon, but at least one-third of hepatocellular cases have features of autoimmunity, marked by high immunoglobulin levels, ANA positivity and liver biopsy findings of autoimmune hepatitis (Cases 3 and 4). These autoimmune cases usually resolve once atorvastatin is stopped, although they may require corticosteroid therapy for resolution. Strikingly, however, some cases of apparent autoimmune hepatitis caused by atorvastatin do not resolve with stopping the medication but are self-sustained and require long term immunosuppressive therapy. It is unclear whether these cases of persistent autoimmune hepatitis caused by the statin therapy or are triggered by statin in a susceptible host. Another possibility is that the association is coincidental and represents a de novo onset of autoimmune hepatitis in someone who happens to be taking a statin.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: A (well known cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The cause of hepatic injury from atorvastatin is unknown. Atorvastatin is largely metabolized in the liver via CYP 3A4 and excreted in bile. The mild, self-limited ALT elevations are likely due to a toxic intermediate of drug metabolism and the reversal of these elevations due to adaptation. The idiosyncratic, clinically apparent liver injury associated with atorvastatin has many features of autoimmunity and may be immune mediated. Other cases may be due to failure of adaptation.</p>
          <p>Because atorvastatin is metabolized by CYP 3A4, it is susceptible to many drug-drug and even drug-food and drug-herb interactions. Strong inhibitors of CYP 3A4 such as clarithromycin, ritonavir (and other HIV protease inhibitors], itraconazole, verapamil and grapefruit juice (high consumption) can increase atorvastatin levels and the dose should be kept to 20 mg daily or less. Cyclosporine, fibrates and niacin can increase the risk of mycopathy from atorvastatin. On the other hand, rifampin and other inducers of CYP 3A4 can decrease atorvastatin levels and efficacy. Drug induced liver injury from atorvastatin has sometimes occurred after long term use of the statin, but shortly after additions or discontinuations or modifications of other medications being taken.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>The mild ALT elevations associated with atorvastatin therapy are usually self-limited and do not require dose modification; atorvastatin should be stopped if ALT levels rise above 10-fold normal, or persist in being above 5-fold elevated or are associated with symptoms of liver injury. However, prospective monitoring of serum enzymes upon initiating atorvastatin therapy is no longer recommended. Clinically apparent liver injury attributed to atorvastatin is usually self-limited and recovery is complete within 1 to 4 months. Several instances of an autoimmune chronic hepatitis have been reported after atorvastatin therapy that required long term immunosuppressive therapy despite stopping atorvastatin, suggesting that the drug triggered an underlying predisposition to autoimmune hepatitis. In other instances, the liver disease ultimately resolved with stopping atorvastatin. In addition, rare instances of acute liver failure have been attributed to atorvastatin, but in these cases the role of atorvastatin in causing the hepatic injury was not always clear. In view of the wide scale use of atorvastatin, clinically apparent and severe liver injury is extraordinarily rare. Recurrence of injury with rechallenge has been reported and should be avoided. Switching therapy to another statin after atorvastatin induced injury is apparently safe, but few instances have been reported, and it should be done with careful monitoring for recurrence. In cases of autoimmune hepatitis-like injury, corticosteroids have been used but with unclear efficacy. If corticosteroids are used, the dose and duration of treatment should be kept to a minimum, and careful followed up after stopping is essential.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Lipid-LoweringAgents">Antilipemic Agents</related-object></p>
          <p>Other Drugs in the Subclass, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Statins">Statins</related-object>: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Ezetimibe">Ezetimibe [used in combination]</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Fluvastatin">Fluvastatin</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Lovastatin">Lovastatin</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Pitavastatin">Pitavastatin</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Pravastatin">Pravastatin</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Rosuvastatin">Rosuvastatin</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Simvastatin">Simvastatin</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Atorvastatin.CASE_REPORTS">
        <title>CASE REPORTS</title>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Case_1._Abnormal_serum_enzy">
          <title>Case 1. Abnormal serum enzymes arising during atorvastatin therapy.</title>
          <p>[Modified from: Gershovich OE, Lyman AE Jr. Liver function test abnormalities and pruritus in a patient treated with atorvastatin: case report and review of the literature. Pharmacotherapy 2004; 24: 150-4. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14740794">PubMed Citation</ext-link>]</p>
          <p>A 71 year old woman was found to have marked elevations in serum ALT and alkaline phosphatase 6 weeks after switching from simvastatin to atorvastatin (80 mg/day) for hyperlipidemia. Her serum ALT levels had been normal on simvastatin (Table). She was asymptomatic and serum bilirubin levels were normal. She had also been taking an herbal weight loss agent which was stopped at the same time as atorvastatin. Serum enzyme levels returned to normal and remained normal during subsequent lovastatin therapy. Switching to atorvastatin again (in lower doses) was followed by a rise in ALT and alkaline phosphatase levels and appearance of pruritus within a week. She was not jaundiced, but direct bilirubin was elevated (total=1.1 and direct=0.6 mg/dL). Atorvastatin was again stopped and serum enzymes fell into the normal range and remained normal on subsequent long term lovastatin therapy.</p>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Key_Points1">
            <title>Key Points</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication:</th>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin (80 mg daily)</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholestatic (R=1.1 initially; 2.0 on reexposure)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1+ (no jaundice)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latency:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 weeks initially, &#x0003c;1 week on re-exposure</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~1 month</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other medications:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T1_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herbal weight loss agent (first exposure only)</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Laboratory_Values1">
            <title>Laboratory Values</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T2" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time After Starting</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time After Stopping</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alk P (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilirubin (mg/dL)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">While on Simvastatin</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Switched to atorvastatin (80 mg/day)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin stopped</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">694</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asymptomatic</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On lovastatin</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Atorvastatin (20 mg/day) restarted</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">711</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin stopped</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">404</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Itching</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On lovastatin</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_1 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_2" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Normal Values</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;42</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;117</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;1.2</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T2_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Comment1">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>The rapid recurrence of liver test abnormalities within days of reexposure is convincing evidence that the initial episode was due to atorvastatin (rather than the herbal weight loss agent) and that the abnormalities were not simple aminotransferase elevations that are common on statin therapy, but rather a manifestation of mild idiosyncratic liver injury with a distinctive cholestatic pattern.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Case_2._Cholestatic_hepatit">
          <title>Case 2. Cholestatic hepatitis due to atorvastatin.</title>
          <p>[Modified from: de Castro ML, Hermo JA, Baz A, de Luaces C, Perez R, Clofent J. [Acute cholestatic hepatitis after atorvastatin reintroduction] (Spanish). Gastroenterol Hepatol 2006; 29: 21-4. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16393626">PubMed Citation</ext-link>]</p>
          <p>A 72 year old man with hyperlipidemia was treated with atorvastatin (20 mg daily) which he took intermittently for 4 to 5 months. Having stopped therapy for 3 months, he restarted it at a dose of 40 mg daily, and one week later developed dark urine and jaundice. He had no constitutional symptoms of fatigue, nausea or abdominal pain and had no fever or rash. Laboratory testing revealed elevations in ALT, alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin levels (Table). He had no history of liver disease or exposures to viral hepatitis and did not drink alcohol. He took prednisone and folic acid for anemia believed to be due to myelofibrosis. Tests for hepatitis A, B and C were negative as were AMA and SMA. ANA was positive at 1:80, but was known to be elevated for several years before treatment with atorvastatin. Ultrasound of the abdomen and MRCP showed no evidence of biliary disease. A liver biopsy showed intrahepatic cholestasis and mixed inflammatory infiltrates compatible with drug induced liver injury. Stopping atorvastatin was followed by a slow return of laboratory tests to normal. His hyperlipidemia was subsequently managed with ezetimibe.</p>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Key_Points2">
            <title>Key Points</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T3" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication:</th>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin (40 mg daily)</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed (R=3), later cholestatic</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+ (jaundice, hospitalization)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latency:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 week on reexposure</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~3-6 months</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other medications:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T3_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prednisone, folic acid</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Laboratory_Values2">
            <title>Laboratory Values</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T4" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time After Starting</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time After Stopping</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alk P (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilirubin (mg/dL)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">282</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin started</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 months</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin stopped</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin restarted</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">920</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin stopped</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1259</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver biopsy</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">441</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1141</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">746</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">431</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 months</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 months</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 months</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 months</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_1 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_2" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Normal Values</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;55</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;270</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;1.2</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T4_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Comment2">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>The rapid development of a cholestatic hepatitis after reintroduction of atorvastatin suggests an immuno-allergic form of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury. While the serum enzyme elevations qualified as being &#x0201c;mixed&#x0201d;, the clinical course was cholestatic.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Case_3._Self-limited_autoim">
          <title>Case 3. Self-limited autoimmune hepatitis-like injury arising during atorvastatin and ezetimibe therapy.</title>
          <p>[Modified from: van Heyningen C. Drug-induced acute autoimmune hepatitis during combination therapy with atorvastatin and ezetimibe. Ann Clin Biochem 2005; 42: 402-4. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16168199">PubMed Citation</ext-link>]</p>
          <p>A 50 year old woman developed nausea, abdominal pain and jaundice with features of autoimmune hepatitis during combination therapy with atorvastatin (80 mg daily for 16 months) and ezetimibe (10 mg daily for 3 months). There was no previous history of liver disease, and laboratory tests had been normal shortly before ezetimibe was started. She had multiple other medical problems including coronary artery disease, osteoarthritis, hypothyroidism, and gastroesophageal reflux. She drank little alcohol and had no exposures to hepatitis. On presentation, she had epigastric tenderness but no rash or fever. Laboratory tests showed raised bilirubin and serum enzymes (Table). Both ezetimibe and atorvastatin were stopped. Tests for hepatitis A, B and C were negative and ultrasound imaging showed no evidence of biliary obstruction. A liver biopsy showed hepatitis with eosinophils and plasma cells. She tested positive for antinuclear antibody and antibodies to double-stranded DNA (anti-dsDNA). Over the next few weeks, her symptoms resolved and laboratory tests improved. Six weeks after onset, her liver tests were normal and autoantibody levels had fallen. She was started on rosuvastatin for her hypercholesterolemia and did well without recurrence of symptoms or liver test abnormalities.</p>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Key_Points3">
            <title>Key Points</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T5" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication:</th>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin (80 mg daily) and ezetimibe (10 mg daily)</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatocellular (R=10.7)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+ (jaundice, hospitalization)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latency:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 months for atorvastatin; 12 weeks for ezetimibe</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~6 weeks</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other medications:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T5_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Furosemide, diltiazem, diclofenac, acetaminophen, atenolol, ibuprofen, clopidogrel, thyroxine, lactulose, and nitrates</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Laboratory_Values3">
            <title>Laboratory Values</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T6" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time After Starting</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time After Stopping</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alk P (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilirubin (mg/dL)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin (~13 months)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Ezetimibe (10 mg/day) started</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1626</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANA 1:160, anti-dsDNA 38</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 days</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">858</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">424</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANA 1:80, anti-dsDNA 31</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 weeks</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANA 1:40, anti-dsDNA 6</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_1 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_2" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Normal Values</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;42</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;130</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;1.2</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T6_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Comment3">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>A well documented example of drug induced autoimmune hepatitis with resolution when the medication was stopped. Particularly convincing was the decrease in autoantibody titers with drug withdrawal. Ezetimibe is perhaps the most likely candidate to have caused the liver injury, but cases of autoimmune hepatitis-like injury from atorvastatin have been reported with latency to onset of more than a year.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Atorvastatin.Case_4._Autoimmune_hepatiti">
          <title>Case 4. Autoimmune hepatitis requiring long term immunosuppression arising during atorvastatin therapy.</title>
          <p>[Modified from: Pelli N, Setti M, Ceppa P, Toncini C, Indiveri F. Autoimmune hepatitis revealed by atorvastatin. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2003; 15: 921-4. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12867804">PubMed Citation</ext-link>]</p>
          <p>A 65 year old woman developed fatigue and jaundice 3 months after starting atorvastatin (20 mg daily) for long standing hypercholesterolemia for which she had previously been treated with prvastatin [6 months] and fluvastatin [3 years] before switching to atorvastatin. Her only other medication was doxazosin which she had taken for years for hypertension. She had no history of liver disease or exposures to viral hepatitis and did not drink alcohol. On examination, she was jaundiced and had hepatomegaly but no fever, rash or signs of chronic liver disease. Laboratory tests showed a hepatocellular pattern of serum enzyme elevations and mild hyperbilirubinemia (Table). Tests for viral hepatitis were negative, but she had hyperglobulinemia with IgG 6.6 g/dL (normal &#x0003c;1.7) and high titers of both ANA and SMA (&#x0003e;1:1280). A liver biopsy showed chronic hepatitis and lobular collapse and mild fibrosis. She was started on prednisone with improvement in blood tests, but three months later she still had ALT elevations and autoantibody titers had not declined. A repeat liver biopsy showed early cirrhosis.</p>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Key_Points4">
            <title>Key Points</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T7" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication:</th>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin (20 mg daily)</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatocellular (R=7.5)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_2_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+ (jaundice, hospitalization)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latency:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_3_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_4_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incomplete</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_1_1" id="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other medications:</th>
                    <td headers="hd_b_Atorvastatin.T7_1_1_5_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doxazosin</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Laboratory_Values4">
            <title>Laboratory Values</title>
            <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T8" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weeks After Starting</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weeks After Stopping</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT* (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alk P (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilirubin* (mg/dL)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">510</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">481</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothrombin 17%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">430</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANA &#x0003e;1:1280</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First liver biopsy</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prednisone (1 mg/kg/day)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANA &#x0003e;1:1280</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second liver biopsy</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_1 hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_2" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Normal Values</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;40</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;279</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;1.2</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T8_1_1_1_6" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>* Values estimated from Figure 3. Bilirubin converted from &#x000b5;mol to mg/dL.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Atorvastatin.Comment4">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>Jaundice and features of autoimmune hepatitis arose after 3 months of atorvastatin therapy in a patient who had been treated with other statins for more than 3 years. Liver tests improved minimally with stopping atorvastatin and one month later prednisone was started, whereupon serum enzymes decreased from ~8-fold to ~twice normal. However, serum autoantibodies remained present in unchanging titers, and a repeat liver biopsy showed progression of fibrosis with nodularity and incomplete cirrhosis. In this case, atorvastatin appeared to trigger a self-sustained autoimmune hepatitis. An alternative explanation is that atorvastatin was an innocent bystander and the development of autoimmune hepatitis was coincidental and unrelated to the chronic statin therapy.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Atorvastatin.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Atorvastatin.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Atorvastatin &#x02013; Lipitor&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Anitlipemic Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=atorvastatin">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Atorvastatin.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCT">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Atorvastatin.T9" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://135019185">134523-00-5</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C33-H35-F-N2-O5</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Atorvastatin.T9_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Atorvastatin.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Image of Chemical Structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Atorvastatin.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 03 August 2017</p>
        <ref-list id="Atorvastatin.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Drugs used in the treatment of hypercholesterolemia and hyperlipidemia. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 660-2.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Expert review of hepatotoxicity published in 1999; the statins have dose related hepatic effects in guinea pigs and rabbits and transient elevations in aminotransferases occur in 1-5% of humans treated; several cases of clinically apparent liver injury from lovastatin and simvastatin have been published).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">De Marzio DH, Navarro VJ. Hepatotoxicity of cardiovascular and antidiabetic medications. Lipid lowering agents. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013, pp. 519-40.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Review of hepatotoxicity of lipid lowering agents; asymptomatic elevations in aminotransferases are common in patients receiving statins, but clinically significant hepatotoxicity is rare).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bersot TP. Drug therapy for hypercholesterolemia and dyslipidemia. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman&#x02019;s the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 877-908.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics: &#x0201c;the statins are the most effective and best-tolerated agents for treating dyslipidemia.&#x0201d; Statins act by inhibition of the rate limiting step in hepatic cholesterol synthesis).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dart A, Jerums G, Nicholson G, d'Emden M, Hamilton-Craig I, Tallis G, Best J, et al. A multicenter, double-blind, one-year study comparing safety and efficacy of atorvastatin versus simvastatin in patients with hypercholesterolemia. Am J Cardiol 1997; 80: 39-44. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In a study comparing atorvastatin [10 to 20 mg] to simvastatin [10 to 20 mg] for 1 year in 177 patients with hypercholesterolemia, there were "no clinically important elevations in ALT, AST or CPK" during treatment with either statin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9205017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Black DM, Bekker-Arkema RG, Nawrocki JW. An overview of the clinical safety profile of atorvastatin (Lipitor), a new HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor. Arch Intern Med 1998; 158: 577-84. <italic toggle="yes">
</italic><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Pooled data of 4271 patients followed for 1845 patient years in 21 clinical trials receiving atorvastatin indicated that 0.7% had ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN, usually within first 16 weeks, 1 patient had cholestatic hepatitis after 36 weeks, resolving in 14 weeks; dose relationship of rate of ALT elevations; 0.2% with 10 and 20 mg, 0.6% with 40 and 2.3% with 80 mg daily).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jiminez-Alonso J, Osorio JM, Gutierrez-Cabello F, Lopez de la Osa A, Leon L, Mediavilla Garcia JD. Atorvastatin-induced cholestatic hepatitis in a young woman with systemic lupus erythematosus. Arch Intern Med 1999; 159: 1811-2. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(20 year old woman with lupus and complex medical history developed jaundice 2 months after starting atorvastatin despite concurrent prednisone therapy [bilirubin 8.2 mg/dL, ALT 783 U/L, Alk P 669 U/L], resolving within a month of stopping atorvastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11893380</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nakad A, Bataille L, Hamoir V, Sempoux C, Horsman Y. Atorvastatin-induced hepatitis with the absence of cross-toxicity with simvastatin. Lancet 1999; 353: 1763-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(70 year old woman developed nausea and weakness after 12 weeks of atorvastatin therapy [bilirubin not given, ALT 230 U/L, Alk P 591 U/L], returning to normal 2 weeks after stopping and no recurrence with simvastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10347994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wierzbicki A, Crook MA. Cholestatic liver dysfunction. Lancet 1999; 354: 954. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 275 patients with familial hyperlipidemia, 3% had ALT elevations and 2 had raised alkaline phosphatase and slight bilirubin elevations during atorvastatin therapy; resolving after switching to fluvastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10489985</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sreenarasinhaiah J, Shiels P, Lisker-Melman M. Multiorgan failure induced by atorvastatin. Am J Med 2002; 113: 348-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(65 year old woman developed jaundice on atorvastatin, resolving when stopping, but recurring in severe form with restarting [bilirubin 25 mg/dL, ALT 290 U/L], progressing to liver and renal failure, myocardial infarction, pancreatitis and death).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lewin JJ 3rd, Nappi JM, Taylor MH. Rhabdomyolysis with concurrent atorvastatin and diltiazem. Ann Pharmacother 2002; 36: 1546-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(60 year old man on long term atorvastatin developed rhabdomyolysis 3 weeks after starting diltiazem [bilirubin 0.7 mg/dL, ALT 1610 U/L, Alk P 287 U/L, CPK 1898 U/L and myoglobinemia], resolving rapidly with stopping medications).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12243603</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gagn&#x000e9; C, Gaudet D, Bruckert E; Ezetimibe Study Group. Efficacy and safety of ezetimibe coadministered with atorvastatin or simvastatin in patients with homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia. Circulation 2002; 105: 2469-75. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Prospective trial comparing the combination of ezetimibe and either atorvastatin or simvastatin to the statin alone in 50 patients with homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia; side effects were similar; two patients on combination therapy had ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN, but both resolved without stopping therapy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ridruejo E, Mando OG. Acute cholestatic hepatitis after reinitiating treatment with atorvastatin. J Hepatol 2002; 37: 165-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(69 year old man developed jaundice 7 months after starting atorvastatin [bilirubin 2.6 mg/dL, ALT 72 U/L, Alk P 3767 U/L, eosinophilia, ANA negative], resolving within 4 months of stopping; he was previously treated with simvastatin and pravastatin without problems).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12076881</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kiortsis DN, Nikas S, Hatzidimou K, Tsianos E, Elisaf MS. Lipid-lowering drugs and serum liver enzymes: the effects of body weight and baseline enzyme levels. Fundam Clin Pharmacol 2003; 17: 491-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 163 patients treated with various lipid lowering drugs, proportion with elevated ALT levels was 9.1% before treatment, 9.5% at 8 weeks and 9.1% at 24 weeks; similar at all body weights, but ALT elevations more frequent in obese and overweight subjects).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12914553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Graziadei IW, Obermoser GE, Sepp NT, Erhart KH, Vogel W. Drug-induced lupus-like syndrome associated with severe autoimmune hepatitis. Lupus 2003; 12: 409-12. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(58 year old woman developed abdominal pain after 7 months of atorvastatin with biopsy findings of autoimmune hepatitis, ANA 1:640 and skin rash [lupus], responding poorly to corticosteroids [bilirubin 4.5 mg/dL, ALT 263 U/L, Alk P 270 U/L, IgG 2.7 gm/dL], ultimately requiring long term tacrolimus and mycophenolate for control).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12765306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pelli N, Setti M, Ceppa P, Toncini C, Indiveri F. Autoimmune hepatitis revealed by atorvastatin. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2003; 15: 921-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(65 year old woman developed jaundice 3 months after starting atorvastatin [bilirubin 3.0 mg/dL, ALT 510 U/L, Alk P 481 U/L, IgG 6.58 gm/dL, both ANA and SMA &#x0003e;1:1280]; only partial response to prednisone with evolution to cirrhosis and requiring long term corticosteroid therapy: Case 4).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12867804</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perger L, Kohler M, Fattinger K, Flury R, Meier PJ, Pauli-Magnus C. Fatal liver failure with atorvastatin. J Hepatol 2003; 39: 1096-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(85 year old man developed jaundice 2 weeks after starting atorvastatin 20 mg daily [bilirubin 25 mg/dL, ALT 1401 U/L, Alk P 393 U/L], worsened despite stopping drug with subsequent coma, hepato-renal syndrome and death).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14642636</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pelli N, Setti M. Atorvastatin as a trigger of autoimmune hepatitis. J Hepatol 2004; 40: 715-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Letter in response to Perger [2003], summarizing their previously published case [Pelli 2003).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15030994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Parra JL, Reddy KR. Hepatotoxicity of hypolipidemic drugs. Clin Liver Dis 2003; 7: 415-33. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review and discussion of individual hypolipidemic agents: atorvastatin is associated with ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN in 0.7%, but only 0.3% stopped therapy because of these abnormalities).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12879992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bays HE, Dujovne CA, McGovern ME, White TE, Kashyap ML, Hutcheson AG, Crouse JR; Advicor Versus Other Cholesterol-Modulating Agents Trial Evaluation. Comparison of once-daily, niacin extended-release/lovastatin with standard doses of atorvastatin and simvastatin(the Advicor Versus Other Cholesterol-Modulating Agents Trial Evaluation [ADVOCATE]). Am J Cardiol 2003; 91: 667-72. <italic toggle="yes">
</italic><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial comparing lovastatin combined with niacin to atorvastatin or simvastatin alone in 315 patients for 16 weeks; no patient had confirmed ALT elevation &#x0003e;3 times ULN).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12633795</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Newman CB, Palmer G, Silbershatz H, Szarek M. Safety of atorvastatin derived from analysis of 44 completed trials in 9,416 patients. Am J Cardiol 2003; 92: 67-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Pooled data from 44 trials which included 9,416 patients treated with atorvastatin; ALT was &#x0003e;3 times ULN in 0.5% of atorvastatin vs 0.3% of placebo recipients; rates rising from 0.13% with 10 and 20 mg, 0.4% with 40 mg and 0.9% with 80 mg of atorvastatin daily).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16377285</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jacobson TA. Comparative pharmacokinetic interaction profiles of pravastatin, simvastatin, and atorvastatin when coadministered with cytochrome P450 inhibitors. Am J Cardiol 2004; 94: 1140-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Pharmacokinetic studies showing that drugs that inhibit CYP 3A4, the major P450 drug metabolizing enzyme, [itraconazole, clarithromycin, verapamil] cause increases in blood levels of simvastatin and atorvastatin, but have little effect on pravastatin levels).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15518608</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gershovich OE, Lyman AE Jr. Liver function test abnormalities and pruritus in a patient treated with atorvastatin: case report and review of the literature. Pharmacotherapy 2004; 24: 150-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(71 year old woman developed ALT and Alk P elevations after taking atorvastatin for 2 months, which resolved rapidly but recurred after 4 days of restarting drug with itching [bilirubin 1.1 mg/dL, ALT 478 U/L, Alk P 711 U/L], resolving rapidly with stopping and not recurring on switching to lovastatin: Case 1).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14740794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Geoghegan M, Smith V, Green JRB. Acute cholestatic hepatitis associated with atorvastatin. Gut 2004; 53 (Suppl.3): A123. [Abstract] Not in PubMed<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Two patients, 1 woman and 1 man, ages 57 and 63 years, developed jaundice 4 and 12 weeks after starting atorvastatin [bilirubin 34.3 and 1.1 mg/dL, ALT 931 and 283 U/L, Alk P 156 and 216 U/L, ANA negative], resolving 8 weeks after stopping).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Aljadhey H, Kesterson J, Murray MD, Hall SD. Patients with elevated liver enzymes are not at higher risk for statin hepatotoxicity. Gastroenterology 2004; 126: 1287-92. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective analysis of electronic records found similar rates of severe ALT or AST elevations with or without statin [atorvastatin, simvastatin or fluvastatin] therapy [0.6% vs 0.4%] in those with baseline elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15131789</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kaplowitz N. Statin-induced hepatotoxicity. Gastroenterology 2004; 127: 1278. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Letter in response to Chalasani [2004] requesting addition information on cohorts: reply by authors provides what was available).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15481021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">de Denus S, Spinler SA, Miller K, Peterson AM. Statins and liver toxicity: a meta-analysis. Pharmacotherapy 2004; 24: 584-91. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In 13 controlled trials with 49,275 patients with routine liver test monitoring for an average of 3.6 years, statin therapy was not associated with increased rate of liver test abnormalities [1.14% vs 1.05%: odds ratio = 1.26; 95% CI = 0.99-1.62] compared to placebo).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15162892</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russo MW, Galanko JA, Shrestha R, Fried MW, Watkins P. Liver transplantation for acute liver failure from drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Liver Transpl 2004; 10: 1018-23. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among ~50,000 liver transplants done in the United States between 1990 and 2002, 270 [0.5%] were done for drug induced acute liver failure, 3 of which were attributed to statins including simvastatin in 1 and cerivastatin in 2).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15390328</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alsheikh-Ali AA, Karas RH. Adverse events with concomitant amiodarone and statin therapy. Prev Cardiol 2005; 8: 95-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of MedWatch adverse event reports for proportion of cases attributed to different statins that included combination with amiodarone; 1.0% for simvastatin, 0.7% atorvastatin and 0.4% pravastatin; 77% muscle, 30% liver involvement).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15860984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nissen SE. Effect of intensive lipid lowering on progression of coronary atherosclerosis: evidence for an early benefit from the Reversal of Atherosclerosis with Aggressive Lipid Lowering(REVERSAL) trial. Am J Cardiol 2005; 96 (5A): 61F-68F. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial comparing pravastatin [40 mg] to atorvastatin [80 mg] daily for 18 months in 654 patients; ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 1.6% on pravastatin vs 2.3% on atorvastatin, but no instances of clinically apparent hepatitis).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16126025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van Heyningen C. Drug-induced acute autoimmune hepatitis during combination therapy with atorvastatin and ezetimibe. Ann Clin Biochem 2005; 42: 402-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(50 year old woman developed jaundice 16 months after starting atorvastatin and 3 months after starting ezetimibe [bilirubin 4.6 mg/dL, AST 1626 U/L, Alk P 468 U/L, positive ANA and anti-dsDNA], resolving 6 weeks after stopping both: Case 3).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16168199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Charles EC, Olson KL, Sandhoff BG, McClure DL, Merenich JA. Evaluation of cases of severe statin-induced transaminitis within a large health maintenance organization. Am J Med 2005; 118: 618-24. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 23,000 patients on statins in a health plan, 17 had an ALT elevation &#x0003e;10 times ULN attributable to statin use; 10 on simvastatin, 5 lovastatin, and 2 atorvastatin; onset 2 days to 4 years after starting; 10 symptomatic; all resolved within 2 to 8 weeks, except one death; 3 of 7 recurred on rechallenge, 5 of 6 tolerated switching to another statin; two atorvastatin cases had ALT 1481 and 478 U/L, bilirubin 1.3 and 1.1 mg/dL, resolved in 5 and 2 weeks).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15922693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alsheikh-Ali AA, Ambrose MS, Kuvin JT, Karas RH. The safety of rosuvastatin as used in common clinical practice: a postmarketing analysis. Circulation 2005; 111: 3051-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of adverse event reporting for rosuvastatin during first year of marketing; liver related events rates were higher for rosuvastatin [~25/million prescriptions] than other statins [~4/million] and higher for comparable periods for simvastatin, pravastatin and atorvastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15911706</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ballantyne CM, Abate N, Yuan Z, King TR, Palmisano J. Dose-comparison study of the combination of ezetimibe and simvastatin (Vytorin) versus atorvastatin in patients with hypercholesterolemia: the Vytorin Versus Atorvastatin (VYVA) study. Am Heart J 2005; 149: 464-73. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Controlled trial of ezetimibe/simvastatin vs atorvastatin in 1902 patients with hypercholesterolemia, ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 1.1% on atorvastatin and none on ezetimibe/simvastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15864235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">LaRosa JC, Grundy SM, Waters DD, Shear C, Barter P, Fruchart JC, Gotto AM, et al.; Treating to New Targets (TNT) Investigators. Intensive lipid lowering with atorvastatin in patients with stable coronary disease. N Engl J Med 2005; 352: 1425-35. <italic toggle="yes">
</italic><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of 10 mg or 80 mg of atorvastatin daily in 10,001 patients with coronary artery disease and LDL cholesterol of &#x0003c;130 mg/dL for an average of 4.9 years; rate of confirmed ALT elevation &#x0003e;3 times ULN 1.2% with high dose and 0.2% with low dose atorvastatin; 5 cases of rhabdomyolysis, but no hepatitis reported).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15755765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Andrade RJ, Lucena MI, Fern&#x000e1;ndez MC, Pelaez G, Pachkoria K, Garc&#x000ed;a-Ruiz E, Garc&#x000ed;a-Mu&#x000f1;oz B, et al.; Spanish Group for the Study of Drug-Induced Liver Disease. Drug-induced liver injury: an analysis of 461 incidences submitted to the Spanish registry over a 10-year period. Gastroenterology 2005; 129: 512-21. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Analysis of 461 cases of drug induced liver disease diagnosed between 1994 to 2004 in Spanish Registry; 11 cases were attributed to "statins", but no specific agent caused more than 4 cases).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16083708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Andrade RJ, Lucena MI, Kaplowitz N, Garc&#x000ed;a-Munoz B, Borraz Y, Pachkoria K, Garc&#x000ed;a-Cort&#x000e9;s M, et al. Outcome of acute idiosyncratic drug-induced liver injury: Long-term follow-up in a hepatotoxicity registry. Hepatology 2006; 44: 1581-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(28 of 493 [5.7%] cases of drug induced liver disease were found to have evidence of chronic injury, including 2 cases due to atorvastatin with raised serum enzymes 9 and 17 months after an acute anicteric liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17133470</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Clarke AT, Mills PR. Atorvastatin associated liver disease. Dig Liver Dis 2006; 38: 772-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(7 cases of atorvastatin liver injury from 1 center between 2002-5; ages 50-78 years, arising 3-52 weeks after starting [bilirubin levels ranging from 0.6 to 40.2 mg/dL, AST 76 to 1702 U/L, Alk P 410 to 1935 U/L], resolving within 1-10 months of stopping, 1 death and 1 prolonged).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16777499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Khorashadi S, Hasson NK, Cheung RC. Incidence of statin hepatotoxicity in patients with hepatitis C. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2006; 4: 902-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Electronic record review of rate of ALT elevations in patients with hepatitis C with or without statin therapy and controls on statin therapy found no differences between the three groups [20%, 24% and 17%]; severe abnormalities most frequent in patients with chronic hepatitis C not on statins [6.6% vs 1.2%]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16697272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cohen DE, Anania FA, Chalasani N, National Lipid Association Statin Safety Task Force Liver Expert Panel. An assessment of statin safety by hepatologists. Am J Cardiol 2006; 97 (8A): 77C-81C. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert opinion of panel of academic hepatologists; statins as a class are associated with low rates of moderate ALT elevations during therapy, particularly with higher doses, but these are generally not indicative of significant liver injury, acute liver failure being very rare; routine monitoring of serum aminotransferase levels is not necessary; statins can be used safely in patients with chronic liver disease including nonalcoholic fatty liver).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16581333</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Conforti A, Magro L, Moretti U, Scotto S, Motola D, Salvo F, Ros B, et al. Fluvastatin and hepatic reactions: a signal from spontaneous reporting in Italy. Drug Safety 2006; 29:1163-72. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Italian Pharmacovigilance Group review of 35,757 adverse reaction reports; 1260 due to statins of which 178 were hepatic: 69 [36%] fluvastatin, 37 [21%] atorvastatin, 50 [28%] simvastatin, 16 [9%] pravastatin, 6 [3%] rosuvastatin; proportion reporting rate based on number of prescriptions was highest for fluvastatin [~9] compared to other agents [~2-3]; 26 fluvastatin cases described as &#x0201c;hepatitis&#x0201d;, but no details given except that most cases occurred within 90 days of starting).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17147462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Law M, Rudnicka AR. Statin safety: a systematic review. Am J Cardiol 2006; 97(8A): 52C-60C. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of safety of statins; 38 cases of acute liver failure submitted to MedWatch by end of 1999, which gives an estimated rate of 1 per million person years of use; rate of confirmed ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN is 0.1% with statins and 0.04% with placebo).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16581329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Goldberg RB, Guyton JR, Mazzone T, Weinstock RS, Polis A, Edwards P, Tomassini JE, et al. Ezetimibe/simvastatin vs atorvastatin in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypercholesterolemia: the VYTAL study. Mayo Clin Proc 2006; 81: 1579-88. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of atorvastatin vs simvastatin/ezetimibe in 1229 patients with diabetes and hypercholesterolemia; confirmed ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 0.3% of atorvastatin vs no simvastatin/ezetimibe treated patient, and no clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17165637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson E, Olsson R. Suspected drug-induced liver fatalities reported to the WHO database. Dig Liver Dis 2006; 38: 33-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In WHO database of fatal adverse drug reactions from 1968-2003, there were 4690 reports of drug induced liver fatality; none of the statins were in the top 20 suspected causes).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16054882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alla V, Abraham J, Siddiqui J, Raina D, Wu GY, Chalasani NP, Bonkovsky HL. Autoimmune hepatitis triggered by statins. J Clin Gastroenterol 2006; 40: 757-61. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Three cases of autoimmune hepatitis arising after simvastatin or atorvastatin therapy 6, 20 and 20 weeks after starting [bilirubin 11.3, 3.4 and 5.5 mg/dL, ALT 1749, 1170 and 155 U/L, Alk P of 228, 160, and 203 U/L, all being ANA or SMA positive in titers of 1:40 to 1:160], all responding to prednisone/azathioprine, but remaining on long term therapy with azathioprine or mycophenylate alone).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16940892</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">de Castro ML, Hermo JA, Baz A, de Luaces C, Perez R, Clofent J. [Acute cholestatic hepatitis after atorvastatin reintroduction](Spanish). Gastroenterol Hepatol 2006; 29: 21-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (72 year old man developed jaundice one week after restarting atorvastatin therapy [bilirubin 8.0 mg/dL, ALT 538 U/L, Alk P 1259 U/L], resolving slowly with stopping therapy: Case 2).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16393626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Clearfield MB, Amerena J, Bassand JP, Hern&#x000e1;ndez Garc&#x000ed;a HR, Miller SS, Sosef FF, Palmer MK, et al. Comparison of the efficacy and safety of rosuvastatin 10 mg and atorvastatin 20 mg in high-risk patients with hypercholesterolemia -- Prospective study to evaluate the Use of Low doses of the Statins Atorvastatin and Rosuvastatin (PULSAR). Trials 2006; 7: 35. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Controlled trial comparing rosuvastatin [10 mg] vs atorvastatin [20 mg] daily for 6 weeks; one patient on atorvastatin had confirmed ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN; no clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17184550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Amarenco P, Bogousslavsky J, Callahan A 3rd, Goldstein LB, Hennerici M, Rudolph AE, Sillesen H, et al.; Stroke Prevention by Aggressive Reduction in Cholesterol Levels (SPARCL) Investigators. High-dose atorvastatin after stroke or transient ischemic attack. N Engl J Med 2006; 355: 549-59. <italic toggle="yes">
</italic><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of atorvastatin [80 mg] vs placebo for 4-6 years in 4731 patients with cerebrovascular disease and hypercholesterolemia; confirmed ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 2.2% of atorvastatin vs 0.5% of placebo recipients; no cases of liver failure).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">G&#x000f3;mez-Dom&#x000ed;nguez E, Gisbert JP, Moreno-Monteagudo JA, Garc&#x000ed;a-Buey L, Moreno-Otero R. A pilot study of atorvastatin treatment in dyslipidemia, non-alcoholic fatty liver patients. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2006; 23: 1643-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Open label study of a one year course of atorvastatin in various doses for nonalcoholic liver disease found some degree of improvement in ALT, AST and GGT levels).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16696815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Silva MA, Swanson AC, Gandhi PJ, Tataronis GR. Statin-related adverse events: a meta-analysis. Clin Ther 2006; 28: 26-35. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Meta analysis of adverse event rates in 18 placebo controlled trials of six statins in 71,108 patients; ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN in 1.7% of statin vs 1.4% placebo recipients; event rates highest with atorvastatin, lowest with fluvastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16490577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Arca M. Atorvastatin: a safety and tolerability profile. Drugs 2007; 67 Suppl 1: 63-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of safety of atorvastatin; ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occur in &#x0003c;1% of statin recipients, but rate may be higher with higher doses of atorvastatin, estimate of rate of acute liver failure is ~1 per million persons years).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17910522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bhardwah SS, Chalasani N. Lipid-lowering agents that cause drug-induced hepatotoxicity. Clin Liver Dis 2007; 11: 597-613. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of statins; reported rates of ALT or AST elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN; atorvastatin 0.7%, fluvastatin 1.2%, lovastatin 0.6%, pravastatin 1.4%, rosuvastatin 0% and simvastatin 1.8%; usually asymptomatic, individual case reports of autoimmune hepatitis).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17723922</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alsheikh-Ali AA, Maddukuri PV, Han H, Karas RH. Effect of the magnitude of lipid lowering on risk of elevated liver enzymes, rhabdomyolysis, and cancer: insights from large randomized statin trials. J Am Coll Cardiol 2007; 50: 409-18. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of relationship between LDL cholesterol lowering effects and adverse events in 23 statin treatment arms representing 309,506 person years of therapy; positive and graded relationship between statin dose [simvastatin, lovastatin and atorvastatin] and rates of ALT elevations, but no independent relationship to degree of LDL cholesterol decrease).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17662392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dale KM, White CM, Henyan NN, Kluger J, Coleman CI. Impact of statin dosing intensity on transaminase and creatine kinase. Am J Med 2007; 120: 706-12. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Meta analysis of rates of ALT and CPK elevations in nine controlled studies comparing low vs high doses of statins; ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 1.5% of high- and 0.4% of low-intensity statin groups, effect particularly seen with hydrophilic [pravastatin and atorvastatin] compared to lipophilic agents [simvastatin and lovastatin]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17679130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Silva M, Matthews ML, Jarvis C, Nolan NM, Belliveau P, Malloy M, Gandhi P. Meta-analysis of drug-induced adverse events associated with intensive-dose statin therapy. Clin Ther 2007; 29: 253-60. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Meta analysis of rates of adverse events in 4 controlled trials in 108,049 patient years comparing standard to intensive-dose statin therapy; increased risk of ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN with intensive therapy [odds ratio 4.5; absolute risk 1.2%], but no mention of clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17472818</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alsheikh-Ali AA, Karas RH. Safety of lovastatin/extended release niacin compared with lovastatin alone, atorvastatin alone, pravastatin alone, and simvastatin alone(from the United States Food and Drug Administration adverse event reporting system). Am J Cardiol 2007; 99: 379-81. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Analysis of MedWatch reports of adverse events found no excess in liver related adverse event reports per million prescriptions due to lovastatin alone [2.3] vs niacin alone [2.5] vs the combination [3.2], but slightly higher rates with atorvastatin [4.5], simvastatin [5.7] and pravastatin [4.9], but data relied upon spontaneous reporting).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17261402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Segarra-Newnham M, Parra D, Martin-Cooper EM. Effectiveness and hepatotoxicity of statins in men seropositive for hepatitis C virus. Pharmacotherapy 2007; 27: 845-51. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective analysis of electronic records on 146 men with chronic hepatitis C who started statin therapy [simvastatin mostly, but also fluvastatin, lovastatin, pravastatin, and atorvastatin, &#x0003c;4 each], mean ALT levels did not change and percent with ALT &#x0003e;3 times ULN was 8% at baseline, 10% at 3 months, 11% at 6 months and 8% at 22 months; only one patient stopped therapy for ALT elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17542767</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sabat&#x000e9; M, Ib&#x000e1;&#x000f1;ez L, P&#x000e9;rez E, Vidal X, Buti M, Xiol X, Mas A, et al. Risk of acute liver injury associated with the use of drugs: a multicentre population survey. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2007; 25: 1401-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 126 cases of drug induced liver injury seen in Spain between 1993-2000, no cases were attributed to statins).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17539979</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Leiter LA, Bays H, Conard S, Bird S, Rubino J, Hanson ME, Tomassini JE, et al. Efficacy and safety of ezetimibe added on to atorvastatin (40 mg) compared with uptitration of atorvastatin (to 80 mg) in hypercholesterolemic patients at high risk of coronary heart disease. Am J Cardiol 2008; 102: 1495-501. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of adding ezetimibe vs increasing atorvastatin dosage in 579 patients; ALT or AST elevations &#x0003e;3 times the ULN occurred in 1 patient in both groups).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19026303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Escobar C, Echarri R, Barrios V. Relative safety profiles of high dose statin regimens. Vasc Health Risk Manag 2008; 4: 525-33. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of efficacy and safety of use of higher doses of statins to achieve lower LDL cholesterol levels; ALT elevations are more frequent [2-3%] with higher than lower [~1%] doses).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18827903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hyogo H, Tazuma S, Arihiro K, Iwamoto K, Nabeshima Y, Inoue M, Ishitobi T, et al. Efficacy of atorvastatin for the treatment of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis with dyslipidemia. Metabolism 2008; 57: 1711-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Open labeled trial of 24 month course of atorvastatin [10 mg daily] in 31 patients with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis; improvements in serum ALT levels [mean 98 to 36 U/L], cholesterol and triglyceride levels and steatosis, but apparent worsening of fibrosis in some patients; no hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19013295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rahier JF, Rahier J, Leclercq I, Geubel AP. Severe acute cholestatic hepatitis with prolonged cholestasis and bile-duct injury following atorvastatin therapy: a case report. Acta Gastroenterol Belg 2008; 71: 318-20. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(52 year old developed severe liver injury 5 weeks after starting atorvastatin, 10 mg daily [bilirubin 5.9 rising to ~29 mg/dL, ALT 6838 U/L, Alk P ~150 U/L, ANA negative, INR 1.9], severe itching and slow recovery requiring 6 months for normalization of bilirubin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19198578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R62">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Fontana RJ, Bonkovsky HL, Watkins PB, Davern T, Serrano J, Yang H, Rochon J; Drug Induced Liver Injury Network (DILIN). Causes, clinical features, and outcomes from a prospective study of drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Gastroenterology 2008; 135: 1924-34. <italic toggle="yes">
</italic><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 300 cases of drug induced liver disease collected from 2004 to 2008 in the US, 9 [3%] were attributed to statins, including 3 to atorvastatin, 3 to simvastatin/ezetimibe, and one each to pravastatin, fluvastatin, and simvastatin, but most cases were mild and some were not clearly attributable to the statin therapy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R63">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martin JE, Cavanaugh TM, Trumbull L, Bass M, Weber F Jr, Aranda-Michel J, Hanaway M, et al. Incidence of adverse events with HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors in liver transplant patients. Clin Transplant 2008; 22: 113-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective review of adverse events associated with statin and fibrate use in 69 patients with liver transplants; myalgias problematic in 5, myopathy in 1, but none had significant ALT elevations or hepatitis related to medication).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18217912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R64">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Robinson JG, Ballantyne CM, Grundy SM, Hsueh WA, Parving HH, Rosen JB, Adewale AJ, et al. Lipid-altering efficacy and safety of ezetimibe/simvastatin versus atorvastatin in patients with hypercholesterolemia and the metabolic syndrome(from the VYMET study). Am J Cardiol 2009; 103: 1694-702. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of ezetimibe/simvastatin versus atorvastatin alone in 1128 patients with metabolic syndrome and hypercholesterolemia; adverse event rates were similar in the two groups, but confirmed ALT or AST elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 0.3% of atorvastatin vs 1.4% of ezetimibe/simvastatin treated patients).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19539078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R65">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Koren MJ, Feldman T, Mendes RA. Impact of high-dose atorvastatin in coronary heart disease patients age 65 to 78 years. Clin Cardiol 2009; 32: 256-63. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of high [up to 80 mg daily] vs standard dose [10 mg] atorvastatin in 2442 patients, analysis of subgroup of 1001 who were 65 to 78 years of age; ALT elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 1.3% in younger vs 14% in older cohort receiving high dose atorvastatin; no mention of clinically apparent liver disease).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19452483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R66">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Minha S, Golzman G, Adar I, Rapoport M. Cholestatic jaundice induced by atorvastatin: a possible association with antimitochondrial antibodies. Isr Med Assoc J 2009; 11: 440-1. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(68 year old man developed fever, rash and jaundice while taking atorvastatin for unknown duration [bilirubin 7.4 mg/dL, ALT 250 U/L, Alk P 555 U/L, ANA and AMA positive], recovering upon stopping but recurring three times after restarting atorvastatin, eventually resolving completely on stopping permanently).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19911499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R67">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russo MW, Scobey M, Bonkovsky HL. Drug-induced liver injury associated with statins. Semin Liver Dis 2009; 29: 412-22. PubMed 19826975<italic toggle="yes">
</italic><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of statin hepatotoxicity and the several forms of liver injury that can occur with atorvastatin, including silent aminotransferase elevations, cholestatic and hepatocellular hepatitis and an autoimmune hepatitis-like syndrome, all of which are rare; two case reports, one with an autoimmune hepatitis [bilirubin 1.0 rising to 12.5, ALT 1750 U/L, Alk P 285 U/L, ANA 1:160] responding to prednisone and one with an acute hepatitis-like onset, but subsequent cholestatic hepatitis [bilirubin 7.8 rising to 30 mg/dL, ALT 6200 U/L, Alk P 280 U/L, ANA negative], with slow but ultimately complete recovery).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19826975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R68">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Athyros VG, Tziomalos K, Gossios TD, Griva T, Anagnostis P, Kargiotis K, Pagourelias ED, et al.; GREACE Study Collaborative Group. Safety and efficacy of long-term statin treatment for cardiovascular events in patients with coronary heart disease and abnormal liver tests in the Greek Atorvastatin and Coronary Heart Disease Evaluation (GREACE) Study: a post-hoc analysis. Lancet 2010; 376 (9756): 1916-22. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1600 patients with coronary artery disease treated with statins or standard therapy, mean ALT levels decreased in statin treated patients [57 to 37 U/L], but not in controls [56 to 63 U/L]; 7 of 880 statin treated patients stopped therapy because of ALT elevations, but none developed clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21109302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R69">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu Y, Cheng Z, Ding L, Fang F, Cheng KA, Fang Q, Shi GP. Atorvastatin-induced acute elevation of hepatic enzymes and the absence of cross-toxicity of pravastatin. Int J Clin Pharmacol Ther 2010; 48: 798-802. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Two men, ages 58 and 53 years, developed ALT elevations within 3 days of starting atorvastatin [peak ALT 120 and 278 U/L], resolving on stopping and not recurring on starting pravastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21084035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R70">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Athyros VG, Tziomalos K, Karagiannis A, Mikhailidis DP. Atorvastatin: safety and tolerability. Expert Opin Drug Saf 2010; 9: 667-74. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of safety of atorvastatin concluded that liver toxicity is rare).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20553090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R71">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hippisley-Cox J, Coupland C. Unintended effects of statins in men and women in England and Wales: population based cohort study using the QResearch database. BMJ 2010; 340: c2197. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 225,992 new users of statins in a UK health database, there was an increased relative risk of "moderate or serious liver dysfunction" [ALT &#x0003e; 3 times ULN] in the range of 1.4- to 2.0-fold compared to nonusers, being higher with higher doses and during the first year of treatment; rates were highest for fluvastatin and lowest for pravastatin; rates for atorvastatin were 0.15%-0.17% per person year).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20488911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R72">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Merli M, Bragazzi MC, Giubilo F, Callea F, Attili AF, Alvaro D. Atorvastatin-induced prolonged cholestasis with bile duct damage. Clin Drug Investig 2010; 30: 205-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(72 year old man developed jaundice 6 weeks after starting atorvastatin [biliubin 22 mg/dL, ALT 81 U/L, Alk P 816 U/L, ANA negative], ALT elevations resolving in 5 and Alk P in 8 months). </italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20155993</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R73">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Devarbhavi H, Dierkhising R, Kremers WK, Sandeep MS, Karanth D, Adarsh CK. Single-center experience with drug-induced liver injury from India: causes, outcome, prognosis, and predictors of mortality. Am J Gastroenterol 2010; 105: 2396-404. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Among 313 cases of drug induced liver injury seen over a 12 year period at a large hospital in Bangalore, India, 5 [2%] were attributed to atorvastatin, but no other statin listed].</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20648003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R74">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Idilman R, Bektas M, Cinar K, Toruner M, Cerit ET, Doganay B, Erden E, et al. The characteristics and clinical outcome of drug-induced liver injury: a single-center experience. J Clin Gastroenterol 2010; 44: e128-32. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 170 patients with drug induced liver injury seen at a single referral center in Turkey between 2001 and 2007, 14 were attributed to statins which were hepatocellular in 10 and cholestatic in 4; no details provided).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R75">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reuben A, Koch DG, Lee WM; Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Drug-induced acute liver failure: results of a U.S. multicenter, prospective study. Hepatology 2010; 52: 2065-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1198 patients with acute liver failure enrolled in a US prospective study between 1998 and 2007, 133 [11%] were attributed to drug induced liver injury, of which 6 [4.5%] were attributed to statins: 2 atorvastatin, 2 simvastatin [one with ezetimibe] and 2 cerivastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R76">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Conard S, Bays H, Leiter LA, Bird S, Lin J, Hanson ME, Shah A, Tershakovec AM. Ezetimibe added to atorvastatin compared with doubling the atorvastatin dose in patients at high risk for coronary heart disease with diabetes mellitus, metabolic syndrome or neither. Diabetes Obes Metab 2010; 12: 210-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Randomized trial comparing addition of ezetimibe to atorvastatin versus doubling the dose [40 to 80 mg daily] in 556 patients; only 1 patient in each group had ALT or AST elevations &#x0003e;3 times ULN during a 6 week period).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20151997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R77">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Saku K, Zhang B, Noda K; The PATROL Trial Investigators. Randomized Head-to-Head Comparison of Pitavastatin, Atorvastatin, and Rosuvastatin for Safety and Efficacy (Quantity and Quality of LDL). Circ J 2011; 75(6): 1493-505. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 298 patients treated with one of three statins for 16 weeks, ALT elevations occurred in 5% on atorvastatin, 1% on rosuvastatin and 4% of pitavastatin, but overall the three agents had similar efficacy and similar rates of toxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21498906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R78">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Foster T, Budoff MJ, Saab S, Ahmadi N, Gordon C, Guerci AD. Atorvastatin and antioxidants for the treatment of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: the St Francis Heart Study randomized clinical trial. Am J Gastroenterol 2011; 106: 71-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1005 patients given atorvastatin with vitamin C and E for up to 4 years, 3 patients had ALT elevations &#x0003e;2 times ULN, but therapy appeared to decrease intrahepatic fat as assessed by CT scans).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20842109</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R79">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mackay J, Fenech M, Myint K. Acute rhabdomyolysis caused by combination therapy with atorvastatin and warfarin. Br J Hosp Med (Lond) 2012;73: 106-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (69 year old man on long term atorvastatin therapy developed rhabdomyosis and marked rise in INR after starting warfarin, suggesting a drug-drug interaction).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22504754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R80">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jackevicius CA, Chou MM, Ross JS, Shah ND, Krumholz HM. Generic atorvastatin and health care costs. N Engl J Med 2012; 366: 201-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Atorvastatin became available generically in 2011 which may result in considerable health care savings). </italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22149736</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R81">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bergmann OM, Kristjansson G, Jonasson JG, Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES. Jaundice due to suspected statin hepatotoxicity: a case series. Dig Dis Sci 2012; 57: 1959-64. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(3 women and 1 man, ages 55 to 85 years, developed jaundice 3, 3, 11 and 30 months after starting atorvastatin [n=3] or simvastatin [n=1], with hepatocellular or mixed injury [peak bilirubin 4.0-7.4 mg/dL, ALT 446-2987 U/L, Alk P 174-716 U/L, ANA positive in 1], all resolving spontaneously in 1-3 months).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22075853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R82">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson E, Jacobsen EI, Kalaitzakis E. Hepatotoxicity associated with statins: reports of idiosyncratic liver injury post-marketing. J Hepatol 2012; 56:374-80. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Between 1988 and 2010, the Swedish registry received 217 adverse event reports possibly related to statins, 124 [57%] being liver related, 73 of which could be evaluated: 2 were fatal and one led to liver transplant; 3 had positive rechallenge; 43 [59%] were hepatocellular, 22 [30%] cholestatic and 8 [11%] mixed; 30 were due to atorvastatin, 28 simvastatin, 11 fluvastatin, 2 pravastatin and 2 rosuvastatin, arising after 30-248 days; atorvastatin injury was more likely to be cholestatic and was estimated to occur in 2.9 per 100,000 person years).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21889469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R83">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Han KH, Rha SW, Kang HJ, Bae JW, Choi BJ, Choi SY, Gwon HC, et al. Evaluation of short-term safety and efficacy of HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors in hypercholesterolemic patients with elevated serum alanine transaminase concentrations: PITCH study (PITavastatin versus atorvastatin to evaluate the effect on patients with hypercholesterolemia and mild to moderate hepatic damage). J Clin Lipidol 2012; 6: 340-51. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 189 patients with hypercholesterolemia and ALT elevations [50-100 U/L] treated with pitavastatin vs atorvastatin for 12 weeks, there were minor ALT decreases in both groups; no placebo arm was included).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22836071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R84">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berkelhammer C, Lerma EV. Statin treatment in patients with elevated liver enzymes: pitch to proceed. J Clin Lipidol 2012; 6: 310-1. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Editorial regarding Han [2012] stressing that chronic but stable ALT elevations are not a contraindication to use of statins).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22836066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R85">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kwon H, Lee SH, Kim SE, Lee JH, Jee YK, Kang HR, Park BJ, Park JW, Hong CS. Spontaneously reported hepatic adverse drug events in Korea: multicenter study. J Korean Med Sci 2012; 27: 268-73. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Summary of 2 years of adverse event reporting in Korea; of 9360 reports, 567 were liver related, including 7 [1.2%] attributed to statins).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22379337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R86">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Scarpini F, Cappellone R, Auteri A, Puccetti L. Role of genetic factors in statins side-effects. Cardiovasc Hematol Disord Drug Targets 2012; 12: 35-43. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Genetic variants in several genes appear to affect the frequency of side effects of statins, but to varying degrees with various statins and with different side effects).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22524173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R87">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu Y, Su Q, Li L. Efficacy of short-term high-dose atorvastatin pretreatment in patients with acute coronary syndrome undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention: a meta-analysis of nine randomized controlled trials. Clin Cardiol 2013; 36: E41-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Metanalysis of 3 trials of high dose, short term atorvastatin in 333 patients with an acute coronary event undergoing percutaneous coronary interventions stenting found no increase in rate of serum ALT elevations [10% vs 7%], but no details provided and no mention of clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24038054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R88">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wili&#x00144;ski J, Dabrowski M. Safety and tolerability of the use of atorvastatin 40 mg in common daily practice in short-term observation in 3,227 patients. Przegl Lek 2013; 70: 373-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Abstract: Prospective questionnaire study of 3227 patients treated with atorvastatin [40 mg daily] found that 0.4% had discontinued therapy because of serum aminotransferase elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24052972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R89">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wu du C. Hepatitis B virus reactivation associated with atorvastatin. Int J Infect Dis. 2013; 17: e1069-70. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (48 year old man with HBsAg [HBeAg negative] and coronary artery disease had worsening of hepatitis B after 8 months of atorvastatin therapy [ALT rising from 41 to 322 U/L and HBV DNA from 3.3 to 6.8 log10 IU/mL], improving upon stopping and not worsening when treated with simvastastin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23725984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R90">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tikkanen MJ, Fayyad R, Faergeman O, Olsson AG, Wun CC, Laskey R, Kastelein JJ, et al.; IDEAL Investigators. Effect of intensive lipid lowering with atorvastatin on cardiovascular outcomes in coronary heart disease patients with mild-to-moderate baseline elevations in alanine aminotransferase levels. Int J Cardiol 2013; 168: 3846-52. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Post hoc analysis of the IDEAL study of 8863 patients with hypercholesterolemia treated with simvastatin [20-40 mg daily] vs atorvastatin [80 mg daily], comparing those with normal ALT levels [7782, mean = 26 U/L] to those with elevated levels [1081, mean = 61 U/L], found improvement in cardiovascular outcomes with atorvastatin in both the normal [12.7% vs 13.9%] and high ALT [6.5% vs 11.5%] groups, rates being higher and the effect greater in the elevated ALT cohort).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24001698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R91">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Thapar M, Russo MW, Bonkovsky HL. Statins and Liver Injury. Gastroenterol Hepatol (N Y) 2013; 9: 605-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the hepatotoxicity of statins including both serum enzyme elevations and clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24729773</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R92">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">Demyen M, Alkhalloufi K, Pyrsopoulos NT. Lipid-lowering agents and hepatotoxicity. Clin Liver Dis 2013; 17: 699-714. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24099026">PubMed Citation</ext-link> (Review of hepatotoxicity of statins, fibrates, niacin, bile acid resins and ezetimibe).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
            </mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R93">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES, Bergmann OM, Bj&#x000f6;rnsson HK, Kvaran RB, Olafsson S. Incidence, presentation and outcomes in patients with drug-induced liver injury in the general population of Iceland. Gastroenterology 2013; 144: 1419-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In a population based study of drug induced liver injury from Iceland, 96 cases were identified over a 2 year period, including 2 cases attributed to atorvastatin [one with jaundice] for an estimated rate of 1:3693 persons treated).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R94">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America. An analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Systematic review of literature of drug induced liver injury in Latin American countries published from 1996 to 2012 identified 176 cases, none of which were attributed to statins or lipid lowering agents).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R95">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russo MW, Hoofnagle JH, Gu J, Fontana RJ, Barnhart H, Kleiner DE, Chalasani N, et al. Spectrum of statin hepatotoxicity: Experience of the drug-induced liver injury network. Hepatology 2014; 60: 679-86. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Among 1,188 cases of drug induced liver disease collected in the US between 2004 to 2012, 22 [2%] were attributed to statins, including atorvastatin [8], simvastatin [5], rosuvastatin [4], fluvastatin [2], pravastatin [2] and lovastatin [1]; median age was 60 years and 68% were women; 9 cases were cholestatic and 12 hepatocellular [6 with autoimmune features]; the latency ranged widely, from 1 month to 10 years; only one case was fatal [a man with preexisting cirrhosis presenting with acute-on-chronic liver failure]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24700436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R96">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bays H, Cohen DE, Chalasani N, Harrison SA. An assessment by the Statin Liver Safety Task Force: 2014 update. J Clin Lipidol 2014; 8 (3 Suppl): S47-57. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the safety of statins including their use in patients with liver disease recommending that liver tests be obtained before therapy, but that routine monitoring is not necessary and that statins can be safety used in patients with nonalcoholic liver disease, and are probably safe in other forms of chronic liver disease and after liver transplantation).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24793441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R97">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
              <annotation>
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">Ooba N, Sato T, Wakana A, Orii T, Kitamura M, Kokan A, Kurata H, et al. A prospective stratified case-cohort study on statins and multiple adverse events in Japan. PLoS One 2014; 9: e96919. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24810427">PubMed Citation</ext-link> (Among 6877 patients started on statins between 2008 and 2010, 139 developed an increase in ALT or AST deemed likely due to the drug with no significant differences among those treated with pra-, ator-, flu-, pita- or rosu-vastatin).</italic>
                </p>
              </annotation>
            </mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R98">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Macedo AF, Taylor FC, Casas JP, Adler A, Prieto-Merino D, Ebrahim S. Unintended effects of statins from observational studies in the general population: systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Med 2014; 12: 51. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of 90 studies of 48 different "unintended effects" of statins with evidence of an increased risk of myopathy [Odds Ratio: OR=2.6] and raised liver enzymes [OR=1.5]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24655568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R99">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drugs for lipids. Treat Guidel Med Lett 2014; 12 (137): 1-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Concise recommendations on management of hyperlipidemia mentions that 1-2% of patients on high doses of statins develop ALT elevations [above 3 times ULN], but that there is not always cross sensitivity to this side effect and that patients with mild-to-moderate ALT elevations can tolerate statins; no discussion of clinically apparent liver).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24419209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R100">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vishwakarma P, Nehra R, Kumar A. Acute hepatic injury with atorvastatin: an unusual occurrence. Indian J Pharmacol 2014; 46: 343-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(63 year old man developed jaundice 2 months after starting 20 mg daily of atorvastatin [bilirubin 5.2 mg/dL, ALT 1124 U/L, Alk P 214 U/L], falling to normal within a month of switching to 10 mg daily of rosuvastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24987187</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R101">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bastida C, Also MA, Pericas JM, Letang E, Tuset M, Mir&#x000f3; JM. [Rhabdomyolysis and severe hepatotoxicity due to a drug-drug interaction between ritonavir and simvastatin]. Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin 2014; 32: 579-82. Spanish. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(52 year old woman with HIV infection on darunavir/ritonavir, lamivudine and raltegravir was switched from atorvastatin [40 mg] to simvastatin [80 mg] daily and developed rhabdomyolysis 3 weeks later [bilirubin 0.5 mg/dL, ALT 787 U/L, CK 34,960 U/L], possibly due to drug-drug interactions between simvastatin and ritonavir).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24913991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R102">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ivandi&#x00107; E, Ba&#x00161;i&#x00107;-Juki&#x00107; N. [Liver damage caused by atorvastatin and cyclosporine in patients with renal transplant]. Acta Med Croatica 2014; 68: 175-8. Croatian. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Ordered).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26012156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R103">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kalantari S, Naghipour M. Statin therapy and hepatotoxicity: appraisal of the safety profile of atorvastatin in hyperlipidemic patients. Adv Biomed Res 2014; 3: 168. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 206 patients started on atorvastatin in a "semi-experimental" study, "in general ALT and AST remained in the normal range").</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25221771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R104">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perdices EV, Medina-C&#x000e1;liz I, Hernando S, Ortega A, Mart&#x000ed;n-Oca&#x000f1;a F, Navarro JM, Pel&#x000e1;ez G, et al. Hepatotoxicity associated with statin use: analysis of the cases included in the Spanish Hepatotoxicity Registry. Rev Esp Enferm Dig 2014; 106: 246-54. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 858 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a Spanish Registry between 1994 and 2012, 47 [5.5%] were attributed to statins [16 atorvastatin, 13 simvastatin, 12 fluvastatin, 4 lovastatin and 2 pravastatin], usually with a hepatocellular pattern of injury, 8.5% with autoimmune features, chronic injury in 19%, and no liver related deaths).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25075655</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R105">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chen GL, Hsiao FY, Dong YH, Shen LJ, Wu FL. Statins and the risk of liver injury: a population-based case-control study. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf 2014; 23: 719-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Among 2165 Taiwanese patients hospitalized for liver injury between 2002 and 2009, use of statins was not more frequent than among 16,600 hospitalized controls, except for use of high doses of rosuvastatin [adjusted odds ratio of 2.29]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4829162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R106">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52.e7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, 31 cases [3.4%] were attributed to statins, including 8 to atorvastatin, 8 simvastatin, 7 rosuvastatin, 4 pravastatin, 2 fluvastatin and 2 lovastatin).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R107">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carrascosa MF, Salcines-Caviedes JR, Lucena MI, Andrade RJ. Acute liver failure following atorvastatin dose escalation: is there a threshold dose for idiosyncratic hepatotoxicity? J Hepatol 2015; 62: 751-2. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(85 year old woman on atorvastatin for more than a year developed jaundice after increasing dose from 40 to 80 mg daily [bilirubin 4.1 mg/dL, ALT 909 U/L, Alk P 415 U/L, CK 4753 U/L, INR 1.71], with transient worsening, but ultimate improvement and resolution).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25463547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R108">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chang CH, Chang YC, Lee YC, Liu YC, Chuang LM, Lin JW. Severe hepatic injury associated with different statins in patients with chronic liver disease: a nationwide population-based cohort study. J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2015; 30: 155-62. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 37,929 Taiwanese persons with chronic liver diesase started on statin therapy for hyperlipidemia between 2005 and 2009, there were 912 incident cases of hospitalization for liver injury, rates being similar for the 6 different statins used [1.94-2.95 per 100,000 person-days], but higher in those on high doses of atorvastatin [40 or 80 mg daily]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25041076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R109">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kim HS, Lee SH, Kim H, Lee SH, Cho JH, Lee H, Yim HW, et al. Statin-related aminotransferase elevation according to baseline aminotransferases level in real practice in Korea. J Clin Pharm Ther 2016; 41: 266-72. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 21,233 Korean patients starting statin therapy between 2009 and 2013, abnormal ALT or AST values above 3 times ULN were more frequent among those with mild baseline elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27015878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R110">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Clarke AT, Johnson PC, Hall GC, Ford I, Mills PR. High dose atorvastatin associated with increased risk of significant hepatotoxicity in comparison to simvastatin in UK GPRD cohort. PLoS One 2016; 11: e0151587. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Analysis of the Clinical Practice Research Database of UK patients initiating statin treatment between 1997 and 2006 identified 71 of 76,411 developing liver dysfunction while on atorvastatin [0.09%] vs 101 of 164,407 on simvastatin [0.06%], rates being higher with higher [40 or 80 mg] vs lower [10 or 20 mg] doses of atorvastatin [0.44% vs 0.07%], but not with higher vs lower doses of simvastatin [0.09% vs 0.05%]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26983033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R111">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang LY, Huang YS, Perng CL, Huang B, Lin HC. Statin-induced liver injury in an area endemic for hepatitis B virus infection: risk factors and outcome analysis. Br J Clin Pharmacol 2016; 82: 823-30. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Have).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27197051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Atorvastatin.R112">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES. Hepatotoxicity of statins and other lipid-lowering agents. Liver Int 2017; 37: 173-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the hepatotoxicity of statins mentions that atorvastatin has been the most frequently implicated statin [accounting for 30-40% of cases] in drug induced liver injury estimated to arise in 1 in 17,000 users, cholestatic in 56% and with autoimmune features in 10% and rarely fatal).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27860156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Atorvastatin.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=atorvastatin+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Atorvastatin: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=atorvastatin">Trials on Atorvastatin: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
