<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Certolizumab" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Certolizumab</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Certolizumab</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Ceritinib" document-type="chapter">Ceritinib</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Cetirizine_Levocetir" document-type="chapter">Cetirizine</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Certolizumab.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Certolizumab.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Certolizumab is a Fab fragment of a monoclonal antibody to human tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF&#x003b1;) which has potent antiinflammatory activity and is used in the therapy of severe rheumatoid arthritis and inflammatory bowel disease. Certolizumab has had limited use and has yet to be specifically linked to instances of idiosyncratic acute liver injury or reactivation of hepatitis B, but is likely to cause similar hepatic injury to what has been described for other TNF&#x003b1; antagonists such as infliximab and adalimumab.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Certolizumab.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Certolizumab (ser" toe liz' ue mab) is a Fab fragment of a humanized recombinant monoclonal antibody to TNF&#x003b1; linked to polyethylene glycol. The monoclonal antibody fragment binds avidly to serum and tissue bound TNF&#x003b1; causing its inactivation and degradation. Inhibition of TNF&#x003b1; activity leads to modulation of the inflammatory and pain pathways activated by this cytokine. The polyethylene glycol alters its pharmacokinetics, prolonging its half-life, and allowing for every 4 week administration. Certolizumab was approved in the United States in 2007 for use in Crohn disease and its indications were subsequently extended to rheumatoid and psoriatic arthritis and ankylosing spondylitis. Certolizumab is considered a disease modifying antirheumatic drug (DMARD) and has been shown to improve symptoms as well as joint and cartilage damage in the inflammatory arthritides. Certolizumab is available as lyophilized powder for reconstitution or in prefilled syringes as 200 mg/1.0 mL under the brand name of Cimzia. The typical dose of certolizumab for Crohn disease is 200 to 400 mg subcutaneously initially and at weeks 2 and 4, followed by 400 mg every 4 weeks. Recommendations vary slightly by indicationCommon side effects include injection site reactions, headache, nausea, abdominal discomfort, diarrhea, skin rash and fever. Severe side effects include bone marrow suppression and hypersensitivity reactions. TNF&#x003b1; antagonists are also capable of causing immune suppression, which can result in reactivation of microbial infections including tuberculosis and hepatitis B.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Certolizumab.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Certolizumab has been associated with a low rate of serum aminotransferase elevations during therapy, similar to the rate found with placebo therapy. The ALT elevations have been transient, mild and asymptomatic, and have rarely required dose modification. Certolizumab has been available for a relatively short period of time, and case reports of clinically apparent hepatic injury due to its use have not been published. Nevertheless, it is likely that certolizumab, like infliximab and adalimumab, is capable of inducing clinically apparent liver injury that resembles autoimmune hepatitis, which generally arises after at least 3 months of use and is associated with a hepatocellular pattern of serum enzyme elevation and autoantibody formation. Autoimmune hepatitis induced by anti-TNF&#x003b1; blocking agents can be severe and self-sustained and require corticosteroid therapy.</p>
          <p>Certolizumab, like other TNF&#x003b1; antagonists, can also be expected to cause reactivation of chronic hepatitis B. Reactivation typically occurs in patients who are inactive HBsAg carriers, with normal serum aminotransferase levels and no or only low levels of HBV DNA in serum. The immune suppression caused by the immunomodulatory agent leads to an increase in HBV replication and rise in serum HBV DNA levels. With stopping the immunosuppression (or between cycles of therapy), restoration of immune function leads to an acute immunological response to the heightened viral replication and a flare of hepatitis, that can be severe and can result in hepatic failure and death. Reactivation in patients with anti-HBc without HBsAg (serologic pattern of previous HBV infection) has been reported only rarely in patients treated with anti-TNF antagonists, and is more common after therapy with rituximab and bone marrow transplantation. The anti-TNF inhibitors have little or no effect on hepatitis C virus levels and have been used safely in patients with chronic hepatitis C.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: E* (unproven but suspected cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Certolizumab.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The mechanism of liver injury due to certolizumab and other TNF&#x003b1; antagonists is not known, but is likely caused by immune modulation and induction of autoimmunity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Certolizumab.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>Most published cases of hepatotoxicity due to anti-TNF&#x003b1; agents have been mild and self-limited. Patients who are to start certolizumab therapy should be screened for evidence of hepatitis B, and those with preexisting HBsAg should be offered prophylaxis with an oral antiviral agent such as lamivudine, tenofovir or entecavir. Patients who develop an autoimmune hepatitis-like syndrome during certolizumab therapy may not recover promptly with stopping the TNF&#x003b1; antagonist and may require corticosteroid therapy. In this event, the corticosteroid dose should be kept to a minimum to control the disease and, ultimately, attempts should be made to withdraw immunosuppression (or decrease to levels used before administration of certolizumab). Rechallenge with another monoclonal antibody based TNF&#x003b1; antagonist after hepatotoxicity from certolizumab has not been reported, but there does not appear to be cross reactivity in hepatic injury between either adalimumab or infliximab and etanercept, which is not a monoclonal antibody, but rather an altered form of the TNF&#x003b1; receptor.</p>
          <p>References on the hepatotoxicity and safety of the anti-TNF necrosis factor agents are given together at the end of the Overview section on the Tumor Necrosis Factor Antagonists.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="AntirheumaticAgents">Antirheumatic Agents</related-object>; Gastrointestinal Agents, Inflammatory Bowel Disease Agents</p>
          <p>Other Drugs in the Subclass, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="TNFAntagonists">Tumor Necrosis Factor Antagonists</related-object>: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Adalimumab">Adalimumab</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Etanercept">Etanercept</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Golimumab">Golimumab</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Infliximab">Infliximab</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Certolizumab.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Certolizumab.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold> REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Certolizumab &#x02013; Cimzia&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antirheumatic Agents; Gastrointestinal Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=certolizumab">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Certolizumab.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCT">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Certolizumab.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Certolizumab Pegol</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://135347437">428863-50-7</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monoclonal antibody</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not available</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td headers="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td headers="hd_h_Certolizumab.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Certolizumab.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 10 February 2017</p>
        <ref-list id="Certolizumab.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Drugs used to treat rheumatic and musculospastic disease. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 517-54.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of hepatotoxicity published in 1999; no mention of tumor necrosis factor antagonists such as infliximab or certolizumab).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reuben A. Hepatotoxicity of immunosuppressive drugs. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2011, pp. 569-91.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of immunosuppressive agents; "the biological immuno-suppressants are largely free from hepatototxicity, with the exception of the TNF alpha antagonists").</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace JL, Sharkey KA. Pharmacotherpay of inflammatory bowel disesae. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 1350-62.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Maini R, St Clair EW, Breedveld F, Furst D, Kalden J, Weisman M, Smolen J, et al. Infliximab (chimeric anti-tumour necrosis factor alpha monoclonal antibody) versus placebo in rheumatoid arthritis patients receiving concomitant methotrexate: a randomised phase III trial. ATTRACT Study Group. Lancet 1999; 354: 1932-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of infliximab vs placebo for 30 weeks in 428 patients with rheumatoid arthritis receiving methotrexate, found no difference in rates of ALT elevations between the two groups [37% vs 29%] and no cases of clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10622295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Menghini VV, Arora AS. Infliximab-associated reversible cholestatic liver disease. Mayo Clin Proc 2001; 76: 84-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(44 year old woman with Crohn disease developed fatigue 19 days after single infusion of infliximab with subsequent jaundice [bilirubin 7.4 rising to 19.2 mg/dL, ALT 149 U/L, Alk P 55 U/L, ANA weakly positive], liver biopsy showing bland cholestasis and abnormalities resolving within 2 months of stopping: Case 1).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11155419</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nathan DM, Angus PW, Gibson PR. Hepatitis B and C virus infections and anti-tumor necrosis factor-. therapy: guidelines for clinical approach. J Gastro Hepatol 2006; 31: 1366-71. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review and proposed guidelines for use of anti-TNF therapy in patients with underlying chronic viral hepatitis; recommended screening for HBV and HCV, careful monitoring during therapy and prophylaxis or early intervention with lamivudine in HBsAg-positive patients).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vassilopoulos D, Calabrese LH. Risks of immunosuppressive therapies including biologic agents in patients with rheumatic diseases and co-existing chronic viral infections. Curr Opin Rheumatol 2007; 19: 619-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of use of anti-TNF agents in patients with chronic hepatitis B, C and HIV infection).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17917544</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sandborn WJ, Feagan BG, Stoinov S, Honiball PJ, Rutgeerts P, Mason D, Bloomfield R, et al.; PRECISE 1 Study Investigators. Certolizumab pegol for the treatment of Crohn's disease. N Engl J Med 2007; 357: 228-38. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of certolizumab for 26 weeks in 662 adults with Crohn disease; "No clinically significant changes in laboratory values occurred in either study group"; no mention of hepatotoxicity or ALT elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17634458</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Domm S, Cinatl J, Mrowietz U. The impact of treatment with tumour necrosis factor-alpha antagonists on the course of chronic viral infections: a review of the literature. Br J Dermatol 2008; 159: 1217-28. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of literature on efficacy and safety of TNF antagonists in patients with chronic hepatitis B and C, recommends screening and monitoring).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18945310</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Fontana RJ, Bonkovsky HL, Watkins PB, Davern T, Serrano J, Yang H, Rochon J; Drug Induced Liver Injury Network (DILIN). Causes, clinical features, and outcomes from a prospective study of drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Gastroenterology 2008; 135: 1924-34. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 300 cases of drug induced liver disease in the US collected from 2004 to 2008, 3 were attributed to etanercept, but none to infliximab, adalimumab or certolizumab).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Li S, Kaur PP, Chan V, Berney S. Use of tumor necrosis factor-alpha(TNF-alpha) antagonists infliximab, etanercept, and adalimumab in patients with concurrent rheumatoid arthritis and hepatitis B or hepatitis C: a retrospective record review of 11 patients. Clin Rheumatol 2009; 28: 787-91. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective analysis of 11 patients with rheumatoid arthritis and either hepatitis B [n=3] or C [n=8] during 3 to 60 months anti-TNF therapy, 3 had transient minimal ALT elevations [peak levels 51, 73 and 51 U/L], without symptoms or jaundice).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19291350</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shao LM, Chen MY, Cai JT. Meta-analysis: the efficacy and safety of certolizumab pegol in Crohn's disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2009; 29: 605-14. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Metaanalysis of safety in 3 controlled trials of certolizumab in 1313 patients with Crohn disease; no increase in serious adverse events except for infections, but no specific data on rates of ALT elevation or liver injury provided).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19183161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smolen J, Landew&#x000e9; RB, Mease P, Brzezicki J, Mason D, Luijtens K, van Vollenhoven RF, et al. Efficacy and safety of certolizumab pegol plus methotrexate in active rheumatoid arthritis: the RAPID 2 study. A randomised controlled trial. Ann Rheum Dis 2009; 68: 797-804. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of methotrexate with or without certolizumab in 619 patients with rheumatoid arthritis; ALT elevations occurred in 5% of patients on methotrexate alone vs 2% on the combination; 5 cases of tuberculosis on certolizumab, but no mention of clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9015207</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shale MJ, Seow CH, Coffin CS, Kaplan GG, Panaccione R, Ghosh S. Review article: chronic viral infection in the anti-tumour necrosis factor therapy era in inflammatory bowel disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2010; 31: 20-34. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Extensive review of literature on effects of anti-TNF therapies on underlying chronic hepatitis B and C; among 28 HBV-infected patients, reactivation was common in those not on antiviral therapy, more frequent with monoclonal antibodies than etanercept; among 110 HCV-infected patients, little evidence of worsening of disease and in some instances a decrease in HCV RNA levels).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19681818</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smith LS, Nelson M, Dolder CR. Certolizumab pegol: a TNF-{alpha} antagonist for the treatment of moderate-to-severe Crohn's disease. Ann Pharmacother 2010; 44: 333-42. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of structure, mechanism of action, pharmacology, safety and efficacy of certolizumab focusing upon Crohn disease; no mention of liver injury or ALT elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20118143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lichtenstein GR, Thomsen O~O, Schreiber S, Lawrance IC, Hanauer SB, Bloomfield R, Sandborn WJ; Precise 3 Study Investigators. Continuous therapy with certolizumab pegol maintains remission of patients with Crohn's disease for up to 18 months. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2010; 8: 600-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 241 patients with Crohn disease continued on certolizumab for up to 80 weeks, 2 patients developed tuberculosis, 1 a lupus-like syndrome, 16 [11%] ANA and 4 [2%] anti-dsDNA reactivity; no mention of liver injury or ALT elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20117244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sokolove J, Strand V, Greenberg JD, Curtis JR, Kavanaugh A, Kremer JM, Anofrei A, et al.; CORRONA Investigators. Risk of elevated liver enzymes associated with TNF inhibitor utilisation in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Ann Rheum Dis 2010; 69: 1612-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective analysis of ALT and AST elevations among 6861 patients with rheumatoid arthritis enrolled in a North American database receiving TNF inhibitors followed for an average of 1.5 years with ~1.7 determinations yearly; any elevation of ALT or AST occurred in 5.4% of visits, &#x0003e;2 times ULN in 0.6%, &#x0003e;5 times ULN in 0.1%; rates slightly higher for those on infliximab or when combined with methotrexate and leflunomide).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20448284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Khokhar OS, Lewis JH. Hepatotoxicity of agents used in the management of inflammatory bowel disease. Dig Dis 2010; 28: 508-18. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the hepatotoxicity of drugs used to treat inflammatory bowel disease focusing upon sulfaxalazine, thiopurines, TNF inhibitors, and methotrexate).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20926880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carroll MB, Forgione MA. Use of tumor necrosis factor alpha inhibitors in hepatitis B surface antigen-positive patients: a literature review and potential mechanisms of action. Clin Rheumatol 2010; 29: 1021-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of literature on anti-TNF therapy in patients with hepatitis B identified 35 cases, 7 cases of reactivation occurred, including 7 of 17 on infliximab but none of 12 on etanercept or 6 on adalimumab; 18 received lamivudine, but only 7 as prophylaxis).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20556450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">P&#x000e9;rez-Alvarez R, D&#x000ed;az-Lagares C, Garc&#x000ed;a-Hern&#x000e1;ndez F, Lopez-Roses L, Brito-Zer&#x000f3;n P, P&#x000e9;rez-de-Lis M, Retamozo S, et al.; BIOGEAS Study Group. Hepatitis B virus (HBV) reactivation in patients receiving tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-targeted therapy: analysis of 257 cases. Medicine (Baltimore) 2011; 90: 359-71. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of literature identified 257 patients with preexisting HBV markers who received anti-TNF therapy, reactivation occurred in 39% of 89 patients with HBsAg [5 had acute liver failure, 4 died], but only 5% of 168 with anti-HBc without HBsAg [1 died]; lamivudine prophylaxis decreased, but did not eliminate reactivation [62% vs 23% in HBsAg carriers).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22033451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brunasso AM, Puntoni M, Gulia A, Massone C. Safety of anti-tumour necrosis factor agents in patients with chronic hepatitis C infection: a systematic review. Rheumatology (Oxford) 2011; 50: 1700-11. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of literature identified 153 patients with chronic hepatitis C treated with anti-TNF agents, mostly etanercept, with only 1 with definite worsening of disease on treatment).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21690185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vassilopoulos D, Calabrese LH. Management of rheumatic disease with comorbid HBV or HCV infection. Nat Rev Rheumatol 2012; 8: 348-57. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Clinical review of chronic hepatitis B and C and the implications in patients with rheumatic disorders with interpretation of virologic markers and recommendations for screening and prophylaxis against HBV during immunosuppressive therapy) </italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22565315</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Aaltonen KJ, Virkki LM, Malmivaara A, Konttinen YT, Nordstr&#x000f6;m DC, Blom M. Systematic review and meta-analysis of the efficacy and safety of existing TNF blocking agents in treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. PLoS One 2012; 7: e30275. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of 26 controlled trials of anti-TNF agents for rheumatoid arthritis found similar rates of efficacy with different agents, but slightly lower rates of adverse events with etanercept, as measured by rates of discontinuation for adverse events [risk ratio=0.71]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22272322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ghabril M, Bonkovsky HL, Kum C, Davern T, Hayashi PH, Kleiner DE, Serrano J, et al.; US Drug-Induced Liver Injury Network. Liver injury from tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1; antagonists: analysis of thirty-four cases. Clin Gastroenterol Hepato 2013; 11: 558-64. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Description of 6 cases of acute liver injury due to anti-TNF agents from the US included 5 women [83%], ages 28 to 54 years, onset after 2-52 weeks of treatment with infliximab [n=3], etanercept [n=2] or adalumimab [n=1], ANA present in 3, [peak bilirubin 1.5-34.2 mg/dL, ALT 384-1687 U/L, Alk P 83-1311 U/L], 5 treated with corticosteroids, but all ultimately recovered).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23333219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Motaparthi K, Stanisic V, Van Voorhees AS, Lebwohl MG, Hsu S. From the Medical Board of the National Psoriasis Foundation: Recommendations for screening for hepatitis B infection prior to initiating anti-tumor necrosis factor-alfa inhibitors or other immunosuppressive agents in patients with psoriasis. J Am Acad Dermatol 2013 Nov 9. [Epub ahead of print]<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Recommendations for screening and monitoring for hepatitis B in patients with psoriasis treated with anti-TNF agents).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24220724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America. An analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of literature of drug induced liver injury in Latin American countries published from 1996 to 2012 identified 176 cases, the most common implicated agents being nimesulide [n=53: 30%], cyproterone [n=18], nitrofurantoin [n=17], antituberculosis drugs [n=13] and flutamide [n=12: 7%]; but none were attributed to a TNF antagonist).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, 6 cases were attributed to TNF antagonists: 1 to adalimumab, 2 etanercept and 3 infliximab, but none to certolizumab or golimumab).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Certolizumab.R28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Petr&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; J, Jar&#x0010d;u&#x00161;ka P, Svajdler M, Pella D, Macejov&#x000e1; Z. Autoimmune hepatitis triggered by adalimumab and allergic reactions after various anti-TNF&#x003b1; therapy agents in a patient with rheumatoid arthritis. Isr Med Assoc J 2015; 17: 256-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (33 year old woman with rheumatoid arthritis developed fatigue after 3 doses of adalimumab [bilirubin not given, ALT 888 U/L, Alk P 348 U/L, ANA positive], biopsy showing interface hepatitis, resolving with prednisolone; later having allergic reactions to etanercept and certolizumab, but responding to anakinra).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26040057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Certolizumab.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Certolizumab/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Certolizumab: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Certolizumab">Trials on Certolizumab: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
