<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Isoflurane" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Isoflurane</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Isoflurane</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2018</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Isocarboxazid" document-type="chapter">Isocarboxazid</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Isoniazid" document-type="chapter">Isoniazid</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Isoflurane.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Isoflurane.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Isoflurane is a commonly used inhalational anesthetic and has an excellent safety record. Isoflurane has been linked to rare instances of severe acute liver injury resembling halothane induced liver injury in small case series and individual case reports.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Isoflurane.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Isoflurane (eye" soe flur' ane) is a widely used major anesthetic agent with rapid onset of action and rapid dispersal. Isoflurane is a halogenated anesthetic, similar in structure and activity to halothane, desflurane, enflurane and sevofurane. Isoflurane is typically given in inhaled concentrations of 0.5% to 3% in oxygen. Because of its pungent odor and somewhat slow onset of action, isoflurane is typically used to maintain anesthesia after induction with other agents such as nitrous oxide, fentanyl and propofol. Isoflurane became available for use in the United States in 1979. Isoflurane must be administered in a controlled situation by a properly trained anesthesiologist or nurse anesthetist.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Isoflurane.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Prospective, serial blood testing often demonstrates minor transient elevations in serum aminotransferase levels in the 1 to 2 weeks after major surgery and halogenated anesthetic agents. Appearance of ALT levels above 10 times the upper limit of normal, however, is distinctly unusual and points to significant hepatotoxicity. Clinically apparent, severe hepatic injury from isoflurane is very rare, only isolated case reports and small case series having been published. The injury is marked by acute elevations in serum aminotransferase levels (5- to 50-fold) and appearance of jaundice within 2 to 21 days of surgery. There are usually minimal increases in alkaline phosphatase and gammaglutamyl transpeptidase levels. Jaundice is usually preceded by a day or two of fever and may be accompanied by rash and eosinophilia. The acute liver injury may be self-limited and resolve within 4 to 8 weeks, but can be severe and associated with acute liver failure. A strong risk factor is previous exposure to any of the halogenated anesthetics and particularly a history of halothane hepatitis or unexplained fever and rash after anesthesia with one of these agents. The differential diagnosis of acute liver injury after surgery and anesthesia is sometimes difficult, and a clinical picture similar to isoflurane hepatitis can be caused by shock or ischemia, other idiosyncratic forms of drug induced liver injury and acute viral or herpes hepatitis.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: B (highly likely cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Isoflurane.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The mechanism of isoflurane hepatotoxicity is suspected to be similar to that of halothane and associated with creation of reactive intermediates. Isoflurane is metabolized to some extent by the microsomal drug metabolizing enzyme CYP 2E1 to a trifluoroacetylated reactive intermediate (TFA) that is capable of binding to multiple intracytoplasmic proteins forming potentially immunogenic adducts. The TFA adducts induce antibodies that can be detected in patients with isoflurane, desflurane as well as halothane hepatotoxicity and are also found in a proportion of health care workers exposed to the volatile anesthetics.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Isoflurane.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>Severity ranges from mild and transient aminotransferase elevations without symptoms or other evidence of liver injury, to a self limited symptomatic acute hepatitis-like reaction to severe, acute hepatic failure. The severity and prognosis may relate in part of patient age, being more severe in the elderly and both milder and less common in children. Obesity may also be both a predisposing factor and predictor of outcome. Chronic liver injury from isoflurane exposure has not been described. Patients with isoflurane induced hepatitis should be cautioned against future exposure to fluorinated hydrocarbon anesthetics such as halothane, enflurane, desflurane or sevoflurane.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="HalogenatedAnestheti">Halogenated Anesthetics</related-object></p>
          <p>Other drugs in the Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Desflurane">Desflurane</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Enflurane">Enflurane</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Halothane">Halothane</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Sevoflurane">Sevoflurane</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Isoflurane.CASE_REPORT">
        <title>CASE REPORT</title>
        <sec id="Isoflurane.Case_1._Isoflurane_hepatotoxi">
          <title>Case 1. Isoflurane hepatotoxicity in a patient with previous history of halothane-induced hepatitis.</title>
          <p>[Modified from: Hasan F. Isoflurane hepatotoxicity in a patient with a previous history of halothane-induced hepatitis. Hepatogastroenterology 1998; 45: 518-22. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9638441">PubMed Citation</ext-link>]</p>
          <p>A 35 year old woman with diabetes and a previous history of elevated ALT levels after halothane exposure underwent arthroscopy under general anesthesia with isoflurane. Her perioperative and postoperative liver profile was normal. Two weeks later, she presented with jaundice. Of interest, she had a history of halothane induced liver injury 1 and 7 years previously, both episodes associated with jaundice and marked serum aminotransferase elevations. On physical examination she was jaundiced and had mild hepatomegaly. Laboratory examination revealed total bilirubin 27.2 mg/dL, ALT 1950 U/L, alkaline phosphatase 226 U/L, albumin 3.5 g/dL, total protein 7.5 g/dL, and prothrombin time 16 sec (normal 11 sec). Complete blood counts were normal. Abdominal ultrasound showed hepatomegaly with increased echogenicity throughout the liver. The gallbladder, common bile duct, spleen and portal veins were normal. Tests for acute hepatitis A, B and C were negative as were autoantibodies. Liver biopsy showed severe, predominantly centrozonal necrosis and cell loss with diffuse inflammatory infiltrates. The patient was treated with supportive measures and the liver function tests improved spontaneously. She was discharged after 16 days of hospitalization and recovered after 12 weeks. Subsequently, she underwent abscess drainage under propofol anesthesia without incident.</p>
          <sec id="Isoflurane.Key_Points">
            <title>Key Points</title>
            <table-wrap id="Isoflurane.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isoflurane</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatocellular (R=25.5)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+ (jaundice, hospitalization)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latency:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 2 weeks</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other medications:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indomethacin, insulin</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Isoflurane.Laboratory_Values">
            <title>Laboratory Values</title>
            <table-wrap id="Isoflurane.T2" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT<break/> (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alk P<break/> (U/L)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilirubin<break/> (mg/dL)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 18, 1987</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Received halothane</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 03, 1987</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1410</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jaundice</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug 12, 1993</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Received halothane</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug 24, 1993</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1830</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jaundice, itching</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sep 17, 1994</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4 hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Received isoflurane</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sep 23, 1994</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1950</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jaundice, liver biopsy</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Normal Values</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;45</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;130</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>&#x0003c;1.2</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T2_1_1_1_5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>* Converted from micromoles to mg/dL.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Isoflurane.Comment">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>Severe isoflurane hepatotoxicity is rare. Most commonly the injury presents with fever and jaundice 3 to 14 days after surgery. Many affected patients have a history of previous halothane or isoflurane exposure. Female gender, as in this patient, is a risk factor. The latency period of halothane anesthetic induced liver dysfunction decreases with the frequency of exposure. Rash occurs in 10% of patients. This is a diagnosis of exclusion, and the most common causes of jaundice postoperatively that require exclusion are sepsis, biliary disease, parenteral nutrition related jaundice and shock or ischemia. Recovery is expected after 3 to 4 months. Rechallenge should be avoided, using total intravenous anesthetic technique whenever possible, which this patient later underwent without difficulty.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Isoflurane.PRODUCT_INFORMATION_Halogenat">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Isoflurane.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Isoflurane &#x02013; Generic, Forane&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Anesthetics, Halogenated</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=isoflurane">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Isoflurane.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTUR">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Isoflurane.T3" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NO</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isoflurane</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://134997135">26675-46-7</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C3-H2-Cl-F5-O</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Isoflurane.T3_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Isoflurane_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Isoflurane chemical structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Isoflurane.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 01 January 2018</p>
        <ref-list id="Isoflurane.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Anesthetic agents. In, Zimmerman, HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999: pp. 457-82.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of hepatotoxicity of anesthetic agents published in 1999; mentions that the newer halogenated anesthetics appear to be safer than halothane, but that hints of liver injury from desflurane and sevoflurane have appeared).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kenna JG. Mechanism, pathology, and clinical presentation of hepatoxicity of anesthetic agents. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013: pp 403-22.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of liver injury from anesthetic agents published in 2013; mentions that a few cases of postoperative liver injury have occurred in patients exposed to isoflurane).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Patel PM, Patel HH, Roth DM. General anesthetics and therapeutic gases. In, Brunton LL, Chabner KA, Knollman KC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 527-64.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics; isoflurane is a commonly used inhalation anesthetic; 99% is excreted unchanged by the lungs and only 0.2% is metabolized by CYP 2E1).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McLaughlin DF, Eger EI 2nd. Repeated isoflurane anesthesia in a patient with hepatic dysfunction. Anesth Analg 1984; 63: 775-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(65 year old woman was found to have liver test abnormalities 11 days after surgery and isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 0.4 mg/dL, ALT 229 U/L, Alk P 900 U/L] which was initially attributed isoflurane, but later shown to be due to biliary obstruction).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6465564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lambert DH. Isoflurane and hepatic dysfunction. Anesth Analg 1985; 64: 458-60. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Letter in response to McLaughlin et al [1984] questioning their interpretation).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2858992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fisher NA, Iwata RT, Eger EI 2nd, Smuckler EA. Hepatic necrosis associated with herpes virus after isoflurane anesthesia. Anesth Analg 1985; 64: 1131-3. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(62 year old man developed fever 4 days after surgery and isoflurane anesthesia followed by diarrhea on day 9 with progressive illness leading to death by day 14 accompanied by mild liver test abnormalities [bilirubin 0.8 rising to 1.2 mg/dL, ALT 21 rising to 207 U/L], with evidence of herpes viruses found in liver on autopsy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2996384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gr&#x000e9;goire S, Smiley RK. Acute hepatitis in a patient with mild factor IX deficiency after anesthesia with isoflurane. CMAJ 1986; 135: 645-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(33 year old man developed fatigue, fever and jaundice 6 to 8 days after surgery and isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin ~4 mg/dL, ALT 2500 U/L, Alk P 190 U/L] with recovery in two months; also received Factor IX IV, raising possibility of short incubation period &#x0201c;non-A, non-B hepatitis&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3756695</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Webster JA. Acute hepatitis after isoflurane anesthesia. CMAJ 1986; 135: 1343-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Letter in response to Gr&#x000e9;goire [1986] contesting conclusions).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3779567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carrigan TW, Straughen WJ. A report of hepatic necrosis and death following isoflurane anesthesia. Anesthesiology 1987; 67: 581-3. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(44 year old woman developed acute liver injury starting 2 days after surgery and isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 9.6 mg/dL, AST &#x0003e;2000 U/L, LDH &#x0003e;4000 U/L], progressing to death by day 4; no rash, fever or eosinophilia and liver injury possibly due to ischemia).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3662087</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stoelting RK, Blitt CD, Cohen PJ, Merin RG. Hepatic dysfunction after isoflurane anesthesia. Anesth Analg 1987; 66: 147-53. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of 45 FDA cases of suspected isoflurane hepatotoxicity by 4 expert anesthesiologists, only 36% of cases were considered as &#x0201c;might be&#x0201d; related).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3813057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brunt EM, White H, Marsh JW, Holtmann B, Peters MG. Fulminant hepatic failure after repeated exposure to isoflurane anesthesia: a case report. Hepatology 1991; 13: 1017-21. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(26 year old obese woman with history of multiple surgeries and exposures to halogenated anesthetics developed nausea 11 days after isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 22 mg/dL, ALT 948 U/L, Alk P 270 U/L], ultimately requiring liver transplant).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2050317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zimmerman HJ. Even isoflurane. Hepatology 1991; 13: 1251. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Editorial in response to Brunt [1991] providing overview of anesthetic induced liver injury and suggesting that isoflurane be added to the list of agents causing it).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2050339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gunza JT, Pashayan AG. Postoperative elevation of serum transaminases following isoflurane anesthesia. J Clin Anesth 1992; 4: 336-41. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(42 year old woman developed asymptomatic and immediate ALT elevation [774 U/L on day 1] without jaundice after isoflurane anesthesia, with fall to normal in 2 weeks, a pattern more typical of ischemic injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1419017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kharasch ED, Thummel KE. Identification of cytochrome P450 2E1 as the predominant enzyme catalyzing human liver microsomal defluorination of sevoflurane, isoflurane, and methoxyflurane. Anesthesiology 1993; 79: 795-807. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Human microsomes were used to assess metabolism of sevoflurane: CYP 2E1 was the major if not sole enzyme catalyzing defluorination of sevoflurane and others).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8214760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Scheider DM, Klygis LM, Tsang TK, Caughron MC. Hepatic dysfunction after repeated isoflurane administration. J Clin Gastroenterol 1993; 17: 168-70. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(45 year old woman developed ALT elevations starting 3 days after isoflurane anesthesia [peak bilirubin 2.5 mg/dL, ALT 320 U/L, Alk P 900 U/L], with recurrence on reexposure to isoflurane [bilirubin 0.5 mg/dL, ALT 90 U/L, Alk P 400 U/L], resolving rapidly).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8409323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Slayter KL, Sketris IS, Gulanikar A. Halothane hepatitis in a renal transplant patient previously exposed to isoflurane. Ann Pharmacother 1993; 27: 101. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(37 year old man with 2 previous exposures to isoflurane developed serum enzyme elevations starting 7 days after halothane anesthesia [peak bilirubin 1.3 mg/dL, ALT 926 U/L, Alk P 472 U/L], resolving within 2 months).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8431608</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gunaratnam NT, Benson J, Gandolfi AJ, Chen M. Suspected isoflurane hepatitis in an obese patient with a history of halothane hepatitis. Anesthesiology 1995; 83: 1361-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(47 year old severely obese man with a history of halothane hepatitis developed fever 1 day and jaundice 10 days after surgery under isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 1.4 rising to 5.5 mg/dL, ALT 1576 U/L, 4% eosinophils], resolving within 40 days; also had anti-TFA-protein antibodies during the acute episode).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8533932</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gelven PL, Cina SJ, Lee JD, Nichols CA. Massive hepatic necrosis and death following repeated isoflurane exposure: case report and review of the literature. Am J Forensic Med Pathol 1996; 17: 61-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(30 year old woman had outpatient surgery under isoflurane anesthesia and died unexpectedly 2 days later, autopsy showed fat, inflammation and massive necrosis; role for isoflurane difficult to assess).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8838473</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sinha A, Clatch RJ, Stuck G, Blumenthal SA, Patel SA. Isoflurane hepatotoxicity: a case report and review of the literature. Am J Gastroenterol 1996; 91: 2406-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(67 year old man developed marked ALT elevations [&#x0003e;1000 U/L] starting 12 days after isoflurane anesthesia without symptoms, fever or jaundice and with rapid recovery; also had late appearance of anti-TFA antibodies).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8931426</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Weitz J, Kienle P, B&#x000f6;hrer H, Hofmann W, Theilmann L, Otto G. Fatal hepatic necrosis after isoflurane anaesthesia. Anaesthesia 1997; 52: 892-5. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(36 year old woman developed nausea, abdominal pain and fever 2 days after surgery using isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 4.8 mg/dL, ALT 1000 U/L, INR 2.1], ultimately undergoing liver transplantation but dying by day 12; anti-TFA negative, massive centrolobular necrosis in explant suggestive of ischemia).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9349074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hasan F. Isoflurane hepatotoxicity in a patient with a previous history of halothane-induced hepatitis. Hepatogastroenterology 1998; 45: 518-22. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(35 year old woman developed hepatitis 2 weeks after isoflurane anesthesia, having had 2 previous episodes of jaundice after halothane [peak bilirubin 27.4 mg/dL, ALT 1950 U/L, Alk P 226 U/L], resolving within 12 weeks. Case 1).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9638441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Meldrum DJ, Griffiths R, Kenna JG. Gallstones and isoflurane hepatitis. Anaesthesia 1998; 53: 905-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(65 year old woman developed abnormal enzymes 3 days after surgery and isoflurane anesthesia with cholestatic pattern [peak bilirubin 0.6 mg/dL, ALT 250 U/L, Alk P 609 U/L], gallstones and dilated bile ducts found, but patient also had anti-TFA-adducts; only possibly due to isoflurane).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9849287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nishiyama T, Yokoyama T, Hanaoka K. Liver function after sevoflurane or isoflurane anaesthesia in neurosurgical patients. Can J Anaesth 1998; 45: 753-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Prospective analysis of ALT, AST, Alk P and bilirubin 1,2,3,7 and 14 days after sevo- or isoflurane [n=45 each] showed minimal increases in ALT and AST peaking at 7 days; elevated in ~15%, no patient was symptomatic or jaundiced).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9793665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Turner GB, O'Rourke D, Scott GO, Beringer TR. Fatal hepatotoxicity after re-exposure to isoflurane: a case report and review of the literature. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2000; 12: 955-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(76 year old woman developed fever on day 1 and jaundice day 6 after isoflurane anesthesia, but she also had sepsis, atrial fibrillation, amiodarone and ciprofloxacin exposures; subsequently had acute liver failure and died on day 7; no anti-TFA and bland centrizonal necrosis with cholestasis and fat on autopsy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10958225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martin JL, Keegan MT, Vasdev GM, Nyberg SL, Bourdi M, Pohl LR, Plevak DJ. Fatal hepatitis associated with isoflurane exposure and CYP2A6 autoantibodies. Anesthesiology 2001; 95: 551-3. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(55 year old woman developed severe hepatitis starting 4 days after isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 8.0 mg/dL, ALT 6564 U/L, Alk P 691 U/L mg/dL and lactic acidosis, pH 7.09], without fever or eosinophilia; immunologic testing showed little anti-CYP 2E1, but high titers of anti-CYP 2A6 and presence of TFA-labeled microsomal proteins).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11506133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Malnick SD, Mahlab K, Borchardt J, Sokolowski N, Attali M. Acute cholestatic hepatitis after exposure to isoflurane. Ann Pharmacother 2002; 36: 261-3. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(70 year old woman developed jaundice and pruritus 2 weeks after isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 17 mg/dL, ALT 1533 U/L, Alk P 203 U/L], resolving over ensuing 4 months).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11847945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Njoku DB, Shrestha S, Soloway R, Duray PR, Tsokos M, Abu-Asab MS, Pohl LR, West AB. Subcellular localization of trifluoroacetylated liver proteins in association with hepatitis following isoflurane. Anesthesiology 2002; 96: 757-61. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(66 year old man developed fever and jaundice 7 days after isoflurane [repeat exposure] anesthesia [bilirubin 10.9 mg/dL, ALT 3973 U/L, PT 20.6 sec] and early coma, but eventual recovery; liver biopsy showed centrolobular necrosis, fat and cholestasis with TFA modified proteins).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11873055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russo MW, Galanko JA, Shrestha R, Fried MW, Watkins P. Liver transplantation for acute liver failure from drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Liver Transpl 2004; 10: 1018-23. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15390328">PubMed Citation</ext-link><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among ~50,000 liver transplants done in the United States between 1990 and 2002, 137 [0.2%] were done for idiosyncratic drug induced acute liver failure, of which 3 were attributed to halothane and 1 to isoflurane, but none to other halogenated anesthetics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson E, Jerlstad P, Bergqvist A, Olsson R. Fulminant drug-induced hepatic failure leading to death or liver transplantation in Sweden. Scand J Gastroenterol 2005; 40: 1095-101. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16165719">PubMed Citation</ext-link><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(36 years of reporting to Swedish registry identified 103 cases of acute liver failure due to drugs, of which 16 were attributed to halothane [ranking #1] but none to other halogenated anesthetics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ihtiyar E, Algin C, Haciolu A, Isiksoy S. Fatal isoflurane hepatotoxicity without re-exposure. Indian J Gastroenterol 2006; 25: 41-2. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(68 year old man developed immediate rise in ALT [7200 U/L], AST [20200 U/L] and LDH [20,730 U/L] on day 3 after cholecystectomy under isoflurane anesthesia, but also 2 days after episode of hypotension: died on day 6, possibly due to ischemic hepatitis).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16567898</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Fontana RJ, Bonkovsky HL, Watkins PB, Davern T, Serrano J, Yang H, Rochon J; Drug Induced Liver Injury Network (DILIN). Causes, clinical features, and outcomes from a prospective study of drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Gastroenterology 2008; 135: 1924-34. <italic toggle="yes">
</italic><annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 300 cases of drug induced liver disease collected in the US between 2003 and 2008, 2 cases were attributed to desflurane, 1 to sevoflurane, but none to isoflurane).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">C&#x000f4;t&#x000e9; G, Bouchard S. Hepatotoxicity after desflurane anesthesia in a 15 month old child with Mobius syndrome after previous exposure to isoflurane. Anesthesiology 2007; 107: 843-5. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(15 month old boy developed ALT of 6,180 U/L and INR of 2.7 on postoperative day 3 after desflurane anesthesia [having had 2 previous exposures to isoflurane] with rapid recovery; bilirubin not mentioned and patient also received acetaminophen).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18073559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Her C. Acetaminophen-induced, not desflurane-induced, hepatotoxicity. Anesthesiology 2008; 109: 570-1. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Letter in response to C&#x000f4;t&#x000e9; and Bouchard suggesting that the liver injury was due to acetaminophen rather than desflurane using Rumack-Matthew nomogram and in view of the high ALT levels).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18719456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reuben A, Koch DG, Lee WM; Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Drug-induced acute liver failure: results of a U.S. multicenter, prospective study. Hepatology 2010; 52: 2065-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1198 patients with acute liver failure enrolled in a US prospective study between 1998 and 2007, 133 were attributed to drug induced liver injury, of which 2 were attributed to anesthetic agents, 1 halothane and 1 isoflurane).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Peiris LJ, Agrawal A, Morris JE, Basnyat PS. Isoflurane hepatitis-induced liver failure: a case report. J Clin Anesth 2012; 24: 477-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (77 year old woman developed jaundice 2 days after a hemicolectomy for which she received isoflurane anesthesia [bilirubin 4.4 mg/dL, ALT 1063 U/L, Alk P 108 U/L], with rapid worsening and death on day 4 from multiorgan failure with massive, centrolobular coagulative necrosis on autopsy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22658370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES, Bergmann OM, Bj&#x000f6;rnsson HK, Kvaran RB, Olafsson S. Incidence, presentation and outcomes in patients with drug-induced liver injury in the general population of Iceland. Gastroenterology 2013; 144: 1419-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In a population based study of drug induced liver injury from Iceland, 96 cases were identified over a 2 year period, none of which were due to anesthetic agents).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nishiyama T. Effects of repeat exposure to inhalation anesthetics on liver and renal function. J Anaesthesiol Clin Pharmacol 2013; 29: 83-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Retrospective analysis of 206 patients who underwent anaesthesia twice within a 1 year period found higher rates of ALT elevations within 16 days after isoflurane [60-83%] than sevoflurane [24-30%] or propofol-fentanyl [12-17%], most elevations being less than twice ULN and no differences between first and second exposure).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23493664</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Safari S, Motavaf M, Seyed Siamdoust SA, Alavian SM. Hepatotoxicity of halogenated inhalational anesthetics. Iran Red Crescent Med J 2014; 16: e20153. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of the volatile halogenated anesthetics).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25593732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lin J, Moore D, Hockey B, Di Lernia R, Gorelik A, Liew D, Nicoll A. Drug-induced hepatotoxicity: incidence of abnormal liver function tests consistent with volatile anaesthetic hepatitis in trauma patients. Liver Int 2014; 34: 576-82. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Retrospective analysis of records from 1556 patients admitted to a trauma unit during 2008 identified 47 cases of possible volatile anesthetic related liver injury, including 12 who developed ALT levels above 200 U/L of whom 11 had fever and 6 eosinophilia, but none were jaundiced or developed acute liver failure).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23944929</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America. An analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. (Systematic review of literature of drug induced liver injury in Latin American countries published from 1996 to 2012 identified 176 cases of which 5 [3%] were attributed to halothane and caused acute liver failure, while<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">no other volatile anesthetic was listed).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Isoflurane.R41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52.e7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, 2 were attributed to isoflurane, 1 to sevoflurane, but none to halothane, enflurane or desflurane).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Isoflurane.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=isoflurane/AE+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI+OR+hepatitis,+toxic%5BMH%5D)+AND+(%222009/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Isoflurane: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=isoflurane">Trials on Isoflurane: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
