<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Mepacrine" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Mepacrine</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Mepacrine</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Memantine" document-type="chapter">Memantine</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Mepenzolate" document-type="chapter">Mepenzolate</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Mepacrine.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Mepacrine.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Mepacrine (also known as quinacrine and atabrine) is an acridine derivative initially used in the therapy and prevention of malaria and later as an antiprotozoal and immunomodulatory agent. Mepacrine causes a yellowing of the sclera that is not due to liver injury, but also can cause serum enzyme elevations during therapy (particularly in high doses) and has been linked to rare instances of clinically apparent acute liver injury which can be severe and has resulted in fatalities.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Mepacrine.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Mepacrine, also known as quinacrine (kwin' a crin) or atabrine, is an acridine derivative that was developed in the 1920s and extensively used as an antimalarial agent by the U.S. military in the South Pacific during World War II. It was recognized as causing a yellowing of the skin that resembled jaundice, but had few serious side effects, particularly at the low doses used for prophylaxis against malaria. Mepacrine was subsequently replaced by chloroquine and other more effective and better tolerated agents for malaria. Mepacrine also has activity against Giardia lamblia parasites as well as antiinflammatory and immunomodulatory activity, but is not approved for use in these conditions in the United States. Mepacrine continues to be used off-label, however, in lupus erythematosus, particularly for the dermatologic manifestations. While not commercially available or approved for use in the United States, mepacrine can be obtained overseas, via the internet and in some compounding pharmacies. The typical dose is 100 mg daily, and it is often combined with hydroxychloroquine, an accepted and widely used agent for rheumatologic disorders. Side effects of mepacrine are not uncommon, but are generally mild including fatigue, abdominal discomfort, cramps, nausea, diarrhea, headache and dizziness. In high doses, mepacrine causes yellowing of the skin that can be mistaken for jaundice. It has occasionally been used to induce factitious illness. Serious side effects include lichen planus, exfoliative dermatitis and aplastic anemia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Mepacrine.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Mepacrine has been reported to cause elevations in serum enzymes, but the frequency of such changes is unknown, arising after 1 to 6 weeks with a mixed pattern of enzyme elevations and resolving within 1 to 2 months of stopping. Most patients are asymptomatic and liver enzyme elevations can resolve with, and sometimes without dose modification. Clinically apparent liver injury from mepacrine has also been reported, but the clinical features of the injury have not been well defined. Because mepacrine causes a yellowing of the skin, jaundice is not a reliable finding and most reports of liver injury from mepacrine have not included bilirubin elevations. Nevertheless, several instances of acute liver failure and death have been attributed to mepacrine therapy, although the reports usually predated the availability of tests for hepatitis A, B and C and often lacked histological documentation. Mepacrine has also been implicated in cases of aplastic anemia and in hypersensitivity reactions with exfoliative dermatitis, suggestive of Stevens Johnson syndrome, conditions that can be associated with liver injury that may be severe.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: E* (unproven but suspected cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Mepacrine.Mechanism_of_Liver_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Liver Injury</title>
          <p>The mechanism of mepacrine hepatotoxicity is not known, but likely to be due to an idiosyncratic reaction to an intermediate of its metabolism. Mepacrine has a prolonged half-life and is highly protein bound. It is preferentially taken up by the skin and liver, but details of its metabolism have not been defined.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Mepacrine.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>Most instances of liver injury attributed to mepacrine have been mild, with nonspecific symptoms and serum enzyme elevations without jaundice. The liver test abnormalities resolve rapidly with stopping therapy. There is no reason to suspect that there is cross sensitivity to hepatotoxicity between mepacrine and other antimalarial agents. Mepacrine has no structural similarity to chloroquine and other antimalarial drugs.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="AntimalarialAgents">Antimalarial Agents</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Mepacrine.CASE_REPORT">
        <title>CASE REPORT</title>
        <sec id="Mepacrine.Case_1._Serum_aminotransferase">
          <title>Case 1. Serum aminotransferase elevations during mepacrine therapy.</title>
          <p>[Modified from: Gibb W, Isenberg DA, Snaith ML. Mepacrine induced hepatitis. Ann Rheum Dis 1985; 44: 861-2. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4083944">PubMed Citation</ext-link>]</p>
          <p>A 37 year old woman with an undifferentiated connective tissue disorder and features of lupus erythematosus developed fatigue, anorexia, pruritus and yellowing of the skin and eyes six weeks after starting mepacrine in an initial dose of 100 mg daily that was then increased to 300 mg daily. Previous trials of hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine had been unsuccessful and associated with side effects of nausea and blurred vision. She had no history of liver disease or alcohol abuse, and liver tests had been normal in the past. Her other medical conditions included migraine headaches, asthma and recurrent bronchitis. Other medications were not mentioned. Mepacrine was stopped, but 4 weeks later she was found to have abnormal liver tests. Serum bilirubin was 0.3 mg/dL, ALT 210 U/L, AST 107 U/L, alkaline phosphatase 160 U/L and GGT 264 U/L. She had a mild eosinophilia of 680 cells per &#x003bc;L. Tests for hepatitis A, B and cytomegalovirus were negative. Liver tests gradually improved and were normal two months later. Skin and sclera remained yellow for two months after mepacrine was stopped.</p>
          <sec id="Mepacrine.Key_Points">
            <title>Key Points</title>
            <table-wrap id="Mepacrine.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
              <table>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mepacrine (300 mg daily)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed (R=~3.8)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1+ (symptoms and enzyme elevations, but no jaundice)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latency:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 weeks</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 months</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other medications:</td>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None mentioned</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="Mepacrine.Comment">
            <title>Comment</title>
            <p>A woman with a lupus-like illness who was intolerant of hydroxychloroquine was switched to mepacrine and developed nonspecific symptoms, and was found to have yellowing of the skin, suggesting significant liver injury. Laboratory testing, however, showed a normal serum bilirubin and only moderate serum aminotransferase elevations. She improved upon stopping mepacrine. While the systemic symptoms (fatigue, anorexia, itching) were likely due to the mepacrine, they may not have been due to liver injury. Fatigue is a not uncommon side effect of mepacrine therapy, particularly with the high doses that were used. Similarly, yellowing of the skin and sclera occur with high doses of mepacrine, probably because of granular deposits of mepacrine in the skin and nail beds, reflecting the yellow color of the medication itself (it is an acridine dye). The yellowish discoloration resolves within a few weeks of stopping mepacrine; the dark staining of nail beds can persist longer. While this report is widely cited as evidence of the hepatotoxicity of mepacrine, it more likely represents the frequent occurrence of nonspecific side effects and mild enzyme elevations with use of high doses. Cases of severe hepatitis with jaundice due to mepacrine have been reported, but are rare and were not well documented, occurring before the availability of tests for hepatitis A, B and C and accurate radiologic imaging of the liver. Liver injury can accompany the severe dermatologic side effects and aplastic anemia that occurs rarely with mepacrine therapy, but the liver injury is generally overshadowed by the other systemic effects.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Mepacrine.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Mepacrine.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Mepacrine &#x02013; Generic</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antimalarial Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=zileuton">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Mepacrine.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTURE">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Mepacrine.T2" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mepacrine</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://134971848">83-89-6</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C23-H30-Cl-N3-O</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Mepacrine.T2_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Mepacrine_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Mepacrine Chemical Structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Mepacrine.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 01 February 2017</p>
        <ref-list id="Mepacrine.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Antimalarials. Hepatic injury from antimicrobial agents. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 623.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of hepatotoxicity published in 1999; mentions that quinacrine was found to cause rare instances of hepatocellular injury when used during World War II, but rarely since, usually in the context of prolonged therapy).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vinetz JM, Clain J, Bounkeua V, Eastman RT, Fidock D. Chemotherapy of malaria. In, Brunton LL, Chabner B, Knollman B, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 1383-418.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Livingood CS, Dieuaide FR. Untoward reactions attributable to atabrine. JAMA 1945: 129: 1091-3. Not in PubMed<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Summary of the dermatologic adverse reactions to atabrine focusing upon atypical lichen planus concludes that &#x0201c;the military value of atabrine in suppressing vivax malaria and curing falciparum malaria far outweighs untoward effects which have been attributed with reason to the use of the drug&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drake JR, Moon HD. Atabrine dermatitis and associated aplastic anemia. Calif Med 1945; 65: 154-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Description of 3 types of dermatitis [lichenoid, eczematoid and exfoliative], aplastic anemia [9 cases, 7 fatal] and &#x0201c;acute yellow atrophy&#x0201d; [8 cases, 2 with dermatitis, one with aplastic anemia and 1 fatal]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21001532</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Agress CM. Atabrine as a cause of fatal exfoliative dermatitis and hepatitis. J Am Med Assoc 1946; 131: 14-21. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of literature found no cases of hepatitis attributed to mepacrine, but authors report 5 cases with exfoliative dermatitis and some degree of hepatitis in patients receiving mepacrine for malaria; 5 Chinese men, ages 24 to 36 years, developed fever and rash within a few days of starting mepacrine with complicated subsequent courses, 3 dying of multiorgan failure and autopsies showing marked hepatic necrosis).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21025602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bower AG. Untoward effects of Atabrine. Calif Med 1946; 65: 157. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Short commentary mentions that the side effects of mepacrine can include nausea, nervousness, psychosis, disorientation, urticaria, exfoliative dermatitis and lichen planus; no mention of liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18731100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Custer RP. Aplastic anemia in soldiers treated with atabrine(quinacrine). Am J Med Sci 1946; 212: 211-24. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(&#x0201c;Atabrine proved superior to quinine for suppressive treatment, being more effective and better tolerated by the troops. It was generally regarded as harmless and, for the most part, with good reason.&#x0201d; Careful review of autopsies, however, showed an increase in aplastic anemia in atabrine treated soldiers leading to this analysis of 57 cases from the South Pacific, for an incidence of 2.8 cases per 100,000 troops, 47 received atabrine for 1-34 months, 25 had atabrine dermatitis; no mention of hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20996966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Findlay GM. The toxicity of mepacrine in man. Trop Dis Bull 1947; 44: 763-79. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Extensive review of the toxicity of mepacrine focusing on lichenoid dermatitis, toxic psychosis and aplastic anemia mentions that liver lesions were found in 10 of 47 autopsied cases of aplastic anemia, with findings typical of &#x0201c;infective hepatitis&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18906096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shumacker HB Jr, Ziperman HH. Unusual case of apparent malingering. Arch Surg 1950; 60: 861-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(49 year old woman had multiple episodes of abdominal pain, fever and apparent jaundice, undergoing multiple surgical procedures without evidence of gallstones or biliary obstruction, eventually being diagnosed as having factitious illness and mepacrine induced yellowing of the skin [fabricated &#x0201c;jaundice&#x0201d;]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15411312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Craddock WL. Toxic hepatitis presumably produced by massive prolonged ingestion of atabrine: a case report with autopsy findings. Mil Surg 1950; 107: 199-201. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(32 year old man who presented with jaundice and fatal variceal hemorrhage gave a history of excessive atabrine ingestion, because of unrealistic fear of malaria; no mention of alcohol use or whether cirrhosis was present and no routine liver tests provided).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15438774</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Page F. Treatment of lupus erythematosus with mepacrine. Lancet 1951; 2 (6687): 755-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 18 patients with lupus erythematosus treated with mepacrine [100 to 300 mg daily], all except one had a clinical response, some of which were complete; only one patient had a serious adverse event [dermatitis], but no mention of liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14874500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Harvey G, Cochrane T. The treatment of lupus erythematosus with mepacrine (Atabrine). J Invest Dermatol 1953; 21: 99-104. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 62 patients with lupus erythematosus treated with mepacrine [usually 200 mg daily], 37 had an excellent or good response and 8 had complications, 2 with severe nausea and 6 dermatitis; no mention of liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13084972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rovelstad RA, Stauffer MH, Mason HL, Steinhilber RM. The simulation of jaundice by action of quinacrine (atabrine). Gastroenterology 1957; 33: 937-47. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Two patients with recurrent gastrointestinal symptoms and jaundice that was due to unacknowledged use of mepacrine to simulate disease, and review of literature on its hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13490686</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marczynska-Robowska M. Acute hepatitis due to intoxication with atabrine. Helv Paediatr Acta 1960; 15: 307-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(5 year old boy developed yellow skin 5 days after starting atabrine [100 mg every 3 days] for suspected malaria and was found to have high fever and jaundice 3 days later [bilirubin 10.3 mg/dL], with worsening fever, stupor and death one week later).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13766606</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gibb W, Isenberg DA, Snaith ML. Mepacrine induced hepatitis. Ann Rheum Dis 1985; 44: 861-2. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(37 year old woman with discoid lupus intolerant of chloroquine developed yellow skin and fatigue 6 weeks after starting mepacrine in a dose of 300 mg daily [bilirubin 0.3 mg/dL, ALT 210 U/L, Alk P 160 U/L, eosinophilia 688/&#x003bc;L], resolving within 2 months of stopping: Case 1).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4083944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wallace DJ. The use of quinacrine (Atabrine) in rheumatic diseases: a reexamination. Semin Arthritis Rheum 1989; 18: 282-96. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Extensive review of mepacrine in rheumatic disease based upon the literature and personal experience mentions that its first use in lupus was in 1939, but it became more widely used after a report in 1951 [Page], subsequently being studied in at least 20 clinical trials with 771 patients yielding beneficial responses in 73%, with onset of action after 3-4 weeks of 100 mg daily, side effects being mild and well tolerated at this dose; mentions a single report of hepatotoxicity [Gibb 1985]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2658071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Scoazec JY, Krolak-Salmon P, Casez O, Besson G, Thobois S, Kopp N, Perret-Liaudet A, et al. Quinacrine-induced cytolytic hepatitis in sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease. Ann Neurol 2003; 53: 546-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(3 patients with Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease developed liver test abnormalities 7, 25 and 42 days after starting 300 mg daily of mepacrine [bilirubin not given, ALT 3-30 times ULN, Alk P 2-8 times ULN], returning to normal within 3-4 weeks of stopping, subsequent autopsies showing mild lobular necrosis, portal inflammation and bile duct inflammation and fibrosis).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12666126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Mepacrine.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52.e7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, none were attributed to antimalarial medications or to mepacrine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Mepacrine.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(zileuton/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Mepacrine: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=zileuton">Trials on Mepacrine: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
