<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Oxazepam" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Oxazepam</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Oxazepam</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Oxaprozin" document-type="chapter">Oxaprozin</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Oxcarbazepine" document-type="chapter">Oxcarbazepine</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Oxazepam.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Oxazepam.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Oxazepam is an orally available benzodiazepine used in the therapy of anxiety and acute alcohol withdrawal syndromes. As with most benzodiazepines, oxazepam therapy has not been associated with serum aminotransferase or alkaline phosphatase elevations, and clinically apparent liver injury from oxazepam has not been reported and must be very rare, if it occurs at all.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Oxazepam.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Oxazepam (ox az' e pam) is a benzodiazepine that is used largely in the therapy of anxiety and alcohol withdrawal states. The antianxiety (anxiolytic) activity of the benzodiazepines is mediated by their ability to enhance gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) mediated inhibition of synaptic transmission through binding to the GABA A receptor. Oxazepam was approved in the United States in 1965 and currently is still in use, but has been replaced in large part by other benzodiazepines with better pharmacokinetics and tolerance. Current indications are for management of anxiety disorders and acute alcohol withdrawal and it is considered particularly useful in older patients. Oxazepam is available in capsules or tablets of 10, 15 and 30 mg in several generic forms and formerly under the brand name Serax. The recommended oral dose for adults is 10 to15 mg three to four times daily. Somewhat higher doses are used for the severe anxiety of alcohol withdrawal states. The most common side effects of oxazepam are dose related and include drowsiness, lethargy, ataxia, dysarthria and dizziness. Tolerance develops to these side effects, but tolerance may also develop to the effects on anxiety.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Oxazepam.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Oxazepam, like other benzodiazepines, is rarely associated with serum ALT elevations, and clinically apparent liver injury from oxazepam is extremely rare, if it occurs at all. There have been no case reports of symptomatic, acute liver injury from oxazepam. Cases of clinically apparent liver injury have been reported with other benzodiazepines including alprazolam, chlordiazepoxide, clonazepam, diazepam, flurazepam and triazolam. The clinical pattern of acute liver injury from benzodiazepines is typically cholestatic and mild-to-moderate in severity with a latency of 1 to 6 months. Fever and rash are uncommon as is autoantibody formation.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: E (Unlikely cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Oxazepam.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>Oxazepam is metabolized by the liver to inactive metabolites which are excreted in the urine. Liver injury from benzodiazepines is probably due to the toxic effects of a rarely produced intermediate metabolite.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Oxazepam.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>The case reports of hepatic injury due to benzodiazepines were followed by prompt and complete recovery upon stopping the medication, without evidence of residual or chronic injury. No cases of acute liver failure or chronic liver injury due to oxazepam have been described. There is no information about cross reactivity with other benzodiazepines, but some degree of cross sensitivity may occur.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="BenzodiazepineDrugs">Benzodiazepines</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Oxazepam.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Oxazepam.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Oxazepam &#x02013; Generic, Serax&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Benzodiazepines, Antianxiety Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=oxazepam">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Oxazepam.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTURE">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Oxazepam.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxazepam</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://134977280">604-75-1</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C15-H11-Cl-N2-O2</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Oxazepam.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Oxazepam_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Oxazepam Chemical Structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Oxazepam.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 24 January 2017</p>
        <ref-list id="Oxazepam.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Benzodiazepines. Psychotropic and anticonvulsant agents. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 491-3.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of benzodiazepines and liver injury published in 1999; mentions rare instances of cholestatic hepatitis have been reported due to alprazolam, chlordiazepoxide, diazepam, flurazepam, and triazolam, and hepatocellular injury with clorazepate and clotiazepam, but no reports of hepatic injury with lorazepam, oxazepam or temazepam).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Larrey D, Ripault MP. Anxiolytic agents. Hepatotoxicity of psychotropic drugs and drugs of abuse. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2013, p. 455.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of sedative induced liver injury mentions that rare instances of acute liver injury [usually cholestatic] have been reported with alprazolam, bentazepam, clotiazepam, chlordiazepoxide, diazepam, flurazepam and triazolam, and a hepatitis-like pattern has been reported with clonazepam and clorazepat, but no mention is made for oxazepam).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mihic SJ, Harris RA. Hypnotics and sedatives. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 457-80.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Davion T, Capron-Chivrac D, Andrejak M, Capron JP. [Hepatitis due to antiepileptic agents] Gastroenterol Clin Biol 1985; 9: 117-26. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of anticonvulsants; among benzodiazepines, cases of cholestatic hepatitis have been linked to chlordiazepoxide and diazepam, but liver injury from this class of drugs is exceptionally rare).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3920108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lewis JH, Zimmerman HJ. Drug- and chemical-induced cholestasis. Clin Liver Dis 1999; 3: 433-64, vii. Erratum in: Clin Liver Dis 1999; 3: 917. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of drug induced cholestatic syndromes, listing many causes including chlordiazepoxide and flurazepam; &#x0201c;Benzodiazepines may cause cholestatic injury, although this is rare&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11291233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson E. Hepatotoxicity associated with antiepileptic drugs. Acta Neurol Scand 2008; 118: 281-90. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of all anticonvulsants focusing upon phenytoin, valproate, carbamazepine; &#x0201c;Furthermore, hepatoxicity has not been convincingly shown to be associated with the use of benzodiazepines&#x0201d;).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18341684</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reuben A, Koch DG, Lee WM; Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Drug-induced acute liver failure: results of a U.S. multicenter, prospective study. Hepatology 2010; 52: 2065-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1198 patients with acute liver failure enrolled in a US prospective study between 1998 and 2007, 133 were attributed to drug induced liver injury, but none were linked to oxazepam or other benzodiazepines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Molleston JP, Fontana RJ, Lopez MJ, Kleiner DE, Gu J, Chalasani N: Drug-induced Liver Injury Network. Characteristics of idiosyncratic drug-induced liver injury in children: results from the DILIN prospective study. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr 2011; 53: 182-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 30 children with suspected drug induced liver injury, half [n=15] were due to antimicrobials [minocycline 4, INH 3, azithromycin 3] and the rest largely due to CNS agents and anticonvulsants; none were due to oxazepam or other benzodiazepines).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21788760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drugs for insomnia. Treat Guidel Med Lett 2012; 10 (119): 57-60. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Guidelines for therapy of insomnia mentions that benzodiazepines are controlled substances and, when used for sleep, may impair next day performance).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22777275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES, Bergmann OM, Bj&#x000f6;rnsson HK, Kvaran RB, Olafsson S. Incidence, presentation and outcomes in patients with drug-induced liver injury in the general population of Iceland. Gastroenterology 2013; 144: 1419-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In a population based study of drug induced liver injury from Iceland, 96 cases were identified over a 2 year period, but none were attributed to oxazepam or any other benzodiazepine, despite the fact that millions of prescriptions for them are filled yearly).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America. An analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of literature on drug induced liver injury in Latin American countries published from 1996 to 2012 identified 176 cases, none of which were attributed to a benzodiazepine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Oxazepam.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-1352.e7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, no cases were attributed to oxazepam or any other benzodiazepine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Oxazepam.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Oxazepam/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Oxazepam: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Oxazepam">Trials on Oxazepam: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
