<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Risperidone" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Risperidone</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Risperidone</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2018</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Riociguat" document-type="chapter">Riociguat</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Ritonavir" document-type="chapter">Ritonavir</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Risperidone.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Risperidone.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Risperidone is an atypical antipsychotic that is used widely in the treatment of mania and schizophrenia. Risperidone therapy is associated with serum aminotransferase elevations and in rare instances has been linked to clinically apparent acute liver injury.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Risperidone.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Risperidone (ris per' i done) is a benzisoxazole derivative which appears to act as a dopamine type 2 (D2) and serotonin (5-HT2) receptor antagonist. Risperidone is indicated for treatment of schizophrenia and as monotherapy or combination therapy for acute manic or mixed episodes of bipolar I disorder in adults. Risperidone is also used for management of irritability with autistic disorder in children and adolescents. Risperidone was approved for use in the United States in 1993 and it is still widely used. Risperidone is available as tablets of 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 3 and 4 mg generically and under the brand name of Risperdal. Oral solutions for pediatric use are available as are orally disintegrating tablets and formulations for parenteral administration. The typical initial dose in adults is 1 mg once or twice daily, with increase in dose to as high as 8 mg daily based upon indications, efficacy and tolerance. Common side effects include somnolence, fatigue, restlessness, dizziness, dry mouth, increased saliva, constipation, increased appetite and weight gain. Rare, but potentially severe adverse events include cerebrovascular events, tardive dyskinesia, neuroleptic malignant syndrome, orthostatic hypotension, suicidal ideation and behavior, seizures, diabetes and agranulocytosis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Risperidone.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Liver test abnormalities may occur in up to 30% of patients on long term therapy with risperidone, usually arising within the first 8 weeks of treatment. The ALT elevations are usually mild, transient and may resolve even with continuation of medication. Instances of more marked ALT and alkaline phosphatase elevations, with or without symptoms and with or without jaundice, have also been reported. The onset of injury typically occurs within a few days of starting risperidone and resolves rapidly with stopping. Instances of acute liver injury with jaundice arising several months and even years after starting risperidone have also been reported. The pattern of serum enzyme elevations is typically cholestatic, but cases with hepatocellular and mixed patterns have also been described. Immunoallergic manifestations (rash, fever, eosinophilia) are rare; a case of autoimmune hepatitis apparently triggered by risperidone therapy was been published, but most cases do not have autoimmune features.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: C (probable rare cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Risperidone.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>The mechanism by which risperidone causes serum ALT elevations is not known. Risperidone is extensively metabolized by the cytochrome P450 system (CYP 2D6) to its active metabolite. Some instances of liver injury may be due to nonalcoholic fatty liver disease caused by weight gain that occurs in at least one-quarter of treated patients and can be as much as 30 kg, generally during the first 1 to 2 years of therapy. In large series, however, the minor ALT elevations that occur on therapy have not correlated well with weight gain.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Risperidone.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>The serum aminotransferase elevations that occur on risperidone therapy are usually self-limited and often do not require dose modification or discontinuation of therapy. No instances of acute liver failure or vanishing bile duct syndrome have been attributed to risperidone. A single case of autoimmune hepatitis due to risperidone has been published. There may be some cross reactivity to liver injury between risperidone and quetiapine, but usually not with clozapine and olanzapine.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="AntipsychoticAgents">Antipsychotic Agents</related-object>, Atypicals</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Risperidone.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Risperidone.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Risperidone &#x02013; Generic, Risperdal&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antipsychotic Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=Risperidone">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Risperidone.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTU">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Risperidone.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risperidone</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://135018248">106266-06-2</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C23-H27-F-N4-O2</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Risperidone.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Risperidone_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Risperidone Chemical Structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Risperidone.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 04 June 2018</p>
        <ref-list id="Risperidone.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Risperidone.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meyer JM. Pharmacotherapy of psychosis and mania. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 417-56.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Larry D. Hepatotoxicity of psychotropic drugs and drugs of abuse. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 2nd ed. New York: Informa Healthcare USA, 2007, pp. 507-26.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of psychiatric agents mentions that at least 10 cases of liver injury have been ascribed to risperidone, some with steatosis and weight gain and others with acute clinical jaundice).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Risperidone for chronic schizophrenia. Med Lett Drugs Ther 1994; 36: 33-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Brief review of efficacy and safety of risperidone shortly after its approval in the United States; common side effects are asthenia, sedation and difficulty concentrating, orthostatic hypotension and weight gain; no mention of liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7511777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fuller MA, Simon MR, Freedman L. Risperidone-associated hepatotoxicity. J Clin Psychopharmacol 1996; 16: 84-5. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Two cases; 64 year old man developed jaundice 6 weeks after starting risperidone [bilirubin 16.1 mg/dL, ALT 297 U/L, Alk P 119 U/L], resolving upon stopping; 68 year old woman developed lethargy 1 year after starting risperidone [bilirubin 0.7 mg/dL, ALT 341 U/L, Alk P 174 U/L], resolving rapidlly upon stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8834428</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kumra S, Herion D, Jacobsen LK, Briguglia C, Grothe D. Case study: risperidone-induced hepatotoxicity in pediatric patients. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry 1997; 36: 701-5. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective review of 13 children on risperidone; 2 developed elevated ALT levels [108 and 144 U/L] with weight gain [16 and 5 kg] on long term risperidone [7 and 17 months], resolution on stopping risperidone even without much weight loss).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9136506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Geller WK, Zuiderwijk PB. Risperidone-induced hepatotoxicity? J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry 1998; 37: 246-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Letter disagreeing with comments of Kumra [1997], arguing against routine ALT monitoring for patients on risperidone).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9519624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Landau J, Martin A. Is liver function monitoring warranted during risperidone treatment? J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry 1998; 37: 10: 1007-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Overweight 13 year old girl found to have ALT elevations [164 U/L] 3 days after starting risperidone and steatohepatitis on biopsy; no values before starting therapy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9785708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Benazzi F. Risperidone-induced hepatotoxicity. Pharmacopsychiatry 1998; 31: 241. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(25 year old woman treated with increasing doses of risperidone [to 6 mg/day] had 20 kg weight gain and fatigue; ALT rose from 13 [pre] to 277 U/L [month 4] without jaundice and fell to normal 1 month after stopping drug).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9930641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Phillips EJ, Liu BA, Knowles SR. Rapid onset of risperidone-induced hepatotoxicity. Ann Pharmacother 1998; 32: 843-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(81 year old man developed jaundice within 2 days of starting risperidone [bilirubin 3.6 mg/dL, ALT 101 U/L, Alk P 244 U/L], resolving 2 weeks after stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9681106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Allison DB, Mentore JL, Heo M, Chandler LP, Cappelleri JC, Infante MC, Weiden PJ. Antipsychotic-induced weight gain: a comprehensive research synthesis. Am J Psychiatry 1999; 156: 1686-96. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Systematic review of 81 articles on weight change with antipsychotics, using change after 10 weeks to compare agents: clozapine +5.7, olanzapine +4.2, chlorpromazine +4.2, quetiapine +2.5, risperidone +1.7, loxapine +0.6, haloperidol +0.5, ziprasidone +0.3, molindone -0.1, and pimozide -2.7 kg).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10553730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Whitworth AB, Liensberger D, Fleischhacker WW. Transient increase of liver enzymes induced by risperidone: two case reports. J Clin Psychopharmacol 1999; 19: 475-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Two cases; 22 year old man had ALT elevation [106 U/L] 16 days after starting risperidone,which improved with lowering dose from 6 to 5 mg/day; 19 year old man had ALT elevation [43 U/L] which fell to normal despite continuing risperidone therapy).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10505592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Szigethy E, Wiznitzer M, Branicky LA, Maxwell K, Findling RL. Risperidone-induced hepatotoxicity in children and adolescents? A chart review study. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol 1999; 9: 93-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective study of 38 children and adolescents on risperidone for ~15 months; only 1 had ALT elevation [46 U/L], degree of surveillance unclear; abstract only).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10461819</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Conley RR. Conley RR. Risperidone side effects. J Clin Psychiatry 2000; 61 Suppl 8: 20-3. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of side effects of risperidone, but no mention of hepatotoxicity or ALT elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10811239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Krebs S, Dormann H, Muth-Selbach U, Hahn EG, Brune K, Schneider HT. Risperidone-induced cholestatic hepatitis. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2001; 13: 67-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(37 year old man developed rises in ALT [140 U/L] and GGT [260 U/L] within days of starting risperidone, that continued on haloperidol [ALT 100 U/L] and olanzapine [ALT 160 U/L]; peak bilirubin 1.6 mg/dL; biopsy showed &#x0201c;cholestatic hepatitis&#x0201d;; tests fell to normal ~1 month after discontinuation).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11204814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cordeiro Q Jr, Elkis H. Pancreatitis and cholestatic hepatitis induced by risperidone. J Clin Psychopharmacol 2001; 21: 529-30. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(32 year old man developed abdominal pain and jaundice 1 week after starting risperidone [bilirubin 2.8 mg/dL, ALT 366 U/L, Alk P 367 U/L, amylase 1617 U/L], resolving rapidly with stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11593080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dumortier G, Cabaret W, Stamatiadis L, Saba G, Benadhira R, Rocamora JF, Aubriot-Delmas B, et al. [Hepatic tolerance of atypical antipsychotic drugs]. Encephale 2002; 28: 542-51. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of literature on liver injury due to atypical antipsychotics).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12506267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mouradian-Stamatiadis L, Dumortier G, Januel D, Delmas BA, Cabaret W. Liver function tests during treatment with antipsychotic drugs: a case series of 23 patients. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry 2002; 26: 1409-11. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(23 hospitalized patients on atypical antipsychotics, 6 had ALT or AST elevations by day 14, ALT 48-158 U/L, 2 on risperidone, 2 on olanzapine and one on amisulpride; 1 on risperidone required discontinuation).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12502031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Haberfellner EM, Honsig T. Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis: a possible side effect of atypical antipsychotics. J Clin Psychiatry 2003; 64: 851. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Three patients with weight gain [24-26 kg] had ALT elevations [47-91 U/L] on olanzapine or risperidone for ~4 years; ultrasound suggested fatty liver).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12934993</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Prior TI, Baker GB. Interactions between the cytochrome P450 system and the second-generation antipsychotics. J Psychiatry Neurosci 2003; 28: 99-112. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the interactions of the atypical antipsychotics with the P450 system; clozapine is metabolized by CYP1A2 and 3A4 and possibly 2C9 and 2D6; risperidone by CYP2D6 and possibly 3A4; olanzapine by CYP1A2 and possibly 2D6; quetiapine and ziprasidone by CYP3A4).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12670127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bender S, Grohmann R, Engel RR, Degner D, Dittmann-Balcar A, Ruther E. Severe adverse drug reactions in psychiatric inpatients treated with neuroleptics. Pharmacopsychiatry 2004; 37 (Suppl 1): S46-53. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Severe adverse drug reactions among 35,293 inpatients; adverse events more common with atypicals [0.5-0.9%] than typical antipsychotic agents [0.02-0.2%], increased liver enzymes was the most common adverse reaction to olanzapine, 4th in frequency to clozapine, 6th to haloperidol, 7th to risperidone; no mention of hepatitis or acute liver failure).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15052514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Holtmann M, Kopf D, Mayer M, Bechtinger E, Schmidt MH. Risperidone-associated steatohepatitis and excessive weight-gain. Pharmacopsychiatry 2003; 36: 206-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(17 year old woman had significant weight gain [35 kg] and ALT elevations [108 U/L] on clozapine that worsened when switched to risperidone; ultrasound showed hypo-echogenicity suggestive of fatty liver; ALT levels decreased after stopping risperidone and a weight loss of 5 kg).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14571356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Choice of an antipsychotic. Med Lett Drugs Ther 2003; 45: 102-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Risperidone is a second generation antipsychotic with the highest rate of galactorrhea, gynecomastia and sexual dysfunction; no mention of liver injury).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14679353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Aman MG, Arnold LE, McDougle CJ, Vitiello B, Scahill L, Davies M, McCracken JT, et al. Acute and long-term safety and tolerability of risperidone in children with autism. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol 2005; 15: 869-84. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(8 week trial of risperidone vs placebo in 101 children and adolescents; ALT levels rose to &#x0003e;2 times ULN in 2 risperidone- vs no placebo-recipients).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16379507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Llinares Tello F, Hern&#x000e1;ndez Prats C, Bosacoma Ros N, P&#x000e9;rez Mart&#x000ed;nez E, Climent Grana E, Navarro Polo JN, Ordov&#x000e1;s Baines JP. Acute cholestatic hepatitis probably associated with risperidone. Int J Psychiatry Med 2005; 35: 199-205. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(64 year old man developed rising serum enzymes between days 2 and 5 of risperidone treatment [bilirubin 0.5 mg/dL, ALT 186 U/L, Alk P 1326 U/L], values falling to near normal 2 weeks after stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16240976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Radzik J, Grotthus B, Leszek J. [Disorder of liver functions in a schizophrenic patient after long-term risperidone treatment&#x02014;case report]. Psychiatr Pol 2005; 39: 309-13. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(51 year old man developed jaundice after 4 years of risperidone therapy [bilirubin 2.5 mg/dL, AST 49 U/L, normal Alk P and GGT], possibly representing Gilbert syndrome and minor AST elevations from risperidone; unclear whether abnormalities resolved on stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15881625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pae CU, Lim HK, Kim TS, Kim JJ, Lee CU, Lee SJ, Lee C, et al. Naturalistic observation on the hepatic enzyme changes in patients treated with either risperidone or olanzapine alone. Int Clin Psychopharmacol 2005; 20: 173-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective analysis found ALT elevations more common among 145 patients on olanzapine [25%] than 298 on risperidone [13%] and particularly &#x0003e;3 times ULN [7.6% vs 2.8%]; no instances of jaundice or hepatitis).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15812269</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Esposito D, Brocvielle H, Becquemont L, Hardy P, Chouinard G, Corruble E. Risperidone-induced immunoallergic hepatitis. Am J Psychiatry 2005; 162: 1984. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(28 year old man developed enzyme elevations 7 weeks and symptoms 8 weeks after starting risperidone [bilirubin normal, ALT 522 U/L], resolving within 3 weeks of stopping; smooth muscle antibody positive).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Legaz Huidobro ML, Gonz&#x000e1;lez Carro P, P&#x000e9;rez Rold&#x000e1;n F, Soto Fern&#x000e1;ndez S, de Pedro Esteban A, Cuesta Dom&#x000ed;nguez R. [Autoimmune hepatitis after risperidone-induced cholestatic hepatitis]. Gastroenterol Hepatol 2005; 28: 135-6. Spanish. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(36 year old woman developed jaundice 10 days after starting risperidone [bilirubin rising from 15 to 29 mg/dL, ALT 818 U/L, Alk P 627 U/L, ANA of 1:320]; ALT continued to rise for 3 weeks [peak 1185 U/L] and prednisone was started with rapid response, but relapse [ALT 843 U/L, ANA 1:1280] when corticosteroids stopped, biopsy showing features of autoimmune hepatitis which was again controlled by prednisone and later with azathioprine alone).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15771859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perlis RH, Baker RW, Zarate CA Jr, Brown EB, Schuh LM, Jamal HH, Tohen M. Olanzapine versus risperidone in the treatment of manic or mixed States in bipolar I disorder: a randomized, double-blind trial. J Clin Psychiatry 2006; 67: 1747-53. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Trial of 3 weeks of olanzapine [n=165] vs risperidone [n=164] for bipolar illness; greater weight gain [16% vs 4%] and ALT elevations [mean increase 15.7 U/L vs 1 U/L] with olanzapine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17196055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rettenbacher MA, Baumgartner S, Eder-Ischia U, Edlinger M, Graziadei I, Hofer A, Huber R, et al. Association between antipsychotic-induced elevation of liver enzymes and weight gain: a prospective study. J Clin Psychopharmacol 2006; 26: 500-3. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Prospective study of 67 patients started on atypical antipsychotics [10 on risperidone]; ALT elevations were more frequent in 14 patients who gained &#x0003e;7% of body weight than in 53 who did not [50% vs 19%] and mean changes in ALT, AST and GGT were greater; all were transient, asymptomatic and not associated with bilirubin elevations).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16974192</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wright TM, Vandenberg AM. Risperidone- and quetiapine-induced cholestasis. Ann Pharmacother 2007; 41: 1518-23. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(30 year old man developed jaundice after 8 years of therapy with risperidone and lithium [bilirubin 4.7 mg/dL, ALT 99 U/L, Alk P 267 U/L], resolving with change of risperidone to ziprasidone, but recurring 3 weeks after starting quetiapine, after tolerating olanzapine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17666578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Atasoy N, Erdogan A, Yalug I, Ozturk U, Konuk N, Atik L, Ustundag Y. A review of liver function tests during treatment with atypical antipsychotic drugs: a chart review study. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry 2007; 31: 1255-60. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Retrospective analysis on 194 patients on atypical antipsychotics; ALT &#x0003e;3 times ULN occurred in 27%, often in first month; among 29 receiving risperidone, 28% had ALT elevations, but elevations were modest and none &#x0003e;3 times ULN).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17600607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sikich L, Frazier JA, McClellan J, Findling RL, Vitiello B, Ritz L, Ambler D, et al. Double-blind comparison of first- and second-generation antipsychotics in early-onset schizophrenia and schizo-affective disorder: findings from the treatment of early-onset schizophrenia spectrum disorders (TEOSS) study. Am J Psychiatry 2008; 165: 1420-31. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Prospective trial of molindone [1st generation antipsychotic agent] vs olanzapine or risperidone [2nd generation agents] for schizophrenia in 199 youths found similar rates of efficacy [34-50%], but more weight gain [mean 6.1 kg] and ALT elevations with olanzapine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18794207</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Erdogan A, Atasoy N, Akkurt H, Ozturk D, Karaahmet E, Yalug I, Yalug K, et al. Risperidone and liver function tests in children and adolescents: a short-term prospective study. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry 2008; 32: 849-57. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 120 children and adolescents prospectively followed for one month on risperidone therapy, 52.5% had mild ALT elevations, but only 1 subject had ALT &#x0003e;3 times ULN [ALT 225 U/L, Alk P 641 U/L, bilirubin 0.4 mg/dL], resolving with discontinuation; no correlation with weight gain, which occurred in 57%).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Fontana RJ, Bonkovsky HL, Watkins PB, Davern T, Serrano J, Yang H, Rochon J; Drug Induced Liver Injury Network (DILIN). Causes, clinical features, and outcomes from a prospective study of drug-induced liver injury in the United States. Gastroenterology 2008; 135: 1924-34. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 300 cases of drug induced liver disease in the US collected between 2004 and 2008; several antidepressants [duloxetine, sertaline, fluoxetine, amitryptilline], but none of the atypical antipsychotic agents were implicated).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Torrent C, Amann B, Sanchez-Moreno J, Colom F, Feinares M, Comes M, Rosa AR, et al. Weight gain in bipolar disorder: pharmacological treatment as a contributing factor. Acta Psychiatr Scand 2008; 118: 4-18. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of frequency of weight gain in patients treated for bipolar disorders, most weight gain occurred with clozapine and olanzapine, but some weight gain also with quetiapine, risperidone, lithium, valproate and gabapentin; not with aripiprazole, ziprasidone, carbamazepine or lamotrigine).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18498432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Parsons B, Allison DB, Loebel A, Williams K, Giller E, Romano S, Siu C. Weight effects associated with antipsychotics: a comprehensive database analysis. Schizophr Res 2009; 110: 103-10. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Analysis of weight gain in 21 placebo controlled trials [~3300 patients]; average monthly weight gain in pounds was +0.1 with placebo, +0.8 olanzapine, 0.6 risperidone, -0.3 ziprasidone; a 5% increase in weight occurred after one year in 13% of placebo, 39% haloperidol, 20% ziprasidone, 45% risperidone and 60% olanzapine treated subjects).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Paulzen M, Orfanos S, Gr&#x000fc;nder G. Remission of drug-induced hepatitis after switching from risperidone to paliperidone. Am J Psychiatry 2010; 167: 351-2. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(43 year old woman with schizophrenia developed jaundice on risperidone and clozapine therapy [bilirubin not given, ALT 75 U/L, Alk P 6 times ULN], improving on switching from risperidone to paliperidone and lowering clozapine dosage).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20194492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lin CH, Kuo CC, Chou LS, Chen YH, Chen CC, Huang KH, Lane HY. A randomized, double-blind comparison of risperidone versus low-dose risperidone plus low-dose haloperidol in treating schizophrenia. J Clin Psychopharmacol 2010; 30: 518-25. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Controlled trial of 6 weeks of risperidone alone vs lower dose risperidone and haloperidol in 88 patients with schizophrenia; no change in mean ALT or AST levels in either group and no mention of hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20814315</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Erdogan A, Karaman MG, Ozdemir E, Yurteri N, Tufan AE, Kurcer MA. Six months of treatment with risperidone may be associated with nonsignificant abnormalities of liver function tests in children and adolescents: a longitudinal, observational study from Turkey. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol 2010; 20: 407-13. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 102 children or adolescents [ages 2-18 years] treated with risperidone for more than 6 months, serum enzyme elevations occurred in 38%, but were usually transient and mild and isolated Alk P elevations only; only one child had ALT rise above twice normal [ALT 225 U/L, GGT 27 U/L, bilirubin 0.5 mg/dL], which resolved within one month of stopping; weight gain averaged 5.5 kg at 6 months).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20973711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Karaman MG, Erdo&#x0011f;an A, Tufan E, Yurteri N, Ozdemir E, Ankarali H. Liver function tests in children and adolescents receiving risperidone treatment for a year: a longitudinal, observational study from Turkey. Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract 2011; 15: 204-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 100 children or adolescents treated with risperidone for more than 6 months, liver tests were abnormal in 21%, but none had symptoms and only one child had an ALT level above 3 times ULN, which resolved rapidly upon stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22121930</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Copur M, Erdogan A. Risperidone rechallenge for marked liver function test abnormalities in an autistic child. Recent Pat Endocr Metab Immune Drug Discov 2011; 5: 237-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(5 year old boy with autism was found to have elevations in serum enzymes during risperidone therapy, which resolved on stopping, but did not recur when risperidone was restarted).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21913889</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Greil W, H&#x000e4;berle A, Schuhmann T, Grohmann R, Baumann P. Age and adverse drug reactions from psychopharmacological treatment: data from the AMSP drug surveillance programme in Switzerland. Swiss Med Wkly 2013; 143: w13772. (Among 39,728 patients treated with psychiatric medications in Swiss hospitals between 2001 and 2010 who were monitored in a drug surveillance program, rates of severe adverse events were similar in those above and below the age of 60 [1.6% vs 1.8%], although weight gain and ALT elevations were less frequent in the elderly [details not provided]).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23821346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">L&#x000f3;pez-Torres E, S&#x000fc;veges A, Pe&#x000f1;as-LLed&#x000f3; EM, Do&#x000f1;a A, Dorado P, LLerena A, Berecz R. Liver enzyme abnormalities during antipsychotic treatment: a case report of risperidone-associated hepatotoxicity. Drug Metabol Drug Interact 2014; 29: 123-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(19 year old man with schizophrenia developed fatigue and weight loss 3 weeks after starting risperidone [bilirubin normal, ALT 778, Alk P normal], resolving within 2 months of stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24598833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America. An analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Systematic review of literature of drug induced liver injury in Latin American countries published from 1996 to 2012 identified 176 cases, but none were attributed to risperidone or other atypical antipsychotic medications).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52.e7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury enrolled in a US prospective study between 2004 and 2013, five were attributed to atypical antipsychotics [3 quetiapine, 2 olanzapine], but none to risperidone).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drugs for psychotic disorders. Med Lett Drugs Ther 2016; 58 (1510): 160-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of medications available in the US for therapy of psychotic disorders; mentions that olanzapine and ziprasidone can cause DRESS syndrome, but does not mention ALT elevations or hepatotoxicity for any of the agents discussed).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27960194</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Morl&#x000e1;n-Coarasa MJ, Arias-Loste MT, Ortiz-Garc&#x000ed;a de la Foz V, Mart&#x000ed;nez-Garc&#x000ed;a O, Alonso-Mart&#x000ed;n C, Crespo J, Romero-G&#x000f3;mez M, et al. Incidence of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease and metabolic dysfunction in first episode schizophrenia and related psychotic disorders: a 3-year prospective randomized interventional study. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 2016; 233: 3947-52. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Among 191 schizophrenic patients treated with an atypical antipsychotic agent for at least 3 years, surrogate markers for steatosis arose in 48 [25%], most of whom had a 7% increase in body weight [n=44: 92%], increase in trigylercides [54%], total cholesterol [52%], and waist circumference [68%]; changes in regard to fatty liver did not vary by specific antipsychotic agent [12 received risperidone]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27620899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Risperidone.R49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Saglam O, Bahsi R, Akkoca Y, Filik L. Risperidone-induced hepatotoxicity in a patient addicted to synthetic cannabinoid. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2016; 28: 360-1. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (31 year old man developed fatigue 3 months after starting risperidone to treat cannabinoid addiction [bilirubin 2.3 mg/dL, ALT 890 U/L, Alk P 736 U/L], resolving within 2 weeks of stopping).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26825144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Risperidone.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Risperidone/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Risperidone: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Risperidone">Trials on Risperidone: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
