<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Ropinirole" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Ropinirole</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Ropinirole</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Romidepsin" document-type="chapter">Romidepsin</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Rosiglitazone" document-type="chapter">Rosiglitazone</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Ropinirole.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Ropinirole.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Ropinirole is a selective dopamine receptor agonist used in the therapy of Parkinson disease. Ropinirole therapy is associated with low rate of transient serum enzyme elevations during treatment and has been implicated in rare cases of acute liver injury.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Ropinirole.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Ropinirole (roe pin' i role") is a synthetic, nonergot derivative dopamine receptor agonist that has selective activity for the D2 class of dopamine receptors and little agonist activity for the D1 class. For this reason, ropinirole may be better tolerated than bromocriptine or pergolide, which act on both classes of dopamine receptors. Ropinirole was approved for use in the United States in 1997 for the therapy of symptomatic Parkinson disease. Indications were later expanded to include restless legs syndrome. Ropinirole is available in tablets of 0.25, 0.50, 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 mg under the brand name of Requip. Ropinirole is typically initiated in low doses, with adjustment upwards based upon tolerance and clinical effects. In treatment of Parkinson disease, the typical dose of ropinirole is 3 to 6 mg daily in three divided doses, often but not always in combination with levodopa/carbidopa. Ropinirole can be initiated more quickly than bromocriptine or pergolide and does not cause the profound hypotension and nausea that are typical of the ergot derivatives. Rolinirole is also approved for use in restless legs syndrome, typically starting at 0.25 mg daily, 1 to 3 hours before bedtime, and increasing the dose slowly based upon tolerance and effect. Common side effects of ropinirole include somnolence, fatigue, vivid dreams, anxiety, confusion, depression, dizziness, headache and gastrointestinal upset, symptoms that are typical of dopaminergic stimulation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Ropinirole.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Ropinirole has been reported to cause serum aminotransferase or alkaline phosphatase elevations in a small proportion of patients, but these abnormalities are usually mild, asymptomatic and self-limiting even without dose adjustment. Ropinirole has been implicated in a small number of cases of acute liver injury, but the clinical characteristics and typical pattern of enzyme elevations has not been characterized. In one case report, the time to onset was 2 months and the pattern of liver enzyme elevations was mixed and associated with marked jaundice. Immunoallergic and autoimmune features were not present. The injury resolved within 2 months of stopping. Thus, ropinirole can cause acute, clinically apparent liver injury with jaundice, but it is rare.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: D (possible, rare cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Ropinirole.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>Ropinirole is extensively metabolized in the liver, largely by the cytochrome P450 system (CYP 1A2) to inactive metabolites. Liver injury may be caused by production of a toxic or immunogenic intermediate of its metabolism.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Ropinirole.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>Instances of liver injury attributed to ropinirole have been mild to moderate and self-limiting. No instances of acute liver failure or chronic injury have been reported.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="AntiparkinsonAgents">Antiparkinson Agents</related-object></p>
          <p>Other Drugs in the Subclass, Dopamine Receptor Agonists: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Apomorphine">Apomorphine</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Bromocriptine">Bromocriptine</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Pergolide">Pergolide</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Pramipexole">Pramipexole</related-object>, <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="Rotigotine">Rotigotine</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Ropinirole.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Ropinirole.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Ropinirole &#x02013; Generic, Requip&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antiparkinson Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=Ropinirole">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Ropinirole.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCTUR">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Ropinirole.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ropinirole</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://135028992">91374-20-8</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C16-H24-N2-O.Cl-H</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Ropinirole.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Ropinirole_Structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Ropinirole Chemical Structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Ropinirole.REFERENCES">
        <title>REFERENCES</title>
        <p>References updated: 21 July 2017</p>
        <ref-list id="Ropinirole.REFERENCES.reflist0">
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Antiparkinsonism drugs. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 715-7.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of hepatotoxicity published in 1999; among anticholinergic agents, "only trihexyphenidyl has been incriminated in hepatic injury"; other antiparkinsonism drugs discussed include levodopa, lergotrile [no longer available], pergolide and bromocriptine, but not ropinirole).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Larrey D, Ripault MP. Hepatotoxicity of psychotropic drugs and drugs of abuse. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier Inc, 2013, pp. 443-62.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of hepatotoxicity of agents acting on the central nervous system).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Standaert DG, Roberson ED. Treatment of central nervous system degenerative disorders. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman&#x02019;s the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, pp. 609-28.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sethi KD, O'Brien CF, Hammerstad JP, Adler CH, Davis TL, Taylor RL, Sanchez-Ramos J, et al. Ropinirole for the treatment of early Parkinson disease: a 12-month experience. Ropinirole Study Group. Arch Neurol 1998; 55: 1211-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(147 patients with early Parkinson disease [not on levodopa] were randomized to receive ropinirole or placebo; no mention of ALT elevations or hepatic adverse events).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9740115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hauser RA, Molho E, Shale H, Pedder S, Dorflinger EE. A pilot evaluation of the tolerability, safety, and efficacy of tolcapone alone and in combination with oral selegiline in untreated Parkinson's disease patients. Tolcapone De Novo Study Group. Mov Disord 1998; 13: 643-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 83 patients with Parkinson disease treated with tolcapone with or without selegiline for 8 weeks, ALT elevations occurred in 1 patient [2%] on tolcapone alone).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9686768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lambert D, Waters CH. Comparative tolerability of the newer generation antiparkinsonian agents. Drugs Aging 2000; 16: 55-65. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of mechanism of action, tolerability and safety of selegiline, pramipexole, ropinirole, tolcapone and entacapone in Parkinson disease).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10733264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reuben A, Koch DG, Lee WM; Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Drug-induced acute liver failure: results of a U.S. multicenter, prospective study. Hepatology 2010; 52: 2065-76. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 1198 patients with acute liver failure enrolled in a US prospective study between 1998 and 2007, 133 were attributed to drug induced liver injury, but none were attributed to agents used for Parkinson disease). </italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hening WA, Allen RP, Ondo WG, Walters AS, Winkelman JW, Becker P, Bogan R, et al; SP792 Study Group. Rotigotine improves restless legs syndrome: a 6-month randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in the United States. Mov Disord 2010; 25: 1675-83. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Among 505 patients with restless leg syndrome treated with one of 4 doses of transdermal rotigotine or placebo for 6 months, symptom scores improved with higher doses [2 or 3 mg/24 hours] and side effects included application site reactions, nausea, somnolence, headache and insomnia, but there were no liver related serious adverse events).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20629075</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Navacerrada F, Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Alonso MR, Alonso-Navarro H, Pilo-de-la-Fuente B, Plaza-Nieto JF, Jim&#x000e9;nez-Jim&#x000e9;nez FJ. Liver toxicity possibly related with ropinirole use in the treatment of restless legs syndrome. Eur J Neurol 2011; 18: e65. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(68 year old woman developed jaundice 3 months after starting ropinirole for restless leg syndrome [bilirubin 11.1 mg/dL, ALT 2399 U/L, Alk P 2020 U/L], resolving within 2 months of stopping and no other cause was found).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21199184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rnsson ES, Bergmann OM, Bj&#x000f6;rnsson HK, Kvaran RB, Olafsson S. Incidence, presentation, and outcomes in patients with drug-induced liver injury in the general population of Iceland. Gastroenterology 2013; 144: 1419-25,1425. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(In a population based study of drug induced liver injury from Iceland, 96 cases were identified over a 2 year period, but none of the 96 were attributed to an agent used to treat Parkinson disease).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drugs for Parkinson's disease. Treat Guidel Med Lett 2013; 11 (135): 101-6. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Concise review of recommendations for therapy of Parkinson disease with description of mechanisms of action, efficacy and adverse events). </italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24165688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hern&#x000e1;ndez N, Bessone F, S&#x000e1;nchez A, di Pace M, Brahm J, Zapata R, A Chirino R, et al. Profile of idiosyncratic drug induced liver injury in Latin America: an analysis of published reports. Ann Hepatol 2014; 13: 231-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 176 reports of drug induced liver injury from Latin America published between 1996 and 2012, none were attributed to an agent to treat Parkinson disease).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24552865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Ropinirole.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chalasani N, Bonkovsky HL, Fontana R, Lee W, Stolz A, Talwalkar J, Reddy KR, et al.; United States Drug Induced Liver Injury Network. Features and outcomes of 899 patients with drug-induced liver injury: The DILIN Prospective Study. Gastroenterology 2015; 148: 1340-52. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 899 cases of drug induced liver injury from the US enrolled in a prospective database between 2004 and 2012, none were attributed to an agent used to treat Parkinson disease).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Ropinirole.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Ropinirole/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Ropinirole: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Ropinirole">Trials on Ropinirole: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
