<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="Streptozocin" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">livertox</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>LiverTox</book-title>
      <subtitle>Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</subtitle>
    </book-title-group>
    <pub-date date-type="pubr" publication-format="electronic">
      <year>2012</year>
    </pub-date>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">Streptozocin</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Streptozocin</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="livertox">LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="Streptomycin" document-type="chapter">Streptomycin</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="livertox" document-id="SubstanceAbuseTreatm" document-type="chapter">Substance Abuse Treatment Agents</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="Streptozocin.OVERVIEW">
        <title>OVERVIEW</title>
        <sec id="Streptozocin.Introduction" sec-type="pubmed-excerpt">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Streptozocin is a unique antineoplastic agent used to treat metastatic pancreatic islet cell carcinoma. Streptozocin has been associated with a high rate of serum enzyme elevation during therapy and to rare instances of severe, clinically apparent acute liver injury.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Streptozocin.Background">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Streptozocin (strep" toe zoe' sin), which was formerly known as streptotozocin, is an antineoplastic antibiotic isolated initially from Streptomyces achromogenes. Structurally, streptozocin is a methylnitrosourea attached to a single molecule of glucosamine and acts as an alkylating agent causing DNA damage and interfering with synthesis. Streptozocin has high affinity for the cell surface glucose transporter GLUT 2 which is highly expressed on beta cells of the islets of Langerhans. As a consequence, streptozocin has differential toxicity to beta cells. In animal models, streptozocin caused loss of pancreatic islet cells, resulting in a decrease in serum insulin and diabetes. Used initially as a means of creating an animal model of type 1 diabetes, streptozocin was later used clinically to treat insulin-secreting islet cell tumors. It was tried, but had little effect in other malignancies. Streptozocin was approved for use in the chemotherapy of metastatic pancreatic islet cell carcinoma in the United States in 1982 and is still used, but largely in combination with other chemotherapeutic agents such as doxorubicin and fluorouracil. In addition, it has been used off label to treat other neuroendocrine neoplasms. Streptozocin is available as a powder for reconstitution in 1 gram vials under the brand name Zanosar. The typical dose is 500 mg/m<sup>2</sup> daily for 5 days every 6 weeks or as 1 gram once weekly intravenously until a remission is achieved or significant toxicity intervenes. Common side effects of streptozocin therapy are nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal discomfort and local infusion site reactions. These immediate reactions can be followed by renal dysfunction (proteinuria, proximal tubular injury, phosphaturia, acute renal failure), bone marrow suppression (anemia, neutropenia) and hepatotoxicity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Streptozocin.Hepatotoxicity">
          <title>Hepatotoxicity</title>
          <p>Serum aminotransferase elevations occur in up to two-thirds of patients treated with streptozocin, but the abnormalities are generally mild, transient and not associated with symptoms or jaundice. Hepatotoxicity is more common with daily dosing and high doses of streptozocin, but with higher doses renal and hematologic toxicities usually overshadow hepatic injury. There have been two reports of rapidly progressive and fatal acute liver failure in patients treated with streptozocin. In one instance, no other chemotherapy was given, in another fluorouracil was coadministered and the patient presented with fever, anuria, acute hepatitis [ALT 1280, bilirubin 11.9, prothrombin index 10%, eosinophils 2600/ &#x000b5;L] at the end of a 5 day course of treatment. In contrast, there have been no individual published case reports of self-limited clinically apparent liver injury attributed to streptozocin, but it has had limited use, as pancreatic islet cell carcinoma and neuroendocrine tumors are rare.</p>
          <p>Likelihood score: D (possible cause of clinically apparent liver injury).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Streptozocin.Mechanism_of_Injury">
          <title>Mechanism of Injury</title>
          <p>Like the renal and bone marrow toxicity, the hepatic injury from streptozocin is likely due to a direct effect of the alkylating agent and its limited uptake by hepatocytes. Higher doses have been shown to cause liver injury in experimental animals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Streptozocin.Outcome_and_Management">
          <title>Outcome and Management</title>
          <p>The severity of the liver injury linked to streptozocin therapy has been generally mild, transient and without symptoms or jaundice. Streptozocin has not been linked to cases of chronic hepatitis or vanishing bile duct syndrome. There is no information on cross sensitivity to hepatic injury between streptozocin and other antineoplastic agents.</p>
          <p>Drug Class: <related-object source-id="livertox" document-id="AntineoplasticAgents">Antineoplastic Agents</related-object></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Streptozocin.PRODUCT_INFORMATION">
        <title>PRODUCT INFORMATION</title>
        <boxed-text position="anchor" id="Streptozocin.BPI" orientation="portrait">
          <p>
            <bold>REPRESENTATIVE TRADE NAMES</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Streptozocin &#x02013; Zanosar&#x000ae;</p>
          <p>
            <bold>DRUG CLASS</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antineoplastic Agents</p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dailymed.nlm.nih.gov/dailymed/search.cfm?labeltype=all&#x00026;query=Streptozocin">COMPLETE LABELING</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>Product labeling at DailyMed, National Library of Medicine, NIH</p>
        </boxed-text>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Streptozocin.CHEMICAL_FORMULA_AND_STRUCT">
        <title>CHEMICAL FORMULA AND STRUCTURE</title>
        <table-wrap id="Streptozocin.T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRUG</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS REGISTRY NUMBER</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOLECULAR FORMULA</th>
                <th id="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRUCTURE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_1" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Streptozocin</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pubchem" xlink:href="sid://134991795">18883-66-4</ext-link>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_3" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C8-H15-N3-O7</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_Streptozocin.T1_1_1_1_4" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Streptozocin_structure.jpg" mime-subtype="jpeg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <alt-text>Streptozocin structure</alt-text>
                  </graphic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Streptozocin.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY">
        <title>ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
        <p>References updated: 23 August 2016</p>
        <ref-list id="Streptozocin.ANNOTATED_BIBLIOGRAPHY.reflist0">
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxic effects of oncotherapeutic and immunosuppressive agents. In, Zimmerman HJ. Hepatotoxicity: the adverse effects of drugs and other chemicals on the liver. 2nd ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1999, pp. 673-708.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Expert review of hepatotoxicity of cancer chemotherapeutic agents published in 1999; mentions that streptozocin can cause elevations in serum aminotransferase levels "but the abnormalities are of little clinical moment").</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">DeLeve LD. Cancer chemotherapy. In, Kaplowitz N, DeLeve LD, eds. Drug-induced liver disease. 3rd ed. Amsterdam, Elsevier, 2013, p. 541-68.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes"> (Review of hepatotoxicity of cancer chemotherapeutic agents; streptozocin is listed as causing transient liver test abnormalities, but not clinically apparent liver injury).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chabner BA, Bertino J, Cleary J, Ortiz T, Lane A, Supko JG, Ryan DP. Cytotoxic agents. Chemotherapy of neoplastic diseases. In, Brunton LL, Chabner BA, Knollman BC, eds. Goodman &#x00026; Gilman's the pharmacological basis of therapeutics. 12th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill, 2011, p. 1698.<annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics).</italic></p></annotation></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Junod A, Lambert AE, Orci L, Pictet R, Gonet AE, Renold AE. Studies of the diabetogenic action of streptozotocin. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 1967; 126: 201-5. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Studies in rats using purified streptozocin demonstrated a highly specific pancreatic beta cell injury with subsequent decrease in serum insulin levels and development of type 1 diabetes; the authors propose its use to develop animal models of diabetes and as therapy of insulin secreting islet cell tumors).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4864021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Murray-Lyon IM, Eddleston AL, Williams R, Brown M, Hogbin BM, Bennett A, Edwards JC, Taylor KW. Treatment of multiple-hormone-producing malignant islet-cell tumour with streptozotocin. Lancet 1968; 2 (7574): 895-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(59 year old woman with metastatic, insulin producing islet cell cancer was treated with 3 infusions of streptozocin and achieved a long term remission).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4176152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Taylor SG 3rd, Schwartz TB, Zannini JJ, Ryan WG. Streptozotocin therapy for metastatic insulinoma. Arch Intern Med 1970; 126: 654-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(70 year old man with metastatic, insulin-producing pancreatic islet cell tumor had a complete remission and correction of hypoglycemia after 5 infusions of streptozocin over a 7 week period).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4319181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sadoff L. Nephrotoxicity of streptozotocin (NSC-85998). Cancer Chemother Rep 1970; 54 (6): 457-9. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 18 patients with various malignancies treated with intravenous streptozocin [2 grams/m2 once weekly], all had some degree of renal tubular toxicity with hypophosphatemia in 14 [5 developing osteomalacia within 6 months], glycosuria in 14, renal tubular acidosis in 10, azotemia in 9, and anuria in 2, one of whom died; 9 patients had AST elevations and 8 hypoalbuminemia "presumably due to liver toxicity").</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4334090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Broder LE, Carter SK. Pancreatic islet cell carcinoma. II. Results of therapy with streptozotocin in 52 patients. Ann Intern Med 1973; 79: 108-18. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Summary of experience using streptozocin for pancreatic islet cell tumors in 52 patients participating in an NCI registry reported a 60% response rate, but toxicities included 7 deaths, 5 from acute renal failure but none from liver injury, despite liver test abnormalities arising in 67% of cases [ALT 16%, AST 27%, Alk P 12%, and bilirubin 4%]; but "hepatic toxicity was difficult to evaluate because most patients had liver metastases").</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4352784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schein P, Kahn R, Gorden P, Wells S, Devita VT. Streptozotocin for malignant insulinomas and carcinoid tumor. Report of eight cases and review of the literature. Arch Intern Med 1973; 132: 555-61. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 8 patients with malignant insulinomas or carcinoid syndrome treated with streptozocin at the NIH Clinical Center, responses occurred only in islet cell tumors and 6 patients had renal toxicity [proteinuria, phosphaturia] which was reversible; and 5 had transient and asymptomatic AST elevations [63-122 U/L]).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4355081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schein PS, O'Connell MJ, Blom J, Hubbard S, Magrath IT, Bergevin P, Wiernik PH, Ziegler JL, DeVita VT. Clinical antitumor activity and toxicity of streptozotocin (NSC-85998). Cancer 1974; 34: 993-1000. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 106 patients with advanced malignancies given streptozocin, responses were not common and limited to lymphomas and islet cell cancer and toxicity included nausea and vomiting [87%] poorly controlled by antiemetics, renal toxicity [28%], and liver enzyme elevations [15%] appearing 1-2 days after the course and rapidly returning to normal without jaundice or symptoms).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4371075</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Loftus L, Cuppage FE, Hoogstraten B. Clinical and pathological effects of streptozotocin. J Lab Clin Med 1974; 84: 407-13. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(One patient with adenocarcinoma and another with islet cell cancer received multiple courses of streptozocin, one dying of renal failure and the second of progressive disease, both having cellular atypia in the liver on autopsies).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4368506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Herbai G, Lundin A. Treatment of malignant metastatic pancreatic insulinoma with streptozotocin. Review of 21 cases described in detail in the literature and report of complete remission of a new case. Acta Med Scand 1976; 200: 447-52. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(55 year old woman with metastatic, insulin secreting islet cell cancer had a remission after 7 infusions of streptozocin; "liver enzyme values and kidney function revealed no abnormalities").</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">189576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hayes JR, O'Connell N, O'Neill T, Fennelly JJ, Weir DG. Successful treatment of a malignant gastrinoma with streptozotocin. Gut 1976; 17: 285-8. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(36 year old woman with gastrin producing islet cell tumor did not respond to streptozocin given intravenously, but did after infusions in the celiac artery during which there was a 3 fold increase in ALT).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">178577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Meyer DJ. Temporary remission of hypoglycemia in a dog with an insulinoma after treatment with streptozotocin. Am J Vet Res 1977; 38: 1201-4. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(7 year old male dog with metastatic insulin secreting pancreatic islet cell tumor developed vomiting followed by proteinuria and liver test abnormalities after a second dose of streptozocin which recurred with another course of treatment [peak ALT 310 and 420 U/L], liver histology at autopsy showing cancer, but no injury to normal liver tissue).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">199092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Oberg K, Bostr&#x000f6;m H, Fahrenkrug J, Dymling JF, Shaffalitsky de Muckadell OB, Lundqvist G. Streptozotocin treatment of a pancreatic tumour producing VIP and gastrin associated with Verner-Morrison syndrome. Acta Med Scand 1979; 206: 223-7. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(57 year old man with metastatic, gastrin and VIP secreting pancreatic islet cell cancer had a long term remission after 3 weekly infusions of streptozocin [2 g each]; no mention of side effects).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">227234</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Moertel CG, Hanley JA, Johnson LA. Streptozocin alone compared with streptozocin plus fluorouracil in the treatment of advanced islet-cell carcinoma. N Engl J Med 1980; 303: 1189-94. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 84 patients with islet cell cancers treated with streptozocin alone or with fluorouracil, response rates were higher with the combination [63% vs 36%] as was survival, while adverse events included marked nausea and vomiting [85% vs 83%], nephrotoxicity [31% vs 29%] and leukopenia [73% vs 5%] and one patient given streptozocin alone developed acute liver failure immediately after therapy and died on day 18, but no further details provided).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6252466</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Weiss RB. Streptozocin: a review of its pharmacology, efficacy, and toxicity. Cancer Treat Rep 1982; 66: 427-38. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Review of the chemistry, pharmacology, efficacy and toxicity of streptozocin mentions that chemical liver dysfunction occurs in 25% of patients, usually 1-2 days after an intravenous course, but the injury is only occasionally severe).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6277485</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Luquel L, Ekherian JM, De Gramont A, Offenstadt G. [Anuria, hepatocellular insufficiency and bone marrow aplasia after the administration of streptozocin and fluorouracil]. Therapie 1988; 43: 125. French. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(52 year old woman developed fever and anuria between days 4 and 6 of a third 5-day course of streptozocin and fluorouracil with rapidly progressive renal, hematologic and liver failure [bilirubin 11.9 mg/dL, ALT 1280, prothrombin index 10%, eosinophils 2600/&#x000b5;L], resulting in death within 8 days; no autopsy performed).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2970126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Moertel CG, Lefkopoulo M, Lipsitz S, Hahn RG, Klaassen D. Streptozocin-doxorubicin, streptozocin-fluorouracil or chlorozotocin in the treatment of advanced islet-cell carcinoma. N Engl J Med 1992; 326: 519-23. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 105 patients with pancreatic islet cell cancer treated with various chemotherapy regimens, streptozocin with doxorubicin yielded the highest rate of tumor regression [69%] and survival rates, while toxicities included severe nausea and vomiting during treatment and delayed renal and hematologic toxicities including one death from sepsis; no mention of ALT elevations or hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1310159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kume E, Fujimura H, Matsuki N, Ito M, Aruga C, Toriumi W, Kitamura K, Doi K. Hepatic changes in the acute phase of streptozotocin (SZ)-induced diabetes in mice. Exp Toxicol Pathol 2004; 55: 467-80. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Study of the direct, acute hepatic toxicity of streptozocin in mice that showed fat droplet accumulation within 24 hours of infusions).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15384252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Aoki T, Kokudo N, Komoto I, Takaori K, Kimura W, Sano K, Takamoto T, et al. Streptozocin chemotherapy for advanced/metastatic well-differentiated neuroendocrine tumors: an analysis of a multi-center survey in Japan. J Gastroenterol 2015; 50: 769-75. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 54 patients with neuroendocrine tumors treated with streptozocin at 5 Japanese cancer centers, 13 [24%] had a partial or complete response and "the adverse event profile was mild and tolerable," with mild liver test abnormalities in only one patient).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25348496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Krug S, Boch M, Daniel H, Nimphius W, M&#x000fc;ller D, Michl P, Rinke A, et al. Streptozocin-Based Chemotherapy in Patients with Advanced Neuroendocrine Neoplasms--Predictive and Prognostic Markers for Treatment Stratification. PLoS One 2015; 10 (12): e0143822. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 77 patients with advanced neuroendocrine tumors seen at a single German referral center between 1995-2013 who were treated with streptozocin with either doxorubicin or fluorouracil [5-FU], the objective response rate was 34% and toxicities were common with serum enzyme elevations in 65% of subjects, which were above 5 times ULN in 5%).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26630134</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="Streptozocin.R23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Clewemar Antonodimitrakis P, Sundin A, Wassberg C, Granberg D, Skogseid B, Eriksson B. Streptozocin and 5-Fluorouracil for the Treatment of Pancreatic Neuroendocrine Tumors: Efficacy, Prognostic Factors and Toxicity. Neuroendocrinology 2016; 103 (3-4): 345-53. <annotation><p><italic toggle="yes">(Among 137 patients with neuroendocrine tumors treated with streptozocin and fluorouracil [5-FU] at a Swedish cancer center between 1981 and 2014, 3% had a complete and 25% a partial response while toxicities were "acceptable"; no mention of ALT elevations or hepatotoxicity).</italic></p></annotation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26279284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Streptozocin.OTHER_REFERENCE_LINKS" sec-type="link-group">
        <title>OTHER REFERENCE LINKS</title>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=search&#x00026;db=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedfilters=true&#x00026;term=(Streptozocin/AE)+AND+Human%5BMH%5D+AND+(drug+induced+liver+injury+OR+jaundice/CI+OR+bile+duct+diseases/CI+OR+liver/DE+OR+liver+diseases/CI)+AND+(%221900/1/1%22%5BEDat%5D%3A%222999/12/31%22%5BEDat%5D)">Recent References on Streptozocin: from PubMed.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=Streptozocin">Trials on Streptozocin: from ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>
            </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
